<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The most Christian Turk: or, a view of the life and bloody reign of Lewis XIV. present King of France Containing an account of his monstrous birth, the transactions that happened during his minority under Cardinal Mazarine; afterwards his own unjust enterprizes in war and peace, as breach of leagues, oaths, &amp;c. the blasphemous titles given him, his love-intrigues, his confederacy with the Turk to invade Christendom, the cruel persecution of his Protestant subjects, his conniving with pirates, his unjustly invading the empire, &amp;c. laying all waste before him with fire and sword, his quarrels with the Pope and Genoieze, his treachery against England, Scotland, and Ireland, the engagements of the confederate princes against him; with all the battles, sieges, and sea fights, that have happened of consequence to this time.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 248 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 95 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51449</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2870A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R216384</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99828115</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99828115</idno>
            <idno type="VID">32542</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51449)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 32542)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1855:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The most Christian Turk: or, a view of the life and bloody reign of Lewis XIV. present King of France Containing an account of his monstrous birth, the transactions that happened during his minority under Cardinal Mazarine; afterwards his own unjust enterprizes in war and peace, as breach of leagues, oaths, &amp;c. the blasphemous titles given him, his love-intrigues, his confederacy with the Turk to invade Christendom, the cruel persecution of his Protestant subjects, his conniving with pirates, his unjustly invading the empire, &amp;c. laying all waste before him with fire and sword, his quarrels with the Pope and Genoieze, his treachery against England, Scotland, and Ireland, the engagements of the confederate princes against him; with all the battles, sieges, and sea fights, that have happened of consequence to this time.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 181, [1] p. : ill., port.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Henry Rhodes, near Bridelan [sic] End, in Fleetstreet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Frontis. = ill.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Louis --  XIV, --  King of France, 1638-1715 --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>France --  History --  Louis XIV, 1643-1715 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:32542:1"/>
            <p>THE MOST <hi>Chriſtian Turk:</hi> Or, a VIEW of the LIFE and Bloody REIGN OF LEWIS XIV. Preſent King of <hi>FRANCE.</hi> CONTAINING An Account of his Monſtrous Birth, the Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſactions that happened during his Minority under Cardinal <hi>Mazarine;</hi> afterwards his own unjuſt En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprizes in War and Peace, as Breach of Leagues, Oaths, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the blaſphemous Titles given him, his Love-Intrigues, his Confederacy with the <hi>Turk</hi> to Invade <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> the cruel Perſecution of his <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant</hi> Subjects, his Conniving with Pirates, his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly Invading the <hi>Empire, &amp;c.</hi> laying all Waſte before him with Fire and Sword, his Quarrels with the <hi>Pope</hi> and <hi>Genoieze,</hi> his Treachery againſt <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> the Engagements of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federate Princes againſt him; with all the Battles, Sieges, and Sea Fights, that have happened of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence to this Time.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Henry Rhodes,</hi> near <hi>Bride<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an</hi> End, in <hi>Fleetſtreet,</hi> 1690.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:32542:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of Lewis XIV</figDesc>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Behold the Chriſtians Scourge, by fortune hur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Like Damn'd Pandoras Ao<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> to plague y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. No Leagues nor oath's, bind this Leviathan; With fire and Sword, he madly ruſhes on.</hi>
                  </p>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:32542:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:32542:3"/>
            <p>LICENSED,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ecemb.</hi> 6th. 1689.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:32542:3"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>THE Reader, at firſt View, may ſuppoſe this Hiſtory to be written by ſome prejudiced hand, and therefore it may Savour of too much Partiality; but if he more deliberately conſult the Actions of this Monarch, and the Reflexions the Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt Spirits of <hi>Europe,</hi> and even his own Subjects have made upon them, we hope the Cenſure may paſs over us. For there be few who allow him not the Epithet of, <hi>Troubler of the Peace of Europe;</hi> in which leaſt Part of the Earth, he has cauſed more Blood to be ſhed ſince his mounting the Throne of <hi>France,</hi> than many Ages before had ſeen, and made ſo many Towns and Villages ſink in Fire, that no barbarous Nation dares venture to reckon with him on that ſcore. <hi>Nero</hi> was a <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:32542:4"/>and yet we have him painted in the blackeſt ſhape, for ſetting Fire to <hi>Rome,</hi> and Perſecuting the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians.</hi> What then could have been expected from thoſe Hiſtorians, had they been to ſet forth the Actions of <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. who is ſtyled, <hi>The Moſt Chriſtian King,</hi> who has not only Deſtroyed one Town or City, but laid whole Countries and Provinces Waſte, with Fire and Sword, Perſecuted and Deſtroyed a Million of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and joined with <hi>Infidels,</hi> to bring Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction even upon <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> it ſelf; and, as he Phraſes it, <hi>Scorning to be a Slave to his Word,</hi> has counted the moſt ſacred Leagues and Oaths as Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fles, to be made and broken at pleaſure, or things only framed to ſerve his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and no longer durable than his Intereſt requires. Therefore we hope the Candid Reader will not impute i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> too great a Boldneſs in a Hiſtorian of theſe times, to lay down in a brief, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> compact <hi>Series,</hi> undeniable Truths, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> have attended his Birth and Reign.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="biography">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:32542:4"/>
            <head>A VIEW of the LIFE and ACTIONS OF LEWIS XIV. The preſent King of <hi>France, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1-50" type="pages">
               <p>NOT doubting but many are unacquainted with the Life and Actions of <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. of <hi>France,</hi> eſpecially as to ſundry Periods and Particulars; we have undertaken to compile what has materially happened relating to that Prince, who has for many Years, but eſpecially of late, made ſuch a noiſe and bluſter in the World, to the damage and diſturbance of all Chriſtendom, and has, as it were, fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted himſelf with Chriſtian Blood.</p>
               <p>After a tedious War between <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain</hi> (which began in the Reign of <hi>Henry</hi> IV. and continued by Truces and Intervals in the Reign of <hi>Lewis</hi> XIII.) nothing was thought more Expedient to put a ſtop to the Progreſs of thoſe
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:32542:5"/>Miſeries that equally afflicted both King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, than a Match; and, both Parties agreeing, a Marriage was made between <hi>Lewis</hi> XIII. (ſtyled by ſome <hi>The Juſt</hi>) and <hi>Anne</hi> of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> the <hi>Infanta</hi> of <hi>Spain:</hi> But although they were both in the Flower of Youth, they deceived for a long time the Expectation of the world, living together in mutual Society Twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty-three Years, without any Appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the Queen's ever being with Child. Inſomuch, that <hi>France</hi> and all <hi>Europe</hi> ſuſpected one or both of them Defective or Stiril; but at the end of theſe Years, when all were out of hopes, a Crotchet came into the Queen's Head, (ſuppoſed to be put into it by Cardinal <hi>Mazarine,</hi> who Ruled all at Court) To go in Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion barefooted to the Chapel of the <hi>Virgin Mary</hi> near <hi>Paris,</hi> whom the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts hold for a very <hi>Lucina,</hi> to demand of her a Son and Heir to the Crown of <hi>France.</hi> And indeed, when a Man ſends his Wife abroad to ask for a Child, 'tis but juſt ſhe ſhould bring one home with her, if ſhe can get it. But, to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. As if this, as a Miracle, was to be aſcribed to the <hi>Bleſſed Virgin,</hi> and an Effect of the Anſwer of the Queen's Prayers; according to the time of Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:32542:5"/>the Queen was brought to bed of a Son in <hi>September,</hi> in the Year One thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſix hundred thirty and eight. And, that the Miracle might be increaſed, or the better to huſh ſome Scruples and Doubts in Court, the Parliament of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris</hi> welcomed him into the World with the Salutation of <hi>Dieu donne,</hi> or <hi>Given of God;</hi> conceiving a Birth, as indeed all <hi>Europe</hi> did, (though perhaps in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſenſe,) to be Miraculous, after ſo many Years paſſing over without any Child, and the Father at that time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Indiſpoſed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Some things were whiſpered abroad at the Birth of this Prince, and although <hi>Mazarine</hi> laboured to ſtill them, yet notwithſtanding ſeveral of the Blood-Royal (who had promiſed themſelves great Advantages upon the Death of <hi>Lewis</hi> XIII. who appeared to them very Infirm, as well in Body as Mind,) could not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear ſpeaking aloud. And as a preſage of Cruelty, (as it happened to our King <hi>Richard</hi> III. of <hi>England,</hi> and others who have delighted in Blood,) This Prince, contrary to the Rules of Nature, was born with long and ſharp Teeth; which made many of the Grandees of <hi>France</hi> look upon ſo unuſual an Accident, as the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:32542:6"/>fore-runner of ill Luck to the World; and upon that conſideration Monſieur <hi>Baſſam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peire,</hi> a very Judicious Man, and a great Favourite of the Father, wrote to the Biſhop of <hi>Greenoble</hi> in theſe Words:</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>My Lord,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>
                        <hi>IN my laſt I gave you the good News of the Queen's being brought ſafe to Bed of a</hi> Dauphin. <hi>All that I tell you at preſent is, that her Majeſty Recovers every Day, and the Child is ſtrong and luſty, and ſeems to promiſe a long Life. There is one thing of him much taken notice of by ſome, That his Gums have Teeth pointing out already, and there is ſcarce a Woman that can ſuffer him to ſuckle. He ſucks ſo eagerly, that he brings Blood with his Milk; and, upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, he has had two Nurſes changed al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready. I pray God this may not be an ill Omen to</hi> France. <hi>We need Princes of a healing and mild Temper, Corroſives not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing with the good of this Monarchy. The Prince is to be named</hi> Lewis Dieu donne, (Given of God,) <hi>as his Majeſty was plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed yeſterday to declare in Council. I am,</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <salute>My Lord,</salute>
                        <signed>Your very humble Servant, Baſſampeire.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:32542:6"/>
               <p>This Letter is found in the <hi>Cologne</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of <hi>Mareſchal Baſſampeire</hi>'s Memoirs, page 134. in <hi>French.</hi> But to return:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lewis</hi> XIII. made great Joy for the Birth of this Son, and all <hi>France</hi> ſhined with Fires of Triumph. And no ſooner was he Chriſtened, but he was Inaugu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated into his Principality, as <hi>Dauphin</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> and had given him his Officers and Attendents; the chief of which were his Governeſs, a Lady of a Maſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line Spirit, and <hi>Hardovine de Perefexi,</hi> who ſince obtained to be Biſhop of <hi>Rhodes,</hi> and after that Archbiſhop of <hi>Paris.</hi> This Man ſerved in the nature of his Tutor, being very cunning and politick.</p>
               <p>Whilſt <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. lay in the Cradle, as we may term it, nothing of Weight or Moment can be expected. But ſcarce was he capable of diſtinguiſhing Right from Wrong, before the Sceptre of <hi>France</hi> dropp'd into his Hand: For <hi>Lewis</hi> XIII. declining more and more, at the End of Four Years and a few Months af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Birth of this Son, left the Stage of this World to ſleep with his Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors. He was the Eldeſt Son of <hi>Henry</hi> IV. of the Houſe of <hi>Bourbon,</hi> to whom the Houſe of <hi>Valois</hi> had given Place, by the Death of <hi>Henry</hi> III. who was ſlain
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:32542:7"/>by one <hi>Clement,</hi> a <hi>Jocobine Monk,</hi> with a Conſecrated Dagger, in his Tent, when ſurrounded by his Army. His Mother was <hi>Mary de Medicis,</hi> of the Houſe of <hi>Medici</hi> of <hi>Florence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The King, before his Death, publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Declaration, bearing Date <hi>April</hi> 12. 1643; by Virtue of which he appointed the Queen as Regent during the Minority of his Son, as likewiſe Governeſs of the Kingdom; and the Duke of <hi>Orleance</hi> was made her Lieutenant. The Chief of the Council, were the Prince of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de,</hi> and Cardinal <hi>Mazarine,</hi> the latter ſwaying all with the Queen, Monſieur <hi>Seguire,</hi> Chancellor of <hi>France,</hi> Monſieur <hi>Bauthlier,</hi> and Monſieur <hi>Chauvigny:</hi> And the Conduct of the Army on Foot, was given to the Duke of <hi>Enguin,</hi> after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Prince of <hi>Conde.</hi> So that <hi>Lewis</hi> XIII. giving up the Ghoſt on the Four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth of <hi>May</hi> 1643. this Order pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented the Conteſts that would have happened in the Court about Priority. However a Calm did not enſue; for the King was no ſooner in his Grave, but Diſcontents, that in reſpect to him ſeemed ſtifled, broke out; both People and Grandees being diſſatisfied with the Cardinal's management of Affairs, and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:32542:7"/>too great Influence upon the Queen, who Acted all by his Advice; and he being an <hi>Italian,</hi> proceeded to impoſe an <hi>Italian</hi> Government in many things, which were highly diſguſted. So that they proclaimed their diſpleaſures at the Head of an Army, with the Noiſe of Trumpets, Drums, and the thundering of Cannon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of which the <hi>Spaniards</hi> taking the Advantage, endeavoured to enlarge their Dominions in the <hi>Low Countries,</hi> where <hi>Don Franciſco de Melo</hi> the <hi>Vice-Roy,</hi> beſieged <hi>Rocroy;</hi> but his Army was beaten off by the Duke of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guin,</hi> General of the <hi>French</hi> Forces, and a conſiderable Defeat given them, which happened ſix days after <hi>Lews</hi> XIV. came to the Throne. And to fluſh him with this Succeſs, the Colours taken were ſpread before him at <hi>Paris,</hi> and ſeveral Applauſes of Triumph made. And, to ſay true, this Victory proved a Check to <hi>Spain,</hi> and gave the <hi>French</hi> Army an Opportunity to enter into their Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories, and take ſeveral Towns and Fortreſſes, as <hi>Maubeuge, Borlemont, Aim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merikt, Binch,</hi> and <hi>Thionville,</hi> with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. Yet the ſmall Caſtle of <hi>Cirke,</hi> ſtopped the Courſe of the <hi>French,</hi> who before rolled on like a Torrent, to the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:32542:8"/>endangering of all <hi>Flanders.</hi> But they had not the like Succeſs in <hi>Germany;</hi> fore there the Mareſchal <hi>de Gu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>briant,</hi> General of the <hi>French</hi> Forces, was ſlain, and his Army worſted, with the loſs of a great many brave Men, which drew off <hi>Enguin</hi> from <hi>Flanders.</hi> But how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, the War ceaſed not, for the War with <hi>Spain</hi> engaged moſt of the Princes of <hi>Europe</hi> in the Quarrel. The Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets carried the Noiſe of War round the Borders of <hi>Savoy,</hi> as likewiſe in <hi>Italy, Navar, Catalonia, Germany, Alſatia, Flanders,</hi> and other Places. Nor were the Seas free from Blood; for the Duke of <hi>Breze,</hi> being Admiral for the <hi>French</hi> in the <hi>Straights,</hi> he twice engaged the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Fleet. Nor did this War end without Rivers of Blood, Burnings, Plunderings, and great Devaſtations; and then the Miſery it had occaſioned in <hi>Europe</hi> moved the Princes to ſend their <hi>Plenepotentiaries</hi> to <hi>Munſter,</hi> to compoſe the Differences, and agree a general Peace. For the Countries were ſo wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted and Impoveriſhed in many Places, that more died by Famine, than the Sword; ſo that <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. began early to build his aſpiring Greatneſs upon Ruine and Deſolation, which threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:32542:8"/>the World with a turbulent Prince.</p>
               <p>To this Treaty, which was abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly neceſſary for the preventing an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Famine, the Queen Regent of <hi>France</hi> ſent the Count <hi>d' Avaux,</hi> and Monſieur <hi>Servien,</hi> to manage the Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of <hi>France;</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Longue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ville</hi> ſoon after followed them. So that, after many Debates, and the Interpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the unintereſted Princes, on the Twenty fourth of <hi>October</hi> 1648. a Peace was concluded, and the Monarchs of <hi>Europe</hi> agreed to lay down their Arms, that Plenty might be reſtored by Peace. And this had been done ſooner, had not the <hi>French,</hi> according to their accuſtom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Manner, (even in the midſt of a Treaty, when others depending upon the publick Faith thought themſelves ſecure,) ſurprized ſeveral Places, and ſuddenly brought their Arms into <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many, Lorrain, Flanders, Catalonia,</hi> and <hi>Italy</hi> at once; as they did early in the <hi>Spring,</hi> 1645. which ſo exaſperated the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> that they requited it before the Peace was concluded, by ſetting upon the <hi>French</hi> Fleet over againſt <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,</hi> putting it to Flight, with the loſs of a great many Men, and ſome Veſſels; the Admiral being killed with
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:32542:9"/>a Cannon Bullet, and the Mareſchal <hi>de Gaſſion,</hi> a great General of <hi>France,</hi> as he laid Siege to <hi>Lens,</hi> was wounded, and being carried to <hi>Arras,</hi> there died; and the <hi>Spaniards</hi> recovered many conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Towns in <hi>Flanders</hi> and other Places, as <hi>Fuens, Courtray,</hi> and <hi>Lens;</hi> and the <hi>French</hi> Army ſuffered very much. However, the Peace held not in <hi>France;</hi> for the Prince of <hi>Conde,</hi> with divers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the Firſt Quality, being grieved that <hi>Mazarine</hi> (once a poor Prieſt and of mean Birth) ſhould play the King of <hi>France,</hi> making his young Pupil, <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. do what he pleaſed, Impoveri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing likewiſe the Kingdom, by ſending vaſt Treaſures into <hi>Italy,</hi> to enrich his poor Kindred; inſomuch, that his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who had never ſeen ſuch Summs before, imagined it rained Gold in <hi>France:</hi> Theſe things, I ſay, and the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolence of that proud Prieſt, made them take up Arms to Reform Abuſes in the Government, publiſhing their <hi>Manifeſto's</hi> to juſtifie their Proceedings, and remove the <hi>Cardinal</hi> from the Young King. So that the great City of <hi>Paris</hi> declared for them, reſolving to defend their Intereſt to the utmoſt, as did many other Towns. Inſomuch, that the Crown
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:32542:9"/>was viſibly at Stake; nor could the <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal</hi>'s Policy have ſaved it, had not the Courage and prudent Conduct of the Mareſchal <hi>de Turin</hi> put a ſtop to the Progreſs of their Arms, whereby he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a great Inſtrument of keeping <hi>Lewis the Great</hi> in his Throne, who elſe had by this time been Little and Inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnificant. But in what manner he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quited him, the Sequel will demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate.</p>
               <p>The Prince of <hi>Conde,</hi> after much Blood-ſhed in an inteſtine War, retrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into <hi>Flanders,</hi> with divers of his Party, who would not leave him, and there was ſet at the Head of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Forces. Whereupon Hoſtilities enſued, and the <hi>Spaniards</hi> recovered a great many of the Towns that had been taken from them. So that where Force could not prevail, Inſinuation and Flattery took place, and at laſt the Prince was gained upon to return Home, as did the Dukes of <hi>Conti</hi> and <hi>Longueville,</hi> being highly Careſſed; and a Pardon was publiſhed to all that had been in the Civil War; and <hi>Lewis,</hi> who hitherto had acted no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing memorable in his own Perſon, being arrived at the Thirteenth Year of his Age, <hi>Anno</hi> 1651, he was declared
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:32542:10"/>to be of ſufficient Years to take upon him the Government, and to act in Perſon, which Declaration was approved by the <hi>Parliament</hi> of <hi>Paris,</hi> and Proclaimed throughout the Kingdom. Yet the War continued with <hi>Spain,</hi> and many Battels were fought, and Towns loſt and won, things being carried on with various Succeſs. So that the King, that he might ſay he had been on Horſe-back, got up at the Head of his Troops, to ſhew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to the People, which did indeed give a little hopes to thoſe that were ready to revolt, that things might go better than they had done. But how they were miſtaken, will appear in its proper place.</p>
               <p>In the Year 1654 great Preparations were made to Crown <hi>Lewis</hi> King of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Navar,</hi> and on the Fourth of <hi>June</hi> the Court arrived at <hi>Rhemes,</hi> and was received by about Two thouſand of the Citizens on Horſeback, about a League from that place; to which was made a Guard of about Five thouſand of the Inhabitants in Arms, and the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urbs were crouded with the Soldiery. At the Entry were divers Triumphal Arches, beautified with golded Lilies, and many flattering Devices, the Streets
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:32542:10"/>being hung with Tapeſtry, and other Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments. And upon his approach the Cannons were thundred off, and volleys of ſmall Shot diſcharged; and the Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of the City taking him for ſome petty Deity, fell on their Knees, and in that poſture preſented him the Silver Keys of the Town: And Cardinal <hi>Mazarine</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the Church of <hi>Noſtrodame</hi> with the Clergy, the King alighted there. The Biſhop of <hi>Soiſſons</hi> officiated in the ſtead of the Archbiſhop of <hi>Rhemes,</hi> who was a little before dead, the Biſhop of <hi>Caeſaria</hi> being his Coadjutor. The Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of <hi>Noyon</hi> and <hi>Beauvais</hi> attended in their Pontificals, the firſt making an O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, in which he gave the King many flattering Epithets, ſcarce due to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Man. However, knowing that Air of Vanity poſſeſſed his Mind, that makes him value himſelf much upon his own Praiſes, nothing was omitted that a Court-paraſite could induſtriouſly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce. Then the Archdeacon did the like, and the Deacon gave him a <hi>Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal</hi> to kiſs, who kneeled down upon two Velvet Cuſhions, placed on a Foot-cloath under a Canopy of State; and from thence he went unto the Choire to aſſiſt at the <hi>Te Deum,</hi> and the <hi>Veſpers</hi> were performed in Muſick.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:32542:11"/>
               <p>The <hi>Veſpers</hi> over, he went to the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop's Palace, which was prepared to receive him; and the next day the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronation was Solemnized with great Pomp, the Queen-Mother of <hi>England,</hi> and the Dukes of <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Glouceſter</hi> being preſent. And there he was annointed with the <hi>Holy Oil,</hi> which the Prieſt makes the ignorant People believe, was miraculouſly ſent from Heaven, on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to annoint their Kings, that they may be the more Dreaded and Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renced.</p>
               <p>And now this ſpruce young <hi>Monſieur</hi> being on the Throne, began to make ſome Figure in the World, though he ſtill acted by others Heads and Advice. And to give the World a proof of <hi>French</hi> Fidelity, he clapp'd up a Peace, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to all Mens Expectation, with <hi>Oliver Cromwell,</hi> the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Protector, at the time when King <hi>Charles</hi> II. with his two Brothers were at the <hi>French</hi> Court, and had been promiſed, not only Protection, but alſo aid to regain the uſurped King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland, &amp;c.</hi> Nor was this all, but he procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded more treacherouſly with his near Kinſmen; for in the Treaty, amongſt other things, there was an Article, to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:32542:11"/>Baniſh them <hi>France,</hi> and its Territories. Of which King <hi>Charles</hi> having private Notice, and finding it fruitleſs to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain where the Royal engagement was ſo little regarded, to avoid a ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious Expulſion, with generous diſdain he turned his Back upon that ungrateful Court, and with his faithful Followers, as Prince <hi>Rupert,</hi> and other Nobles, he retired into <hi>Germany,</hi> and was there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived with all imaginable Joy, and found amongſt Strangers that Reception, without any promiſe or word given, which his Couſin of <hi>France</hi> had ſo gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly promiſed, and afterward ſo baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly denied. But his Brothers, the Dukes of <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Glouceſter,</hi> ſtayed behind; the firſt having a Command in the Army, under Mareſch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l <hi>de Turin,</hi> againſt the <hi>Spaniards.</hi> But that weighed nothing; for the League being made, he was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered to be Packing. Nay, it went ſo far, that a Meſſage was ſent to their Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, though Daughter to <hi>Henry the Great</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> to be gone; but ſhe ſent Word, <hi>That ſhe knew her Right to be in</hi> France, <hi>if the King knew not what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed to his Dignity; and that a Daughter of</hi> Henry <hi>IV. from whom he was deſcended, and held the Crown, was not ſo eaſily ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:32542:12"/>from her Native Country.</hi> This re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Anſwer of the Queen's, made <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. diſſemble the Matter, and her ſtay was winked at, though not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved.</p>
               <p>Here you may ſee <hi>French</hi> Faith to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed Princes, who though never ſo near Ally'd to that King, could obtain Refuge no longer than his Intereſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved him to break his Promiſes. And this early beginning has been very much improved, as will appear in the Series of this Hiſtory.</p>
               <p>The League Offenſive and Defenſive being made with <hi>England</hi> againſt <hi>Spain,</hi> Six thouſand Men were ſent into <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> who beat the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> and took <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> whilſt the <hi>French,</hi> in a manner, ſtood ſtill, and looked on. For, as an Hiſtorian of their own truly has it, <q rend="margQuotes">Though <hi>France</hi> abound with Men, it is wont to make uſe of the Valour of its Neighbours in all Wars againſt Strangers. For it hath (continues he) been found by Experience, That the <hi>French</hi> are only for the firſt Onſet, but cannot abide, nor weather ſo many Diſcouragements as the <hi>Engliſh, Scots,</hi> and <hi>Switzers</hi> can in War. Beſides, their Foot are not to be compared to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:32542:12"/>Strangers, therefore they may aſcribe their moſt difficult Conqueſts to their Money, and the Valour of the <hi>Engliſh, Scotch, Iriſh,</hi> and <hi>Switzers.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>According to the Treaty, <hi>Dunkirk</hi> was ſecured by the <hi>Engliſh.</hi> For the crafty <hi>Protector</hi> not being ignorant of the Falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of the <hi>French</hi> Court, had given ſecret Orders to <hi>Lockhart,</hi> who Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded in Chief, immediately upon ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render to enter it, and Poſt his Men there, and even to diſpute it with the <hi>French,</hi> if it was not quietly put into their Hands. However, though <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarine</hi> and his Pupil had a great Mind to this ſtrong and important Place, yet at that time they were forced to let it ſlip through their Fingers, as well knowing the <hi>Protector</hi> had a powerful Army on Foot in <hi>England.</hi> But, ſome time after, they found means to Charm it from us with <hi>French</hi> Gold, to the great endama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of our Shipping which Trade on that Coaſt.</p>
               <p>In the Year 1656. the <hi>French</hi> relying upon their own Strength, at the remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Siege of <hi>Valenciennes,</hi> received a great Overthrow. But the <hi>Engliſh</hi> had better Succeſs; for whilſt the <hi>French</hi> ſtood looking on, and concluded it utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:32542:13"/>impoſſible, Sir <hi>Thomas Morgan,</hi> who Commanded the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Forces, Stormed <hi>Mardike,</hi> recovering the Top of the Walls almoſt before they were expected, paſſing through ſhowers of Bullets and Fire, to the Aſtoniſhment both of the <hi>French,</hi> and the Beſieged, and poſſeſſed themſelves of that ſtrong Fortreſs, and after that they ſaved it from a Surprize, attempted by the <hi>Spaniards</hi> in the dead of the Night. And indeed, moſt of the Towns that were taken, during this War, may be juſtly aſcribed to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour; which Valour peradventure <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. may one day Experience in the Heart of <hi>France,</hi> as ſeveral of his Predeceſſors have done.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Spaniards</hi> grown weary of this War, the uſual way of Accommodation was propoſed, <hi>viz.</hi> a Match between the <hi>Spaniſh Infanta,</hi> and the <hi>French</hi> King. This Match was greatly oppoſed by <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarine,</hi> who concluded, if a Peace enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and the King gave himſelf up to the Embraces of a Young Wife, his Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity would be leſſened. But the Queen-Mother declared reſolutely for it; ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>That whether he would or no, it ſhould be done; for that her Son ſhould marry one of her Kinſwomen.</hi> But this had like to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:32542:13"/>have broken off by the Sickneſs of <hi>Lewis,</hi> which every one concluded would termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate in his Death. Whereupon Cardinal <hi>Mazarine</hi> knowing the many Villainies he had committed in <hi>France,</hi> and the Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief done by his Evil Council, was about to pack up his Awls and trudge for <hi>Italy;</hi> fearing, if the King ſhould die, he ſhould fall a Sacrifice to the Fury of the Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. And thereupon he ſent a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to the Mareſchal <hi>de Turin,</hi> to know if he might have a ſafe Retreat in the Army, till he could otherways ſhift for himſelf. But that Proteſtant General re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned him ſo cold an Anſwer, that he was put out of all Hopes. However, whilſt he was ſtudying what to do, the King began to recover; and accordingly eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped that Death that threatned him, to be the cauſe of the Death and Ruine of more than a Million of People.</p>
               <p>The King being Recovered, <hi>Mazarine</hi> was ſent to <hi>Bayon,</hi> and <hi>Don Louis d' Ardo de Guſman</hi> came to Saint <hi>Sebaſtians,</hi> the more commodiouſly to treat about the Peace, being conſtituted for that end <hi>Plenepotentiaries.</hi> And accordingly it was concluded on ſundry Articles, to the great Joy of the Frontier-Towns, who by Burning, Plundering, Quartering Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:32542:14"/>and Contributions, were redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to extream Miſery. And <hi>Lewis</hi> ſent a Procurator to <hi>Don Louis d'Ardo,</hi> in his Name to Eſpouſe the <hi>Infanta,</hi> and the Marriage was conſummated at <hi>Fonterabia,</hi> in the preſence of the Court of <hi>Spain;</hi> and the two Kings met in the <hi>Iſle of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference,</hi> ſituate between both Kingdoms, where <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>Spain</hi> was delivered to <hi>Lewis</hi> of <hi>France</hi> as his Wife, and both Kings ſolemnly ſwore to keep and confirm to one another the Treaty of Peace, and the Young Queen entered <hi>Paris</hi> in an open Chariot, ſhining with the Treaſure of both the <hi>Indias.</hi> But Card. <hi>Mazarine</hi> for Grief to ſee his Purpoſe croſſed, as ſome gave out, fell ſick, and died on the Nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth of <hi>March</hi> 1661. to the Joy of all <hi>France;</hi> to whom he had a long time been a Scourge, and inſtilled that Spirit of Cruelty into <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. that has ſince been manifeſted to the World in Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters of Blood.</p>
               <p>This Cardinal had his firſt Riſe under <hi>Richelieu,</hi> the great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ardinal of <hi>France,</hi> and from a mean Birth raiſed himſelf and his Family to the greateſt Dignity <hi>France</hi> could afford a Subject. He was born an <hi>Itaelian,</hi> and by his cunning bore himſelf up in the Favour of this King
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:32542:14"/>and his Father, in ſpight of all the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Opponents he met withal. For be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide the Prince of <hi>Conde,</hi> Duke of <hi>Conti,</hi> and moſt of the Nobles; he ſtood the Envy of the People in general, whom he had ſorely vexed by Taxes and Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. The Court went into Mourning for him, but continued it not long; for, an occaſion of Joy ſoon after made it vaniſh. The Duke of <hi>Orleance</hi> falling in Love with the beautiful Daughter of <hi>Charles</hi> I. of <hi>England,</hi> the Lady <hi>Henrietta,</hi> at the publick Ceremory of that illuſtrious Marriage the Mourning went off.</p>
               <p>Thus far we have traced this Monarch, as we may term it, in his Leading-ſtrings. For the Cardinal, whilſt he lived, had the abſolute Rule of his Mind, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſhare he had in his Body; and from thence we may hitherto conclude him an Engine, that moved by the Dictates of that covetous and ambitious Prelate; but for the future we muſt conſider him moving more directly in his own Sphere. It is obſerved of <hi>Nero,</hi> by <hi>Suetonius</hi> and others, That the beginning of his Reign, was tolerable, and not comparable to thoſe Cruel and Irregular practices that followed, and left a Laſting ſtain upon him to all Poſterity.</p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:32542:15"/>
               <p>Notwithſtanding the terrible Name <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. ſuppoſed to have gained in the year 1662, his Ambaſſador contending with the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Ambaſſador for Prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency, at the Reception of another Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador near the <hi>Tower,</hi> was there wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, had ſeveral of his Horſes, and ſome of his Attendence killed and wounded. For the King of <hi>England</hi>'s Council not undertaking to determine in this Matter, they were left to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpute it; and a Proclamation was put out, forbidding any <hi>Engliſh</hi> to meddle in this Matter, upon great Penalties; ſo that the Ambaſſador of <hi>Lewis the Great</hi> appear'd but very Little, being forced to ſneak to his Lodging by all the by-Ways he could find, though they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to claim Precedency of all the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors of <hi>Europe</hi> unleſs at the Court of <hi>Vienna,</hi> where the Lords of <hi>Auſtria</hi> bear Rule. Yet this made <hi>Monſieur</hi> to ſtorm and bluſter at a ſtrange rate, inſomuch, that the King of <hi>Spain</hi> being of a quiet diſpoſition, and not deſirous to involve himſelf in another War, gave him ſuch ſatisfaction as contented him upon his ſending complaints to <hi>Madrid,</hi> preferring the Quiet of his Kingdoms be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a Punctilio of Honour. Which ſo
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:32542:15"/>puffed up the <hi>Frenchman,</hi> that he had a great Mind to be Quarrelling with <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland;</hi> and not well knowing how to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, he pitched upon a peremptory de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of <hi>Dunkirk</hi> that was then in the Hands of King <hi>Charles</hi> II. This De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand was looked upon by the <hi>French</hi> themſelves as ſo Extravagant, that they could not imagine the <hi>Engliſh</hi> would hearken to the delivery of a place gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the loſs of the Lifes of ſo many brave Men, and extreamly ſtrengthened and fortified, at the Expence of vaſt Treaſure, lying at the ſame time ſo Commodious for Trade, and other Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages.</p>
               <p>The pretences the <hi>French</hi> King made were, That there was an Agreement with <hi>Oliver Cromwell,</hi> that upon the Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a certain Summ of Money, it ſhould be delivered to the <hi>French.</hi> But no body, as we can hear of, was privy to this Contract but himſelf. However, contrary to all Mens Expectation, his <hi>French</hi> Piſtols gained that ſtrong Town, which all the Cannon and Forces of <hi>France,</hi> had the King of <hi>England</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended it, could never have done. But now we Experience the damage of that Overſight, when too Late. For <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kirk</hi>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:32542:16"/>was delivered for Money, and <hi>Lewis</hi> had the unexpected Pleaſure of entering into it in Triumph, on the Second of <hi>December,</hi> in the Year 1662.</p>
               <p>Theſe Succeſſes fluſhed his Ambition to greater Attempts, nothing leſs now than the <hi>Dukedom</hi> of <hi>Lorrain</hi> will ſerve his turn, and thereupon he ſent his cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Sophiſters to wheedle the Duke out of it by Threats and Promiſes. Firſt, That he had an Army ready to fall into it, if it were refuſed. Secondly, That he would conſign him Lands more ſecure in Lieu of it in another place. And, to make the old Duke more fond, promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to declare him Heir to the Crown of <hi>France,</hi> in Caſe the Family of <hi>Bourbon</hi> failed, although there was a <hi>Dauphin</hi> born of the young Queen. Theſe, and other inveiglings between Force and fair Means, wrought ſo powerfully, that the Agreement was made the Sixth of <hi>Febru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary</hi> 1662. and in <hi>March</hi> following con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed in the <hi>Parliament</hi> of <hi>Paris,</hi> to the apparent Wrong of Prince <hi>Charles,</hi> the preſent Duke of <hi>Lorrain;</hi> who, though of years, was no ways conſenting to his Father's Act. And upon this Agreement, the <hi>French</hi> Troops were immediately ſent, who ſeized upon all the Cities and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:32542:16"/>Country of that fertil and ſpacious <hi>Duke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> except <hi>Marſal,</hi> which being gari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned and influenced by the young Prince, oppoſed their Progreſs. This made <hi>Monſieur</hi> ſtorm and immediately he or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered his <hi>Generals</hi> to be ready for an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition, to make War, as he term'd it, for the Glory of his Arms; and came on ſo terribly in the Head of his Forces, that the old Duke, though he repented of what he had done, foreſeeing the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine that would inſue to his People if he oppoſed, and being altogether unfur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, by the ſurprize of his Towns, to Encounter a great Army, thought it his beſt way to ſubmit to his Misfortune. And thereupon, in an humble manner he went to <hi>Metz</hi> in <hi>Lorrain</hi> to excuſe himſelf to <hi>Lewis,</hi> who received the vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable old Man after a haughty manner, and would hear of nothing but the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render of <hi>Marſal;</hi> which not being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to hold out againſt ſuch a powerful Army, as he had brought into the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, it was put into <hi>French</hi> hands on the Third of <hi>September</hi> 1663.</p>
               <p>Much about this time, <hi>Lewis</hi> fell a ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velling, like an Unchriſtian Son, with his <hi>Holy Father</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Manner was thus. <hi>Monſieur de Crequi,</hi> his Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:32542:17"/>in that City, bearing himſelf with too high a hand, and putting A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſes even upon the <hi>Pope</hi> himſelf, it ſo enraged ſome of the <hi>Pope</hi>'s Guards, that (whether willingly, or by chance, remains doubtful) a <hi>Harquibus</hi> was ſhot into his Coach, which wounded ſome of his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants. This Affront made ſuch a noiſe in the Court of <hi>France,</hi> that <hi>Lewis,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of going in Devotion, immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately prepared to make a Proceſſion to <hi>Rome</hi> with his Dragoons, which ſo frighted Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> II. that then held the Chair, that he was forced to ſend and meet his Army with Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation of his Trouble for what had hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened, and that he ſhould have any ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction. This ſtopped his Carier a little, and <hi>Piſa</hi> was pitched upon as the City to examine the matter. And on the Twelfth of <hi>March</hi> 1664. it was agreed between the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Pope</hi>'s Deputies, (a thing that the Pride of the <hi>Popes</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> never ſubmitted to for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Hundred years;) <hi>viz,</hi> that <hi>Flavio Chigi,</hi> the <hi>Pope</hi>'s Nephew, ſhould come to the King, and beg the <hi>Pope</hi>'s Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, (ſo that it ſeems, the <hi>Great Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doner</hi> was forced to creep at this Time for a pardon from one of his Sons.)
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:32542:17"/>And farther, That a Monument ſhould be raiſed in the place where the Affront was done, with an Inſcription, decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Cauſe of its being erected. This was performed, but it did not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie: For whilſt it was a doing, the <hi>French</hi> fell into the <hi>Pope</hi>'s County <hi>Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> of <hi>Avignon,</hi> drove out the Garriſons, and without reſpect to St. <hi>Peter, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-Church,</hi> or Father <hi>Pope,</hi> plundered his Patrimony; for which the <hi>moſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian King</hi> highly applauded them. But ſoon after, the Queen-Mother of <hi>France</hi> died; and now <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. began to take his pleaſure without Regard to the young Queen. Wherefore, though it may be looked upon as a digreſſion, it may not be amiſs to ſee a few of <hi>Lewis the Great's</hi> Intrigues with his Little Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes; for you muſt underſtand, his Inclinations have been as well to Love as Glory.</p>
               <p>Since <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. was Married to <hi>Maria Thereſa</hi> of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> daughter of <hi>Spain,</hi> the firſt Miſtreſs (though the Queen was charming enough, young, brisk, and lively,) that he publickly owned, was Madam <hi>de la Valliere,</hi> and that ſhe might come up the better to his Humour, he made her Ducheſs of <hi>Vau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jour.</hi>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:32542:18"/>And although the Queen grew jealous, and the Queen-Mother very much reproved his over-fondneſs of this Woman, yet he little regarded their Reproaches. Whereupon they uſed ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny devices to draw off his Affections, but thoſe not ſucceeding, one <hi>Father A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat,</hi> a Jeſuit, and at that time his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor, was prevailed upon to reprove him. So that he took upon him boldly to repreſent to him the Scandal, and bad Effects ſuch a looſe way of Living occaſioned, by making an ill Impreſſion upon the Minds of the People, and that if, he did not Reform, he muſt enjoin him ſharper Penance at his next Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion. But <hi>the moſt Chriſtian King,</hi> lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſatisfied with this Diſcourſe, coldly replyed, <hi>That he thanked him kindly for his good Advice, and his paſt Service, but that for the future, he would make uſe of no other Confeſſor, but the Parſon of the Pariſh.</hi> And ſo the old Fellow was turned out of Service for his Ill timed Preachment, which made the Society of <hi>Jeſuits</hi> curſe him for being ſo ſcurvy a Politician, on ſuch an occaſion; which he might have Improved to their Advantage. But however, though this was Caſhiered, yet others of the Society, more cunning
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:32542:18"/>and facetious, made a ſhift to creep in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the King's Boſome, making their own Advantages by embroiling a great part of <hi>Europe.</hi> And the more to flatter his Ambition, contrary to the Rules of their Order they took away the Name of <hi>Jeſus</hi> from off the Gates of one of their Colleges in <hi>Paris,</hi> and placed the King's Name inſtead of it, which occaſioned this Diſtich.</p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Abſtulit hinc <hi>Jeſum,</hi> poſuit<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> 
                        <hi>Inſignia Regis</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Impia Gens, Alium non habet Illa <hi>Deum.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>They Jeſus name have ta'en from their Aboad,</l>
                     <l>And plac'd the King's, he only is their God.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>After a long Careſſing of this Miſtreſs, (by whom he had ſome Children, and is ſaid, in a great Immergency, to play the Man-Midwife to one of them himſelf,) and Entertaining her with all the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Gallantry of his Kingdom, he grew weary of thoſe Beauties-himſelf had ſullied, and ſearched for thoſe that were freſher. Whereupon he caſt his Eyes upon Madam <hi>Monteſpan,</hi> who char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med his Affections a very conſiderable time; which ſo vexed the former to ſee her ſelf outed, that ſhe went into a Nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nery,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:32542:19"/>and there turned Penitent, leaving the King to take his full ſwinge with <hi>Monteſpan,</hi> who made her Advantage by preferring all her Kindred to places of Honour and Truſt. Her Brother, who would otherways have never deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved it, was made <hi>Duke,</hi> and <hi>Peer General</hi> of the Galleys, and a <hi>Mareſchal</hi> of <hi>France.</hi> Theſe Qualifications rendered him of the greateſt Quality for a Subject in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, which cauſed a pretty Retort, when one was comparing this <hi>Vivone</hi> with <hi>Feillade, viz.</hi> that the laſt was made <hi>Mareſchal</hi> by the Sword, and the firſt by the Scabbard. Yet many were of Opinion that the Kings paſſion was not ſo great for <hi>Monteſpan</hi> as he pretended; for if fame be true, one Madam <hi>Du Lude,</hi> a Nun of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> came in with her for a ſhare, though privately, to ſave the Credit of that Order; which occaſioned theſe following Verſes.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>La Valliere</hi> of common Race,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Monteſpan</hi> of Noble was,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Du Lude</hi> a pious Nun,</l>
                  <l>All for Miſtreſſes are Known;</l>
                  <l>If you'd know the Reaſon why</l>
                  <l>Theſe three his Favourites he creates,</l>
                  <l>Our great Prince has a mind to try</l>
                  <l>To <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nite the three Eſtates.</l>
               </q>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:32542:19"/>
               <p>But his mind continued wavering; for not long after <hi>Monteſpan</hi> was laid aſide, and <hi>Madamoſel de Fontagne</hi> was taken in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Favour; but ſhe lived not long after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, as being ſuppoſed to have received a Doſe from her ſhe had rivalled: and the Prince of <hi>Marſilack,</hi> who brought her to the King, was, for finding the Game ſo well, made <hi>Chief Huntſman</hi> of <hi>France.</hi> To her ſucceeded <hi>Madam de Maintenon,</hi> who joining with <hi>Monteſpan,</hi> as a Teſtimony of their Repentance, built the Abby of St. <hi>Cry,</hi> by ſome called the <hi>Seraglio,</hi> to train up young Women: Which occaſioned this Epigram;
<q>
                     <l>Two of fair <hi>Venus</hi>'s Votaries,</l>
                     <l>Their Souls with holy Zeal inflam'd,</l>
                     <l>Have founded two new Nunneries</l>
                     <l>With the Revenues by their Pleaſure gain'd.</l>
                     <l>But, without Miracle, they ſeem</l>
                     <l>To be in a pitious taking,</l>
                     <l>Since that that founded and ſupporteth them</l>
                     <l>Is now in a continual ſhaking.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>But to cut off this Digreſſion, if it may properly be ſo termed, as to what is conſiſtent to Hiſtory of this Nature, we find that <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. was not ſatisfied with having <hi>Dunkirk</hi> delivered to him;
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:32542:20"/>but dreading the Growing Greatneſs of his <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Neighbours, <hi>viz. England,</hi> and the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces,</hi> by ſome extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Contrivance they were ſet toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the Ears, and engaged in an Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy War, occaſioning much blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed on either Part, whilſt <hi>France</hi> was a looker on. But when that Court per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the <hi>Dutch</hi> inclined to a Peace, as being wearied with an Expenſive and hazardous War; then, and not till then, the <hi>French</hi> put in to aſſiſt the <hi>States,</hi> to keep the flame ſtill blazing; that ſo the two moſt powerful Nations at Sea under Heaven, might weaken each other, and thereby lay themſelves more open and expoſed to the Projects of <hi>France,</hi> which has but too apparently been manifeſted. For, although in the Year 1666. the <hi>French</hi> Fleet was abroad, yet it was on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in a bravado; for we could never learn from any hand, That that Fleet (though the Ships carried many terrible Names, as <hi>Tempeſt, Lightning, Thunder,</hi> &amp;c.) effected any thing; but rather ſtood as a looker on, whilſt the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> battered each other; though at the ſame time they might have come up, the Wind being favourable. Nor were the <hi>Engliſh</hi> better ſerved when they
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:32542:20"/>were on their part, as will hereafter ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear: So that if there was not (as let thoſe believe who are very credulous, if they pleaſe,) a deſign in it for the weakning the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Intereſt; at leaſt we may conclude, That this produced nothing as to the Reputation of making War, for the Glory of the Arms of <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. However, after ſeveral Fights, and much Blood-ſhed, though little or none of the <hi>French</hi> in theſe Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, upon more deliberate Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, a Peace was concluded in 1668. Yet in this Interim, there are other Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks than what we have mentioned.</p>
               <p>The <hi>French,</hi> during this <hi>Naval</hi> War, had not the Courage to make any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent upon <hi>England,</hi> or any of the Three Kingdoms; but upon our People in the <hi>Weſt-Indias</hi> their Treachery appeared in a Crimſon dye, eſpecially in the Iſland of St. <hi>Chriſtophers;</hi> where the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Engliſh,</hi> as planters of that Iſland, had lived together in neighbourly Love, as every one thought, for many years, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciprocally and with much ſatisfaction enjoying the Fruits of their Labour. But upon Notice of this War, and the iuſtigation of <hi>French</hi> Popiſh Cruelty, they fell unawares upon the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:32542:21"/>Maſſacred them without mercy, or ſo much as giving them time to think of a future State, ſeizing upon their Goods and Poſſeſſions, to the eternal Infamy of the <hi>French</hi> Nation. They likewiſe ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed upon the Iſlands of <hi>Antigo,</hi> Saint <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtach,</hi> and <hi>Tobago.</hi> Yet all this while the Court of <hi>France</hi> pretended they had no Quarrel againſt the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> but what they did was in the defence of their Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, pretending a great Kindneſs for the <hi>Dutch;</hi> who ſince have experienced it to their no ſmall Detriment, which however may in time be repay'd. How the <hi>Port</hi> at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and the <hi>French</hi> Court have hitherto taken equal Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, never obſerving any Obligation longer than it tended to their Intereſt, we leave the World to judge.</p>
               <p>This was not all the deſign of <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. for by embroiling <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> he had leiſure (notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Peace ſolemnly ſworn to, and concluded with the King of <hi>Spain</hi>) to enter <hi>Flanders,</hi> under Pretence of ſome Particulars not performed, relating to the Contract of Marriage with the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fanta.</hi> Nor could his Queen perſuade him to reaſon, but in <hi>May</hi> 1667. he entered <hi>Flanders</hi> with an Army of 30000.
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:32542:21"/>Horſe and Foot; upon which unexpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted ſurprize, many of the Garriſons drew off, as <hi>Armantiers, Labaſſee, Conde, Bergues, S. Guilhain,</hi> and <hi>Furves;</hi> of which the Mareſchal <hi>d' Aumont</hi> took Poſſeſſion. And the better to ſecure the Frontiers, <hi>Lewis</hi> commanded <hi>Charleroy</hi> to be Rebuilt and Fortified. Many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Towns of Note were taken, being rather got by ſurprize than by true Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour on the part of the <hi>Franch:</hi> For many of them, in this ſecurity, were unprovided of many things that might have contributed to a longer Defence, or ſecured them from falling into the Hands of the Invader. <hi>Lille</hi> was the only Place that made a reſolute Defence; for in this place was a Governour of great Repute, under whoſe Command was a Garriſon of 4000 Foot, and 800 Horſe: Nor was it gained but by a bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Siege, when the Governour found all hopes of expecting Relief vain, through the want of timely Notice of the <hi>French</hi> King's Intentions to Invade thoſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces, or the unpreparedneſs of the Court of <hi>Spain</hi> to ſend an Army to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Torrent of a <hi>French</hi> Power, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantageouſly poured into thoſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries. The Town Surrendered upon
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:32542:22"/>Articles on the 28. of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> and <hi>Lewis,</hi> who then was in the Army, entered into it. Notwithſtanding, the <hi>Spaniards</hi> during the Siege made ſome Attempts to Relieve it, but, their Forces being ſmall, they were fruſtrated.</p>
               <p>In the Year 1668. for the Glory of his Arms, <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. thought of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Enterprize, which was, to take into his Poſſeſſion by Force the <hi>French Comte,</hi> which, as a kind of a <hi>Palatinate,</hi> or ſeparate <hi>Principality,</hi> had enjoyed many Privileges and Immunities; which being altogether unarmed or capable of Defence upon ſuch a Surprize, the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants were forced to ſend to the King's Deputies to treat of Yielding; thereby to prevent the Spoils and Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vage of a Hunger ſtarved Army. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, in the midſt of the Treaty, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanſon</hi> was poſſeſſed by a forced Surren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der on the Sixth of <hi>February. Salines</hi> was alſo Surprized; and many other places not being ſufficiently Garriſoned, or provided with Stores, were obliged to their Gates. <hi>Dole</hi> only was capable of making a ſhew of Reſiſtence; but the <hi>French</hi> Army being numerous, and ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly poſſeſſing themſelves of the Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>works, they were forced to accept of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:32542:22"/>ſuch Terms as were offered by the <hi>French</hi> King, and thereupon they ſent him the Keys of the City.</p>
               <p>It may be gueſſed what little Expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion this Country had of a <hi>French</hi> Army, when in the ſpace of Twelve Days ſo many ſtrong Places Yeilded, that were capable of holding out many Years, had they had timely Notice, and well pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided. But it has ever been obſervable, that this King gains moſt of his Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages by this way, or the force of golden Piſtols, charged into the Governours Pockets.</p>
               <p>The <hi>French</hi> King perceiving that the <hi>Dutch</hi> (weary of his Alliance, who had done ſo little for them, and pretended ſo much,) were inclined to make a Peace, and join with the <hi>Spaniards;</hi> and thinking he had gained ſufficiently, if he could keep what he had got, Overtures of Peace where thereupon propoſed, and <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur Colbert</hi> was ſent to <hi>Aix la Chapelle</hi> to meet the Miniſters of the Mediating Princes. And accordingly the Articles of Peace between <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain</hi> were ſigned on the Sixth of <hi>May,</hi> and made Publick at <hi>Paris</hi> and <hi>Bruſſels.</hi> Yet <hi>Lew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is</hi> was not well pleaſed to be fruſtrated in his Expectation of ſwallowing the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:32542:23"/>
                  <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Provinces, attributing his diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment to the <hi>Dutch;</hi> who declaring for the Intereſt of <hi>Spain,</hi> had obliged him to this Peace. But his Threats were retarded by another Enterprize. It ſo happened, that the <hi>Turks,</hi> with a nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Army, had beſieged the City of <hi>Candia,</hi> ſituate in the Iſland formerly called <hi>Creet,</hi> belonging to the <hi>Venetians:</hi> So that may of the <hi>French</hi> Nobility, who had prepared their Equipages for the enſuing Compaign, and being prevented by the Peace the <hi>French</hi> King was forced to comply withal, went thither, and upon their Return gave an account of the place. Inſomuch that <hi>Lewis</hi> think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to have the Honour of relieving that Bulwork of <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> which had held out a long, doubtful, and bloody Siege, and upon the Event of which the Eyes of all <hi>Europe</hi> were fixed, ſent an Army of <hi>French</hi> men, under the Command of the Dukes of <hi>Beaufort</hi> and <hi>Navailles,</hi> conſiſting of 10000 Men; who, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any detriment, entered that City, which was laid almoſt in Ruines with the Bombs ſhot in by the <hi>Infidels.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, it was concluded in a Council of War, that it could be no longer tena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble without performing ſome extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:32542:23"/>Exploit; and after a farther-Conſult, it was agreed, That a vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Sally ſhould be made, in Order to the raiſing of the Siege.</p>
               <p>The <hi>French</hi> indeed were very forward; and, to give the Duke of <hi>Beaufort</hi> his Due, he behaved himſelf like a man of good Courage and Conduct. The Sally was accordingly made, with great Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, and the <hi>Turks</hi> at firſt were beaten out of their Trenches: But the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> poſſeſſing themſelves of a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gazine of Three hundred Barrels and Sacks of Powder; whether by Matches laid on purpoſe by the Enemy, or fired by chance, it blew up and deſtroyed al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt one whole Regiment, in which it was thought the Duke of <hi>Beaufort</hi> was killed, and buried by the overthrowing of the Earth; for his Body was not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards found. Which terrible thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dercrack ſo diſmayed the <hi>French</hi>-men, who were the foremoſt in the Sally, that they retired in great confuſion, think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by the Earthquake it made, that all the Ground was hollow, and charged with Mines. So that the <hi>Turks</hi> Rallying, and being reinforced with great Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers that came pouring from the Hills, the Belieged were driven into the City,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:32542:24"/>and the <hi>French</hi> never after that could be perſuaded to make any other Sally, or ſo much as to ſtay for the Defence of the Place, although the Governour almoſt with Tears beſought it. But the Duke of <hi>Novailles,</hi> who now Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Chief, pretending Orders from his Maſter, took Shipping, and with thoſe Forces he had left, returned to <hi>France;</hi> which was not for the Glory of the King's Arms. For, had they ſtayed, and done what became Soldiers, that famous City had undoubtedly been ſaved, which by this Defeat, was in a ſhort time after delivered to the <hi>Turks,</hi> with whom <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. has ſince had a better Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence; as will appear in due Place and Order.</p>
               <p>In the year 1669. the Duke of <hi>Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain,</hi> grieved that he had ſo eaſily par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with his Countries, hoping it was not yet too late to retract, he required Aid of the <hi>Emperor,</hi> and King of <hi>Spain,</hi> labouring to engage them againſt <hi>France.</hi> Whereupon <hi>Lewis</hi> ſent the <hi>Mareſchal de Crequi</hi> with an Army of 18000 Men in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Country, who diſmantled and pulled down the Walls of divers Towns, making great Ravagement, though he found little or no oppoſition. For on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:32542:24"/>the little Towns of <hi>Epinal</hi> and <hi>Chate</hi> made ſome ſhew of a Reſiſtence. But there being no Army that could promiſe them Relief, they were compelled to ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render, and the old Duke to fly his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimonial Country, and foregoe thoſe vaſt Promiſes the <hi>French</hi> Court had made him. The Eyes of all <hi>Europe</hi> being up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this unfair dealing, and greatly Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gretting it; to keep the Inhabitants qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et, he ordered they ſhould be treated with ſomewhat more Mildneſs than is uſually obſerved in the <hi>French</hi> Conqueſts, (as they term them, though for the moſt part got by Surprize or Treachery.) And finding the <hi>Hollanders</hi> were no way ſatisfied with his proceedings, (for he had infringed upon their Commerce,) he reſolved to begin firſt; and having viſited and ſtrengthened his Towns in <hi>Flanders,</hi> and upon the Frontiers, he by a ſubtil Negotiation (as ſome Hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans will have it) of <hi>Henrietta,</hi> Ducheſs of <hi>Orleance,</hi> who had an Interview with her Royal Brothers at <hi>Dover,</hi> drew the King of <hi>England</hi> into an Expenſive War againſt the States. But whether by the means of that Princeſs, who died upon her return into <hi>France,</hi> or otherwiſe, we determine not. However, it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:32542:25"/>that great Naval Preparations were made before it was publickly known to what Intent.</p>
               <p>The Ducheſs of <hi>Orleance</hi> dying ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly, and not without Suſpicion of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Practice; the Duke, by the perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. was Married to the Daughter of the Prince <hi>Palatine</hi> of the <hi>Rhine.</hi> Upon which Country no doubt (and it ſince has but too plainly appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) he had an Eye.</p>
               <p>In the Year 1672, on the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>April,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> King's Declaration was put forth, prohibiting all Trade and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce with the <hi>States</hi> of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces.</hi> And, out of a Bravado, he mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched in perſon at the Head of an Army of 150000 Men. By which ſurprizing Invaſion, he like a Torrent carried all before him. So that many looked upon the <hi>Low Countries</hi> to be loſt, if no ſpeedy Stop was put to this Progreſs. But it has always been obſerved, that though the firſt Motions of the <hi>French</hi> are impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, yet the leaſt diſcouragement makes them Recoil. They had on a ſudden filled with their Troops the <hi>Duchy</hi> of <hi>Cleves,</hi> the <hi>Electorate</hi> of <hi>Collen,</hi> the <hi>Duchy</hi> of <hi>Limburg,</hi> the County of <hi>Zutphen, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>treitcht,</hi> and its Territories,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:32542:25"/>with many other places, and got into their hands ſeveral ſtrong Towns; and into this Combination the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> was drawn, who took <hi>Groll</hi> and ſome other places, though not very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable. They paſſed the <hi>Rhine</hi> like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, and did conſiderable damages in ſuch places as were found unprovided, Committing great Outrages. Which ſo puffed up <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. that being return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>Paris,</hi> he was congratulated with Flatteries and Applauſes from all the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties of the Kingdom. And in Imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Heathen Idolaters, the Queen cauſed a Chapel to be built at <hi>Roan,</hi> dedicated to our <hi>Lady of Victories.</hi> The King was ſtyled <hi>the invincible Hero,</hi> though he was always ſo tender of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, that he neither engaged in any Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel or Skirmiſh, or ſeldom came within Cannon ſhot of any place that reſiſted, doing what beſt ſuited his Valour, which has not overmuch of the <hi>Hero</hi> in it. But indeed the Progreſs of his Arms had a Recoil: for the <hi>Provinces</hi> being reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered out of the Amaze this ſudden At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt put them into, and the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> (now King of <hi>England</hi>) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed in his Patrimonial Offices, and honourable Truſts, as <hi>Stadtholder, Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral,</hi>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:32542:26"/>and <hi>General</hi> of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces;</hi> he preſently took the Field with an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of 24000 Men, recovering ſeveral places, and cauſing the <hi>French</hi> to retire, and performing many other Exploits worthy himſelf, and the Glory of his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors. But having taken a view of the <hi>French</hi> King's Affairs hitherto at Land, let us caſt our Eyes a little upon the Ocean</p>
               <p>The <hi>Fleets</hi> being Abroad in <hi>May</hi> 1672. on the 28<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of that Month a ſharp In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement enſued, the then Duke of <hi>York</hi> commanding as Admiral. It continued a long time bloody and doubtful, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring which many brave Men were loſt, as the Earl of <hi>Sandwich,</hi> &amp;c. who would not leave his Ship, though all in Flames, till it was too late to ſuccour him. His Body was found ſloating, and afterward honourably buried; but we cannot learn that the <hi>French</hi> did any thing conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in this Action, or that any more than their Reer-Admiral, <hi>Monſieur de Rabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niere Trees les Bois,</hi> came up to a cloſe Fight; who behaving himſelf like a man of Courage was ſlain, and afterward honourably Interred at <hi>Rochel;</hi> the reſt lying off in a Line and firing at a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and many times greatly enda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maging
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:32542:26"/>the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> eſpecially in their Rig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, though they perceived only the <hi>Blue</hi> Squadron Engaged, the <hi>Red</hi> not being able to come up in time. So the <hi>French</hi> ſtood rather Neuters, or Lookers on, than any ways concerned in the Battel.</p>
               <p>From this there grew a ſuſpicion, that they had Orders to keep from Engaging as much as poſſible, that the two Fleets of <hi>England</hi> and the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces</hi> might batter each other, that through their weakneſs the <hi>French</hi> King might become ſtrong at Sea; which more viſibly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared the following Year, 1673.</p>
               <p>This Year the Valiant Prince <hi>Rupert</hi> Commanded the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Fleet, where the <hi>French</hi> joining him, he made One hundred and twenty Sail of ſtout Ships. The <hi>Dutch</hi> were Commanded by <hi>Du Ruytter</hi> and <hi>Van Trump;</hi> ſo that a ſharp Engagement happened. But the <hi>French</hi> no ſooner heard the Bullets begin to rat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and ſaw with what Fury and Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence the <hi>Dutch</hi> and <hi>Engliſh</hi> Engaged, but almoſt all that Fleet ſtood away, pretending to gain the Weather-gage, the which, when they had very favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably got, they e'en kept it for the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of their Maſter's Arms; for they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver came up again during the Fight.
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:32542:27"/>And thoſe few Captains, that had ſo much Senſe of Honour, as not to follow their Admiral, (who were but very few,) had ſecret Intimation that they were in danger of being hanged, when they came into <hi>France,</hi> for not following their Flag, or Orders. But how they came off, has not yet occurred.</p>
               <p>The Prince, though he made good the Fight, and came off with Honour and Bravery, ſtormed to be thus deſerted. Whereupon, when the <hi>French</hi> Admiral came on board him to make his Excuſe (which proved but a very lame one) the Prince is reported to look upon him with Indignation, and after reproaching him with Baſeneſs, told the <hi>Monſieur,</hi> That had he been one of his Maſter, the King of <hi>England</hi>'s Subjects, he would have killed him with his own Hand.</p>
               <p>And to let the World ſee how much the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Valour ſurpaſſes that of the <hi>French,</hi> and how much <hi>Lewis</hi> is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holden to it for his Greatneſs, I need inſtance but one Particular, <hi>viz.</hi> During this War the ſtrong City of <hi>Maſtreicht</hi> was beſieged by an Army of about Forty Thouſand, and the King came as near as he durſt venture, that his Men might be the better encouraged. It was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:32542:27"/>on the Sixth of <hi>June,</hi> and there was in it a Garriſon of 7 or 8000 Men, one <hi>Faro,</hi> a Valiant Man, being Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. The beſieged made a ſtout re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence, and many were killed on both Sides; inſomuch that the <hi>French</hi> began to ſaint. At what time the Heroick Duke of <hi>Monmouth,</hi> who was at the Head of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> in the height of Youthful Valour, deſpiſing Danger, went on to the Aſſault through Showers of ſmall and great Shot; and Commanding in the Trenches, though Two or Three Mines were ſprung to obſtruct his Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, he and the few that followed him, charged with ſuch reſolution, that they carried the <hi>Half-Moon,</hi> contrary to the Expectation of all Men, in leſs than half an Hour; though the Shot flew round him as thick as Hail, maintaining it till he had delivered it to a <hi>French</hi> Collonel, who was ſent to relieve him. But no ſooner was the Duke and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired, but the <hi>French,</hi> though ſtrongly poſſeſſed, not being able to endure the fire of the Beſieged, quitted it. This vexed the Duke to ſee that a Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment could not keep, when put into their hands, what himſelf and a very few <hi>Engliſh</hi> had got. Inſomuch, that he
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:32542:28"/>prepared to regain it, which he did with ſuch daring Reſolution, that, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied only by Twelve Voluntier-Gentlemen, he threw himſelf over the Works and Trenches, with his Weapon in his Hand, and beat out the Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, gaining the <hi>Half-Moon</hi> a ſecond time, and delivered it <hi>Monſieur de la Feuvilade,</hi> whom then ſhame more than true Valour compelled to ſecure it. And indeed, it is conjectured by many, that this ſtrong Place had put a ſtop to the <hi>French</hi> Arms, had not the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> who bore all the brunt of the Siege, done things to a wonder; ſo that at laſt it ſurrendered upon honourable Conditions on the Thirteenth of <hi>June.</hi> But the <hi>French</hi> fury, like a blazing Comet, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving by this time ſpent it ſelf, and the Confederate Armies gathering like a black Tempeſt around them, <hi>Lewis</hi> found that this had been but a kind of a Frolick, to make him more known. For he was not capable of Garriſoning the Towns he had poſſeſſed and keep an Army in the Field, which made him ſpue them up as faſt as he had ſwallowed them; withdrawing his Garriſons, and Abandoning them to their true Owners. which occaſioned a Comical Portraicture
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:32542:28"/>of <hi>Lewis the Great,</hi> Spewing and Sh—ing Towns and Caſtles. However, upon leaving thoſe places, many of them were diſmantled, and the Inhabitants obliged to part with almoſt all they had, for their Contribution or Ranſom, at the diſcretion of the Soldiers.</p>
               <p>King <hi>Charles</hi> II. of <hi>England,</hi> by this time grown weary of a War, into which he had been unadviſedly drawn, and the which without any advantage to <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> had coſt a great deal of Blood and Treaſure, whilſt the <hi>French</hi> reaped the Profit; a Peace was concluded with the <hi>States</hi> for himſelf on very honourable Terms. So that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Fleet being laid up, the <hi>French</hi> durſt be little at Sea; yet at Land the War continued, where the <hi>French</hi> Gold did the greater Service, as indeed it has all along had the Luck to do. And in this State things continued, till the beginning of <hi>May,</hi> 1674.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. finding he had ingaged himſelf too far, and that his violent Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings had drawn a great many Princes upon him, (for they found it high time to Confederate againſt the Diſturber of Chriſtendom,) ſome Overtures of Peace were made, and a Treaty ſet on Foot
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:32542:29"/>in the City of <hi>Cologne,</hi> where divers were aſſembled, in hopes of bringing it to Perfection. But upon the Emperor's ſeizing of the Prince of <hi>Furſtemburg,</hi> (who worked the <hi>French</hi> Intereſt, tho' a Subject of the Empire, and ought to have done the contrary,) it greatly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſted the <hi>French</hi> King, and proved a <hi>Remora</hi> to this Treaty. So that Hoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities continued, and the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> ſeized on <hi>Navaigne;</hi> which, after a ſhort Siege was delivered up; and the King himſelf laid Siege to <hi>Dole,</hi> which made a ſtout reſiſtence, and killed him a great many Men. But not being timely ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coured, it at laſt fell into their Hands.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="50-100" type="pages">
               <p>Theſe proceedings made the Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate Armies draw together to oppoſe them; ſo that on the Fifteenth of <hi>June,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> and the Count of <hi>Caprara,</hi> gave <hi>Turin</hi> Battel; but want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Foot, as having but One Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Foot to Seven thouſand Horſe, and hourly Expecting the Duke of <hi>Bournonville,</hi> who was coming towards them, the <hi>French</hi> on the other hand being Twelve thouſand ſtrong, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding a deſperate Fight, they were forced to retire over the <hi>Necker,</hi> many brave Men being killed, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:32542:29"/>taken Priſoners. The loſs of the ſlain are held to be equal; and had not the Duke wanted Foot, the <hi>French</hi> had been utterly routed: For he Charged with ſuch Fury and Reſolution, at the Head of his Troops, as if he had been weary of his Life, and expected a <hi>Duke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> in another World, rather than this.</p>
               <p>Whilſt theſe things paſſed, the <hi>Dutch</hi> ſcoured the Seas with their Fleet, the <hi>French</hi> not daring to peep abroad; for now they had nothing to fear on the Ocean, having made a Peace with the <hi>Engliſh.</hi> Whereupon they braved the <hi>French</hi> in their Harbours, and made a Deſcent on <hi>Bell Iſle,</hi> but could make no Advantage on that ſtrong Place. But the <hi>Dutch</hi> Forces at Land took the <hi>Grime,</hi> a very ſtrong Place, after a hard Siege. And now <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. betook him to the <hi>French</hi> Policy, of tampering abroad: And finding by his Agents, that the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of <hi>Meſſina</hi> in <hi>Sicily,</hi> grew wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Government, he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged them to Rebel, and ſent them Succours under the Command of the Duke <hi>de Vivone;</hi> ſeizing that City, and taking an Oath of Fidelity of the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants. But when he had brought them to this Revolt, and kept a Garriſon there a
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:32542:30"/>very conſiderable Time, contrary to the Expection of all Men, and out of what Caprice none perhaps but himſelf knows to this Day, he ſuddenly recal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led his Forces, leaving ſo many of the Inhabitants, as would not leave all they had to Ship themſelves and fly into <hi>France,</hi> (where they could rely upon no Succour,) to the Mercy of the Inraged <hi>Spaniards,</hi> whom they had highly of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended by this Revolt. Nor had they above four Hours Notice: Yet as many as could, crowded on Board, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward lived in Exile, not daring to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn.</p>
               <p>King <hi>Charles</hi> II. of <hi>England</hi> having made a Peace with the <hi>States</hi> of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Provinces,</hi> iſſued out a Proclamation on the Nineteenth of <hi>May,</hi> 1675. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding all his Subjects in the <hi>French</hi> Service as Soldiers, ſince the Treaty of Peace, to quit forthwith that Service, and return Home; and prohibiting any <hi>Engliſh</hi>-men to engage themſelves in the like for the future; which proved a great Detriment to the Progreſs of the <hi>French</hi> Arms, as ſoon after appeared: For the Army as not only overthrown, but <hi>Turin,</hi> the moſt Experienced General of <hi>France,</hi> was ſlain. But, becauſe this
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:32542:30"/>Action was very Memorable, we ſhall not think it amiſs to give a brief Account of it.</p>
               <p>On the Eighteenth of <hi>July</hi> 1675, the <hi>Mareſchal de Turin</hi> commanded out the Regiments of Horſe of <hi>Campaigne</hi> and <hi>Orleance,</hi> with Nine Squadron of Horſe, under the Command of the Marqueſs <hi>de Rone, Mareſchal,</hi> to paſs the River <hi>Ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chau,</hi> by the Means of Two Bridges he had laid over. And being informed, That the <hi>Imperialiſts</hi> had laid an Ambu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcade on the other ſide, he went in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to ſee if he could diſcover it from a certain Height, near the Bridge: When the <hi>Imperialiſts,</hi> having planted Two ſmall Pieces in a Wood hard by, fired one of them without any conſiderable Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; but the ſecoud being Charged with Iron, or Cartridge-ſhot, put a period to <hi>Turin</hi>'s Life; killing likewiſe, the Lieutenant-General of the Ordnance, and divers others of Quality about him; though ſome Accounts ſay, he was killed with a Cannon Shot. However, thus ended that great General, who had been brought up in War, as we may proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly term it, from his Infancy, and ſeen many Rivers of Blood; whoſe Death gave a great check to the <hi>French</hi> Affairs,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:32542:31"/>and the Army was ſo much diſcouraged, that it immediately retired in ſome diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order; when being purſued, and hotly engaged by <hi>Montecuculi,</hi> the <hi>Imperial</hi> General, between Six and Seven thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand of them were ſlain, and ſeveral Colours, with ſome Cannon and Bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage taken; the Count <hi>de Lorge,</hi> who Commanded after the Death of <hi>Turin,</hi> being wounded, and many Perſons of Quality killed.</p>
               <p>This was ſeconded by the Overthrow of the <hi>Mareſchal de Crequi,</hi> near <hi>Treves:</hi> For the <hi>Confederates</hi> having beſieged that place, which had been ſurprized by the <hi>French,</hi> the <hi>Mareſchal</hi> came to Succour it; but the Beſiegers drawing off, and giving him Battel, his Forces were totally defeated, with the loſs of Three or Four thouſand Men, and of all the Baggage and Cannon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Army ſcattering, and getting into the adjacent Town. The <hi>Mareſchal</hi> with ſive or ſix men got into <hi>Treves,</hi> and, the Governour being killed, took upon him to defend the place; but the Beſiegers having made Three Breaches ſo wide, that Forty Men a-breaſt might enter; the Officers finding the Ditches likewiſe filled up, and the Storm ready to be
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:32542:31"/>made, they Capitulated without <hi>Crequi;</hi> who, to regain in ſome meaſure the Credit he had loſt, ſuffered himſelf to be made a Priſoner of War. <hi>Binch</hi> was likewiſe taken by the <hi>Dutch,</hi> and many other Advantages gained. So that <hi>Lewis the Great,</hi> began to think that he had overſtood his Markets, and thought it high time to look out for Confederates. Whereupon he drew the King of <hi>Sweeden</hi> into an Alliance with him, to divert the War on that ſide of the King of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark</hi> and Duke of <hi>Brandenburg.</hi> But the <hi>Sweeds</hi> had but little Succeſs in his Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel, as being worſted by Land and Sea, and having nothing but the <hi>French</hi> King's Word for Reparation. Inſomuch that they were obliged to ſit down by the Loſs, and thereupon <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. began to tamper with the <hi>States</hi> of <hi>Holland,</hi> to clap up a Peace without the Conſent of their Allies. But whilſt it was on Foot, which made the King grant the larger Terms, his Forces under the Duke of <hi>Luxemburg</hi> were beaten near <hi>Mons</hi> by the <hi>Engliſh, Dutch,</hi> and <hi>Germans.</hi> In which Action, his preſent Majeſty of <hi>England</hi> ſignalized his Valour and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct to a wonder; and the Duke of <hi>Monmouth</hi> being a Voluntier in the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:32542:32"/>by his Example ſo animated the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> that they let the <hi>French</hi> ſee they were capable of turning the Scale of Victory.</p>
               <p>Theſe Bad Succeſſes making <hi>Lewis the Great</hi> fear he ſhould be reduced to <hi>Lewis the Little,</hi> he made ſuch Offers (which were ſeconded by many Promiſes and Crafty Inſinuations) that the <hi>States</hi> did conclude a peace, and had all their Towns, except <hi>Maeſtreicht,</hi> delivered into their poſſeſſion; which made many wonder. But thoſe that have weighed the Matter, give theſe Reaſons for their making a peace, when other Princes their Confederates were in Treaty; for that of <hi>Nimeguen</hi> was ſtill on Foot:</p>
               <p>Firſt, They perceived the Ambaſſadors of their Allies, had been ſeveral Years in debate at <hi>Nimeguen,</hi> without bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any thing to Perfection as to the Treaty with <hi>France;</hi> and they had great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly waſted their Treaſure in the War, and found a peace was neceſſary to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cruit.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Their Trade, on which the Provinces moſtly depend, was greatly obſtructed; by which means the People were Impoveriſhed.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, They were Conſtrained to
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:32542:32"/>take up Moneys on the publick Truſt, to ſupply the Charge of the War; which being of long Continuance, could not but have conſumed vaſt Treaſures</p>
               <p>Fourthly, That the <hi>Spaniard</hi> had not thoſe Forces on foot in the <hi>Netherlands</hi> that was Expected; which might have hindered the <hi>French</hi> from taking ſeveral Towns in <hi>Flanders,</hi> of which, without any conſiderable Oppoſition, they had poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed themſelves.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, That all things were reſtored to them that had been taken away, which would have been difficult to have Recovered by other means.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, By this Treaty they cauſed to be rendered up to <hi>Spain,</hi> part of what had been taken during the War.</p>
               <p>Seventhly, That the <hi>French</hi> Miniſters aſſured the <hi>States,</hi> that they would ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily make a Peace with their Allies, and that they, <hi>the States,</hi> ſhould be Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trators of that Peace.</p>
               <p>Theſe are given as Reaſons. And indeed, conſidering how the Miniſters of <hi>France</hi> preſſed it with Eagerneſs, and declared the Extream Paſſion and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire the King their Maſter had to be at peace; it might have been thought, that he mean'd as he ſaid. The King
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:32542:33"/>himſelf, during the Negotiation, ſent them a Letter, wherein he ſtyled them, <hi>His good Friends, Allies, and Confederates;</hi> promiſing wonderful things in the moſt obliging Flattery. But no Words or Promiſes can bind this <hi>Leviathan;</hi> for <hi>Lewis</hi> knew well enough what he did by making a Separate Peace; conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, if he ſhould be brought to Strict Terms with all the Allies, he muſt of Neceſſity part with <hi>Lorrain</hi> to the Duke, its <hi>Rightful Lord,</hi> and with the <hi>Franche Compte</hi> of <hi>Bourgogne,</hi> to the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> taken, contrary to faith given, ſince the <hi>Pyrenean</hi> Treaty. But, by not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the <hi>Dutch</hi> Army upon his back, he ſound himſelf able to deal with the reſt, and to tire them out by delays. And indeed, by taking theſe Meaſures, he conſtrained the Duke of <hi>Brandenburg,</hi> and the Prince of <hi>Zel,</hi> to reſtore all they had taken from the <hi>Sweed,</hi> ſince that King ſtood for the <hi>French</hi> Intereſt.</p>
               <p>King <hi>Charles</hi> II. of <hi>England,</hi> perceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. delayed the Treaty to incroach upon <hi>Flanders,</hi> found his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour touched, ſince he became a Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator, and was to be Guarrantee of the Peace. And thereupon ſent over five or ſix Thouſand Men, to defend the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:32542:33"/>Netherlands,</hi> where the <hi>French,</hi> du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Treaty, and daily Expectation of Peace, were like ſo many <hi>Tartars,</hi> or wild <hi>Arabians,</hi> Ravaging and deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Country; but the Terrour of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> put a Check to their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. having obtained a Peace with the <hi>States</hi> of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces,</hi> he more and more delayed the Treaty of <hi>Nimeguen,</hi> as not doubting to bring the other <hi>Confederates</hi> to more Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageous Terms, than otherwiſe he could have been capable of doing. And that which made the <hi>French</hi> King more ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent for a Separate Peace, was, that he knew well enough that it could not be Reaſonably made with the <hi>Allies</hi> in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction, but that the Country of <hi>Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain</hi> would be required for that Duke, and the <hi>Franche Compte</hi> for the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> or what ever had been ſnatched from that Crown ſince the <hi>Pyrenean</hi> Peace, which had been ſo openly vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated by <hi>France.</hi> And therefore he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, to divide the <hi>Allies</hi> was to make his own Terms. And indeed it ſo fell out, to the great prejudice of the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federaters,</hi> Eſpecially <hi>Spain</hi> and the <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire,</hi> as in due place will appear. And
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:32542:34"/>indeed, <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. by this means pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved moſt of his important Conqueſts at that time, whilſt the <hi>Elector</hi> of <hi>Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denburg,</hi> and the Prince of <hi>Zell,</hi> found themſelves in a Neceſſity to Reſtore to <hi>Sweden</hi> all they had taken, or, by ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out, run the Hazard of a <hi>French</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my Ravaging their Countries; whilſt their <hi>Allies,</hi> who had already made peace, could not fairly give them any Aſſiſtence; unleſs, like him with whom they had made the peace, they layed no Streſs upon Leagues, any longer than it tended to their purpoſe. But the <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror,</hi> as well as <hi>Holland,</hi> having con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded with <hi>France,</hi> the reſt found them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves too weak long to contend with a <hi>Monarch</hi> of ſuch vaſt Territories, and one whoſe Flatterers ſtyle <hi>Invincible;</hi> though, the contrary has often appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. And, according to the opinion of Politicians and thoſe Experienced in war, had that vaſt Army of the <hi>Confederates</hi> been unanimous, and vigourouſly puſhed on, they might, by entering the very Heart of <hi>France,</hi> have reduced the Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of <hi>Lewis,</hi> and have made their own Terms. <hi>Sed, divide, et Impera.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Peace, as is already ſaid, being concluded with <hi>Holland</hi> at <hi>Nimeguen,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:32542:34"/>the latter End of the Year 1678, was ſoon followed by his <hi>Imperial</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty. But, before either of theſe were concluded, it will not be amiſs to ſhew the plauſible pretences of <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. to the former, in a Letter in Anſwer to a Letter to the <hi>States General,</hi> preſented him by their Ambaſſador, the <hi>Heer Vain Beverning,</hi> in theſe Words:</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng" rend="margQuotes">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Moſt dear great Friends, Allies, and Confederates,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>WE have with much Pleaſure un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, as by the Letter you writ us, ſo by the Aſſurances which the <hi>Heer Van Beverning,</hi> your <hi>Extraordinary Ambaſſador,</hi> hath in your Name given us, the Diſpoſitions in which you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs your ſelves to be at Peace. We cannot better let you know how firm and ſincere our Intentions are, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure ſo great and ſo general a Good for <hi>Europe,</hi> than by a Writing, which we have Commanded to be put into his Hands. You will ſee the new Facilities we offer, to put you in a State to bring your <hi>Allies</hi> to conſent to the Conditions, which we cannot doubt but you will judge Equitable. And having nothing farther to add thereunto, we only aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:32542:35"/>you of the Satisfaction we ſhall have of giving you back with the Peace our old and real Friendſhip, and in enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with you into the ſtrongeſt and moſt capable Engagements, for ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ever your Liberty; which we have more amply explained our ſelf upon to the <hi>Heer Van Beverning,</hi> whoſe Conduct and Perſon hath been very acceptable to us. There remains on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, That we pray <hi>God</hi> to have you, moſt dear great Friends, Allies, and Confederates, in his holy Keeping.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>Given in our Camp at</hi> Wetteren, <date>
                              <hi>the Firſt Day of</hi> June, 1678.</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <signed>Your good Friend, Ally, and Confederate, LOVIS.</signed>
                        <signed>Underneath Signed <hi>Arnauld.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>The Matter to which <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers them to, is a <hi>Memorial</hi> delivered to the aforeſaid <hi>Ambaſſador</hi> by his Order, in theſe following Words:</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">THE King hath with Pleaſure ſeen, as by a Letter from the <hi>States Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral,</hi> ſo by the Aſſurances which they have given him by the <hi>Heer Van Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning,</hi> their <hi>Extraordinary Ambaſſador,</hi>
                     <pb n="63" facs="tcp:32542:35"/>that their Intentions to a general Peace, correſpond with the Deſires his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty hath always had to procure the ſame; and that they are ready to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the Conditions that his Majeſty hath offered them by his <hi>Ambaſſadors</hi> and <hi>Plenepotentiaries</hi> at <hi>Nimeguen.</hi> But, at the ſame time the <hi>Heer Van Bever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> hath made known to him the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents of the ſaid <hi>States General,</hi> he hath in their Names pray'd, that his Majeſty would grant a Ceſſation of Arms for ſix Weeks, and hath repreſented to him, that they had need of that time to Communicate with their Allies, and obtain their Conſent for the concluding ſo great a Work: The Condition in which his Majeſty's Arms are at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and the favourable Opportunity that would be loſt in deferring their Acting, would not permit him to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to this Propoſal, if the deſire of giving Peace to <hi>Europe</hi> did not much more prevail with him, than that of enlarging his Frontiers by new Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts. It is upon this Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, of contributing to the publick Repoſe, that he will agree, at the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of the ſaid <hi>States General,</hi> to a Ceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of Arms for Six Weeks; ſuch a
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:32542:36"/>one as was ſtipulated between <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain, Anno</hi> 1668. But for as much as it would not be juſt, if the Enemies of his Majeſty ſhould let the time paſs fruitleſly; and that, inſtead of its ſerving to Advance the Peace, they ſhould make Advantage of it, to avoid the Effect of his Majeſty's Arms, that he ſhould have loſt the advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous Conjuncture that is at preſent in his Hands: His Majeſty deſires of the ſaid <hi>States General,</hi> that they do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe him, that in caſe during the Time of Ceſſation of Arms, they cannot bring their <hi>Allies</hi> to accept the Conditions he hath offered, that they will not aſſiſt them directly or indirectly againſt him or his <hi>Allies,</hi> during the whole Courſe of the War. In Exchange, his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty will in ſuch Caſe renew to them the ſame Engagements, which he hath taken with them, by his Letter of the Eighteenth of the laſt Month, as well as what concerns theſe ſame Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which he will be always ready to agree to. As for the ſecurity of the Places in the <hi>Spaniſh Netherlands,</hi> his Majeſty hath thought fit to make known unto the <hi>States General,</hi> by this <hi>Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial</hi> which he hath appointed to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:32542:36"/>to the <hi>Heer Van Beverning,</hi> the ſincerity of his Intentions for a Peace. And to give yet a greater Teſtimony thereof, he doth Command the Duke of <hi>Luxemburg,</hi> General of his Army, to go and expect their Anſwer, during this Month, in the Neighbourhood of <hi>Bruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels,</hi> with Orders not to Attack any Place during that time.</q>
               </p>
               <p>In this we may obſerve no ſmall piece of <hi>French</hi> Policy, not ſo much deſiring the Peace of <hi>Europe,</hi> (which has never been the aim of this Ambitious Prince,) as during the time of this Truce, to draw his Army farther into <hi>Flanders,</hi> which ſoon after proved almoſt the Ruine of many delicious places in that fruitful Country, when Peace was in the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Proſpect. And theſe Flatteries ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved only to render thoſe he treated with ſomewhat more ſecure, whilſt he made his own Markets. And indeed by theſe, and ſuch like Artifices, he gained upon the Belief and good Intention of the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates,</hi> more than by open ſincerity he thought convenient to do. For <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. having earneſtly ſued for Peace, though under a Reſerve or Mask of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe, which was not then ſufficiently
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:32542:37"/>looked through, all the Princes and States of <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> ſuppoſed they ſhould remain at reſt; and thoſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries that were at the brink of Ruine, by being the Seats of a tedious War, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to rejoice, thinking the <hi>French</hi> King in good earneſt; and that he would (af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſo much Waſte and Deſolation, by Firing, Plundering, Quartering, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions, Contributions, Slaughters, and making the Fields white with the Bones of the Slain, whilſt the Rivers were diſcoloured, and run red to the Sea with <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Blood,) take pity on the languiſhing Eſtate of; <hi>Europe,</hi> there being a powerful Enemy in the <hi>Eaſt, viz.</hi> the <hi>Ottoman Emperor.</hi> But, inſtead of Sincerity, all proved but outſide and formal. For <hi>France</hi> rather coveted time to breath a little, than to give over. And <hi>Lewis,</hi> who ſo often pretends to make War for the Glory of his Arms, that he might with leſs trouble Invade the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> ſecretly Negotiated with <hi>Teckely,</hi> to Invade with an Army, ſuch as he could gather in the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Territories, the <hi>Emperor</hi>'s Hereditary Countries in <hi>Hungary, &amp;c.</hi> furniſhing him with Money, and folliciting by his Ambaſſadors at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> with Gifts,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:32542:37"/>Preſents, and promiſe of Diverſion on the other-ſide, to break the Truce. And all this under the glorious Title of <hi>the moſt Chriſtian King,</hi> and <hi>Eldeſt Son of the Church;</hi> which even barbarous Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions have deteſted in a time of Peace. And yet, ſuch have been the Humours of this King's Flatterers, that they have more and more blown up his Ambition, by comparing him <hi>to the Sun,</hi> as, <hi>to the Star of Stars, from whence all other Kings and Potentates receive their Luſtre,</hi> with many other Attributes, as if they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to ſet him up for an <hi>Idol</hi> for all the World to fall down before. And of theſe we ſhall give the Reader a touch; becauſe thoſe Paraſites ſtrive, by glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Epithets, to make him appear white and ſhining, almoſt, if not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together, to a height of Blaſphemy, whom all unprejudiced and unbiaſſed Men behold cloathed with Oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Cruelty, and dying his Scarlet Robes yet deeper in innocent Blood.</p>
               <p>Amongſt other things attributed to him, paſſing over what is mentioned as to the placing his Name on the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> College, inſtead of that of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> we find theſe that follow, which may be ſaid to exceed what the <hi>Heathens</hi> have
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:32542:38"/>aſcribed to thoſe they fooliſhly Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for Gods, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Lowis the Great, <hi>born for the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of</hi> France, <hi>and Happineſs of his People, in whom there lives an admirable Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Divine Wiſdom and Fortitude, that alone is ſufficient to convince Atheiſts,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Lewis the Great, <hi>a King indeed, ſince he Reigns not only over his Subjects, but his own Paſſions; being Invincible, and ſtrongly and ſweetly overcoming all things; who,</hi> juſt as a <hi>God,</hi> by one ſingle Act of his Will, ſubjects all things to his ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Power, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Lewis the Great, <hi>ſtrong in Zeal for Juſtice, a powerful and moſt juſt Rewarder of all good Actions, the ſevere Puniſher of Duels, Blaſphemy, and all Iniquity, the true Imitator of God, who is ſo Good to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pay by way of Recompence what he promiſes by way of Mercy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Lewis the Great, <hi>according to God's own Heart, annointed with his own Holy Oil, whom in a particular manner God comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his Holy</hi> Angels <hi>to preſerve in all his Ways, and whence the Exiſtence of</hi> Angels <hi>is deduceable,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Lewis the Great, <hi>meditating only on eternal Things, and knowing that the gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:32542:38"/>the World with the Loſs of the Soul pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiteth nothing, and therefore ſeeking of</hi> God <hi>the alone Happineſs which</hi> God <hi>of his Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs has called Man to.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. Lewis the Great, <hi>Intent upon the Extirpation of publick Sin, and the Encreaſe of Integrity, of Manners and Virtue, and for that Effect giving moſt ſure Laws, through the Inſpiration of</hi> God, <hi>the Supream Law giver, by whom Kings Reign,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Lewis the Great, <hi>the Prodigy of the Grace of</hi> God, <hi>and of ſo thankful a Mind towards him on that Account, being Careful to Exalt that Grace, has comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded all the Faculties of his Kingdom to explain that Grace, conform to the Edicts of the Popes,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Lewis the Great, <hi>the Eldeſt Son of the</hi> Church, <hi>who has reſtored to their</hi> See <hi>the Biſhops that had been banifhed by He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks; the Enemy of Hereſie; the Van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſher of the</hi> Turks, <hi>confiding only in</hi> God, <hi>and burning in Love towards him; the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of Faith, Love, and Charity,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Lewis the Great, <hi>a Prince of Peace, the Scourge of War, having ſo far layed aſide his Majeſty, that he might Remember the Mercies of</hi> Chriſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">10. Lewis the Great, <hi>deſtroying all Vice, and decreeing Several puniſhments on
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:32542:39"/>the Infringers of</hi> Divine <hi>and</hi> Eccleſiaſtical <hi>Laws. In all things he hath demonſtrated himſelf a moſt obedient Son of the</hi> Church.</p>
               <p n="13">13. <hi>To declare the kinds of Sin, though hard to ſome, yet not to perfect</hi> Chriſtians, <hi>whoſe defender</hi> Lewis the Great, <hi>juſtly to be named the King of Glory, Strong and mighty in Battel,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>We might recite a number more of this Kind, which we find in print, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding the boaſting Language of the <hi>Turks,</hi> in their denunciation of War, or magnifying their <hi>Emperor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They have not only put them in print, no doubt, with the Approbation of this King, who is not a little Ambitious of his own Praiſe, but the Duke <hi>De Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>villade</hi> has erected his <hi>Effigies</hi> Crowned with Rays and Stars, as the old Romans uſed to do their God <hi>Jupiter,</hi> and in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place he is figured driving the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot of the Sun, with this <hi>Motto, I ſhine to All.</hi> And indeed, this very much Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembles him; for <hi>Europe</hi> has found him a very <hi>Phaeton,</hi> if we conſider the almoſt numberleſs Towns and Villages he has cauſed to fall in Flames. At other times, they call him <hi>Homo Immortalis,</hi> an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Man, the ſame Character the <hi>Heathens</hi> were wont to give to thoſe
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:32542:39"/>they fanſied to be deified; gathering the Conduct, Courage, Wiſdom, &amp;c. not only of his Anceſtors, but of all the Renowned Heroes that ever have been, which they will have centre in him, who indeed is but <hi>Mortalis Homo, cum Fiſtula in. Ano,</hi> notwithſtanding all the Flattery of Medals, Prints, Landskips, Inſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Statues; or, as they have in one place made the Figures of <hi>Europe, Aſia, Africa</hi> and <hi>America,</hi> Kneeling at his feet, as if he gave Laws to the whole Earth. But how far he anſwers any of theſe Characters, let us lay aſide for a time his Actions and Behaviour to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his Neighbours, and look a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle into the Interiour parts of his Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, and there ſee how he keeps his word, and uſes his own Subjects, by whoſe Help and faithful Aſſiſtence, his Anceſtors mounted, and himſelf as yet is fixed in the Throne of <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>King <hi>Henry</hi> IV. Grandfather to <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. had, for the Many memorable and ſignal Services done him, granted the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> the free Exerciſe of their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion by an <hi>Edict,</hi> and other Privileges that were granted them by <hi>Lewis</hi> XIII, Father to this King. The <hi>Edict</hi> of King <hi>Henry</hi> was given at <hi>Nantes</hi> in <hi>April</hi> 1598,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:32542:40"/>under the favour of which, the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> that had eſcaped the bloody Maſſacre in the Reign of <hi>Charles</hi> IX. and the Sword of War that had continued for many Years, revived, as we may term it, or multiplied in their Generations: But when they thought themſelves moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure, and every one ſat under their Vines of plenty, this King by the Inſtignation of the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> and his own Inclination, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to thirſt after their wealth, as <hi>Ahab</hi> in another place had done after <hi>Naboth</hi>'s Vineyard. And finding whilſt this <hi>Edict</hi> was in force, it could not be attempted with the leaſt Colour of Juſtice, he pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed a Strict Decree to diſannul it, as likewiſe the <hi>Edict</hi> of <hi>Niſmes</hi> given in <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> 1629. together with all the Conceſſions granted in them, as well as other De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations, Edicts, and Arreſts, of what nature ſoever; forbiding any of the <hi>Reformed Religion,</hi> under great Pains, Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties, and Forfeitures, to have any pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blick Worſhip amongſt them; as know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, like thoſe who ſought to deſtroy <hi>Daniel,</hi> he could not make them diſobey him in any thing Lawful.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Bloody Decree</hi> being ſigned by the King at <hi>Fountainbleau, in October</hi> 1685, it was Regiſtered and Publiſhed by the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:32542:40"/>King's <hi>Attorney General.</hi> And in order to its being put in Execution, and the Copies being examined and compared, it was ſent into the ſeveral Bailiffwicks, and Courts of Juſtice, Sherifs-Courts, Diſtricts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> there to be Regiſtered, and Charge given to the Deputies of the <hi>Attorney General,</hi> to take care they were put in Execution, with all Imaginary Force and Rigour, and to certiſie the Court thereof at <hi>Paris</hi> in the Court of Vacation on the 22<hi rend="sup">d</hi> of <hi>October.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. when he did this, had, it ſeems, forgotten that he had on <hi>the Word of a King</hi> Ingaged the contrary, or he concluded, it was no diſhonour for a King to break his Word whenever he pleaſed. Wherefore, before we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to take a view of his perſecuting his beſt Subjects, it will be convenient to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert his own Letter in Anſwer to a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Duke of <hi>Brandenburg</hi>'s on the behalf of the <hi>Proteſtants.</hi>
               </p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng" rend="margQuotes">
                  <body>
                     <head>Lewis <hi>XIV's Letter to his</hi> Electoral High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs <hi>of</hi> Brandenburg.</head>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Brother,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>I Would not have diſcourſed the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter you writ to me about, on the behalf of my Subjects of the <hi>Preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:32542:41"/>Reformed Religion,</hi> with any other Prince, beſide your ſelf: But, to ſhew you the particular Eſteem I have for you, I ſhall begin with telling you, That ſome Perſons diſaffected to my Service, have ſpread Seditious Pamphlets among Strangers, as if the <hi>Acts</hi> and <hi>Edicts</hi> that were paſſed in Favour of my ſaid Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of the <hi>pretended Reformed Religion</hi> by the Kings my Predeceſſors, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by my ſelf, where not kept and executed in my Dominions, which would have been contrary to my Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: For I take Care that they be Maintained in all the Privileges which have been granted them, and be as kindly uſed as my other Subjects. To this I am engaged by my Royal Word, and in Acknowledgment of the Proofs they have given me of their Loyalty during the late Troubles, in which they took up Arms for my Service, and did vigorouſly oppoſe and ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully Overthrow the ill Deſigns which a Rebellious Party againſt my Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity Royal, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>This, one would think, was ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently binding; but, as it appears by a Clauſe in the <hi>Decree,</hi> bearing date long
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:32542:41"/>ſince this Letter, the King never intended to be as good as his Word, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">Whereas, (ſays the <hi>Decree,</hi>) That it hath pleaſed <hi>God</hi> to grant that our Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects enjoy a perfect Peace, and we our ſelves being no longer taken up with the Cares of protecting them againſt our Enemies, are now in a Condition to make good uſe of the ſaid Truce, <hi>viz.</hi> of <hi>Nimeguen,</hi> which we have on purpoſe facilitated, in order to the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying our ſelves entirely to the ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of means, which might ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully effect, and accompliſh the Deſign of the Kings, our ſaid Grand-father and Father, our Intentions ever ſince we came to the Crown; we ſee at preſent,</q> (notwithſtanding a juſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment of what we owe to <hi>God</hi> on that account,) <q rend="margQuotes">that our endeavours have attained the end we propoſed to our ſelves, foraſmuch as the greater and better part of our Subjects of the ſaid <hi>pretended Reformed Religion,</hi> have already Embraced the <hi>Catholick;</hi> and ſince by means thereof the Execution of the <hi>Edict</hi> of <hi>Nantes,</hi> and all other Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, in favour of the ſaid <hi>pretended Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Religion</hi> become uſeleſs, we judge that we can do nothing better towards
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:32542:42"/>the entire effacing the memory of thoſe Troubles, Confuſions, and Miſchiefs, which the Progreſs of that <hi>Falſe Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> have been the cauſe of in our King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and which have given occaſion to the ſaid <hi>Edict,</hi> and to ſo many other <hi>Edicts</hi> and <hi>Declarations</hi> which went be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it, or were made ſince, with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference thereto; than by a total Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation of the ſaid <hi>Edict</hi> of <hi>Nantes,</hi> and particular Articles and Conceſſions granted therein, and whatſoever hath been Enacted ſince, in Favour of that Religion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>By this 'tis evident, That when he paſſed his Word to the <hi>Elector,</hi> and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved the Loyalty of his <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, he had it in his thoughts upon his firſt coming to the Crown to ſuppreſs them. But this is the very <hi>Genius</hi> of <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. and now let us ſee how gent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he deals with them, and what Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward they have for their Fidelity, and the Expence of their Blood and Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to keep him in the Throne, againſt a powerful Faction under the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> and others, who were at the point of ſupplanting him; why thoſe that were to ſee the <hi>bloody Decree</hi> Executed, fell to Conſulting how they ſhould raiſe the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:32542:42"/>Malice high enough in Cruelty againſt People that had never injured them; whilſt the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> like the <hi>Jews,</hi> when <hi>Ahaſuerus</hi>'s Decree went forth, mourned their hard Fate, and made their Application to the King; but <hi>Heſter</hi>'s Tears could not prevail with his <hi>Moſt Chriſtian Majeſty,</hi> though they had power to make a <hi>Heathen</hi> relent.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Intendent</hi> of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pper Guienne,</hi> who Reſided at <hi>Montauban,</hi> ſummoned the Chief <hi>Proteſtants</hi> of that City to appear before him, and let them know, That it was the <hi>unalterable Pleaſure</hi> of the King, to have but <hi>one Religion</hi> in his Kingdom, and that they muſt prepare to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with it; giving them time to aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble themſelves in the <hi>Town-houſe,</hi> where they unanimouſly agreed, rather to die than violate their Conſciences, and by one deputed by the reſt ſent their Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, when, the following Day, a Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tallion of <hi>La Ferre,</hi> conſiſting of Sixteen Companies, entered the City, and were followed by a greater Number. The <hi>Proteſtants</hi> thereupon conſulted each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and reſolved to ſubmit to what ſhould befal them, not caring for the Spoil of their Goods, ſo they might pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve their Religion, reſolving to rely
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:32542:43"/>on Providence; and the Richer agreed to help the Poorer to the laſt of their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. But whilſt they were thus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting, the <hi>Dragoons</hi> entered their Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes like the Locuſts of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and having eaten up all they found, fell to deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Goods, ſuffering their Wines and other Liquors to run about the Cellers, ſcattering alſo their Corn in the Streets. And when they grew even wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of this waſteful Deſtruction, they car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried Linnen, Plate, Puter, and other things, to the Market-place, and offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it to Sail, where the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> and <hi>Popiſh Prieſts</hi> bought them for trivial Prices, and encouraged the <hi>Lay-Papiſts</hi> to do the like. So that the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> in four or five days, loſt to the value of a Milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; yet they might be ſaid, even to take joyfully the ſpoiling of their Goods: But when this availed not to ſhake their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy, theſe Miſſionaries of <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. very proper Fellows to convert Souls, fell to Out-raging their Perſons with Cruelties and Barbarities worſe than Death. One <hi>Bervois</hi> they dragged to the Guards, and there for a whole Night the Soldiers continued in turns to kick and buffet him. Monſieur <hi>Solignack</hi>'s Hand they bound to a Spit, and forced
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:32542:43"/>him to turn it, till, by the Exceſſive Fire they made, he himſelf was near Roaſted to Death: And, to ſhew their farther Malice, made a Stable of his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning-room, where the Furniture was worth Ten thouſand <hi>Livres,</hi> which they afterward deſtroyed. Another Perſon they dragged to <hi>Maſs,</hi> and becauſe he hung back, and cryed out, <hi>He would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver do it,</hi> they beat him to Death. But ſhould we come to particular Perſons, the Numbers would fill a Volume as large as thoſe of the <hi>Martyrs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Monſieur <hi>de Garriſon,</hi> a Venerable Man, who had done great Kindneſs for the <hi>Intendent,</hi> went to wait upon him in this extremity to intreat his Protection; but he, like a true <hi>Papiſt,</hi> who holds no Faith to be kept with <hi>Hereticks,</hi> notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding he offered him all his Goods, not only rejected his ſuit, but cauſed him, beyond what he had ſuffered, to be dragged through the Streets, and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably miſuſed, as a means to deterr others from Petitioning him. This ſort of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting was not only uſed in this City, but throughout all the Dominions of the King, though in different Methods of ſtudied Cruelty. Some they toſſed from one Soldier to another, kicking, buf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feting,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:32542:44"/>and beating them with Rods three or four Days and Nights together to keep them waking; and when at any time they fainted, or ſunk down, then they uſed them in that manner on the Ground, or on Beds, and when they had reſted, rouſed them again: Some they hung up by the Heels, and ſmoaked them with burning wet Straw, till they were almoſt dead Some again they blew up almoſt to burſting, by putting a pair Bellows into their Fundaments: They baſted the Soles of the Feet of others with Lard, and held them to a Fire till almoſt Roaſted. One <hi>Iſaac Favin,</hi> a Citizen of <hi>Negropliſſe,</hi> they hung up by the Armpits a whole Night, and pinched off his Fleſh with Pincers, yet could not prevail to make him abjure.</p>
               <p>Theſe Cruelties, and many more, were committed not only upon Men, but alſo upon Women, and even upon Children that were of any Years. The younger Infants were every where taken from their Parents by force, and thruſt into Monaſteries and Nunneries; Wives, Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows, and Virgins were in many Places Raviſhed and Deflowred. Some Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, though of very tender Years, they kept faſting till they fainted, and then
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:32542:44"/>brought them before their Parents, as imagining they would rather turn, than ſee their Children Periſh. Many times the Prieſts would perſuade ſome to Abjure, declaring, it ſhould be only ſeemingly, to comply with the King's <hi>Decree;</hi> but when they had unadviſedly done that, in hopes of ſome reſpite, then they compelled them to torment their Friends and Relations into an Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juration; the which, if they did not in three Days, or ſo much time as was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven them, the <hi>Booted Apoſtles</hi> are ſent to them again, upon a ſcruple of their not being thorowly Converted. Sometimes they bind the Mothers, that give ſuck, to Poſts, and lay their Infants to periſh in their ſight, unleſs they will Abjure. And when theſe <hi>Dragoons</hi> were weary of tormenting, and inventing new manner of Torments, tired with the patience of the Sufferers, and deſpairing to bring them to their Terms, the Officers Rate them, and ſend them back to torture them worſe, ſaying, <hi>The King has Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded it, and it muſt be done;</hi> bawling out, <hi>That the King intends to have but one Religion in his Dominions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe are the pleaſant Paths by which <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. invites his <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Subjects
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:32542:45"/>to enter into the Boſom of <hi>Mother-Church,</hi> exceeding thoſe of the <hi>Heathen</hi> Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors; for they only killed, and made way for the triumphing <hi>Martyr</hi> to enter into Glory; but here they have a linger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Death, and by a <hi>Series</hi> of Torments, above what humane Nature is able to bear, their Hearts are ſometimes forced to give their Tongues the Lye. Some Perſons they tortured with Engines, and put braſs Pans or Kettles over the Heads of others, and with continual beating upon them, made the Party in a manner diſtracted. Thoſe of the better Sort fled to <hi>Paris,</hi> thinking the <hi>Dragoons</hi> would not come ſo near the King's Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace: But alas, there they found no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uge; for a <hi>Decree</hi> was ſet forth, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding them to depart the City, and retire to their reſpective Habitations on greater Pains and Penalties. Nor did theſe Monſters of Converters only ſpightfully miſuſe their Perſons, but likewiſe ſhewed their Malice upon the poor Cattle; as if the King had commanded them to bring the Hogs, Cows, Sheep, and Oxen over to the Church, as well as their Owners; for ſome of them they Hoxed, and ſo ſuffered them, for want of Legs, to go to periſh in the Fields; others they killed
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:32542:45"/>out-right, and ſuffered to rot on the Ground. Some again they drove into Rivers and drowned. They cut down the Timber, and burnt it; deſtroyed their Vineyards, and ſold their Houſes; drew their Fiſh-ponds, and threw their Fiſh into the Street.</p>
               <p>Theſe <hi>Miſſionaries</hi> exceeding the Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barity of <hi>Tartars,</hi> were attended by a multitude of Raſcally <hi>Friars</hi> and <hi>Prieſts</hi> to take Confeſſions and Abjurations, as likewiſe by a <hi>Biſhop,</hi> before whom they were to be Examined. And when thoſe that through Torments, and being tired out, had Abjured, were at <hi>Maſs,</hi> they had Spies ſet upon them; and if it appeared that they did it not ſincerely, then they were thrown back into their former Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery. And although theſe Loyal People (as the King himſelf confeſſed them to be) would have left all they had, and forſaken the Country; yet that was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid them on ſtrict Penalties, as even Death, or perpetual Impriſonment. The <hi>Ports</hi> were ſtrictly watch'd, and Ships on pain of Forfeiture forbidden to take them in; yet, through Providence, many eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caped into <hi>England, Holland, Germany, &amp;c.</hi> and found Succour and Shelter. Their Miniſters only found the Favour
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:32542:46"/>to be Baniſhed, but to leave behind them their Wives, Children, and Relations: Nay, they hardly eſcaped ſending to the <hi>Gallies;</hi> for ſuch are the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nchriſtian</hi> Ways of the <hi>Moſt Chriſtian King,</hi> that he will have it a Crime, in his Country, for Men to be Learned and Vertuous: So by this means a Million of Families were ruined, and many Thouſands pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed through Want, Torture, and in Priſons; for all the Gaols of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces were filled with theſe diſtreſſed People. Nor did their Malice and Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty ſtop here; for although the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters had Liberty to go into Baniſhment, under the hardeſt of Conditions; yet the King's Miniſters on the <hi>Frontiers,</hi> frequently ſtopped them, under frivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous pretences, till the time given them to depart was expired; and then char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged them with breaking the Orders, in not departing within the limited time, and that they muſt go to the Gallies; by which means they ſtripped them of all that little they had left; and well they thought it, if they ſo eſcaped, to wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in ſtrange Lands, and relie upon Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, which indeed did almoſt every where plentifully provide for them. The <hi>Elector</hi> of <hi>Brandenburgh</hi> put out a Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:32542:46"/>in Favour of them, inviting and encouraging as many as would or could Eſcape, to take up their Habitations in his Territories; commanding all his Subjects to Comfort, Harbour, Cheriſh, and Entertain them; and gave Order to his Miniſters, to ſee it carefully obſerved in all his Cities, and Towns, through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his Dominions. The like, in effect, was obſerved in <hi>England, Holland,</hi> and other Places, where Briefs were granted, and large Contributions given for the Support of ſuch poor Refugees as took ſhelter, and by many Difficulties eſcaped the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nchriſtian</hi> Cruelties of the <hi>Moſt Chriſtian King.</hi> Nor will it be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proper, for the better informing the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Reader, to give a brief Account of what the Manner and Form of the <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurations</hi> and <hi>Subſcriptions</hi> thoſe of the <hi>Reformed Religion</hi> were to make, for the Pleaſure of <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. in which <hi>Popery</hi> is briefly anatomized: <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <p>IN the Name of the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, Amen. I Believe and Confeſs with a firm Faith, all and every thing and things contain'd in the <hi>Creed,</hi> which is uſed by the <hi>Holy Church</hi> of <hi>Rome, viz.</hi> I Receive and Embrace
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:32542:47"/>moſt Sincerely the Apoſtolical and Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Traditions, and other Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervances of the ſaid Church. In like manner I Receive the Scriptures, but in the ſame ſenſe as <hi>Mother-Church</hi> hath and doth now underſtand and expound the ſame, for whom and to whom it only doth belong, to Judge of Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of the ſacred Scriptures; and I will never take them or underſtand them otherwiſe than according to the Unanimous Conſent of the <hi>Fathers.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I profeſs, that there be truly and properly <hi>Seven Sacraments</hi> of the New Law, Inſtituted by our <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and neceſſary for the Salvation of Mankind, although not Equally needful for every one, <hi>viz. Baptiſm, Confirmation, the Euchariſt, Penance, Extream <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction, Orders,</hi> and <hi>Marriage;</hi> and that they do confer Grace, and that Baptiſm and Orders may not be reiterated without Sacrilege. I receive and Admit alſo the Ceremonies Appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the <hi>Catholick Church,</hi> in the Solemn Adminiſtration of the foremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned Sacraments.</p>
                  <p>I Receive and Embrace all and every thing and things, which have been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined concerning <hi>Original Sin</hi> and
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:32542:47"/>
                     <hi>Juſtification,</hi> by the <hi>Holy Council</hi> of <hi>Trent.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I likewiſe profeſs, that in the <hi>Maſs</hi> there is offered up to <hi>God</hi> a true, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and propitiatory Sacrafice for the Living and Dead, and that in the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sacrament of the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> there is truly realy and <hi>Subſtantially</hi> the <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood,</hi> together with the <hi>Soul</hi> and <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity</hi> of the <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> and that in it there is made a Change of the <hi>whole Subſtance</hi> of <hi>Bread</hi> into his <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,</hi> and of the <hi>whole Subſtance</hi> of the <hi>Wine</hi> into his <hi>Blood.</hi> Which Change the <hi>Catholick Church</hi> calls <hi>Tranſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation.</hi> I confeſs alſo, that under one only of theſe two Elements, whole <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and the true Sacrament is Received.</p>
                  <p>I conſtantly believe and Affirm, that there is a <hi>Purgatory,</hi> and the Souls there detained are relieved by the ſuffrages of the faithful.</p>
                  <p>In like manner I believe, that the Saints Reigning in Glory with <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> are to be worſhipped and Invo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated by us, and that they offer up Prayers to <hi>God</hi> for us, and that their Relicks ought to be honoured.</p>
                  <p>Moreover, I do moſt ſtedfaſtly A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vow, that the Images of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi>
                     <pb n="88" facs="tcp:32542:48"/>of the <hi>bleſſed Virgin,</hi> the <hi>Mother of God,</hi> and of <hi>other Saints,</hi> ought to be kept and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ained; and that due Honour and Veneration muſt be yeilded unto them.</p>
                  <p>I alſo do affirm, that the Power of <hi>Indulgences</hi> was left to the <hi>Church</hi> by <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> and that the uſe thereof is very beneficial to <hi>Chriſtians.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I do acknowledge, the <hi>Holy Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Apoſtolick</hi> and <hi>Roman Church,</hi> to be the Mother and Miſtreſs of all other Churches; and I profeſs and ſwear true Obedience to the Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor of the bleſſed St. <hi>Peter,</hi> Prince of the Apoſtles, and Vicar of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In like manner, I own and profeſs, without doubting, all other things left, defined, and declared by the <hi>Holy Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons</hi> and <hi>General Councils,</hi> eſpecially by the moſt <hi>Holy Council</hi> of <hi>Trent;</hi> and withal, I do condemn, reject, and hold accurſed, all things that are contrary thereto, and all thoſe Hereſies that have been condemned, Rejected, and Accurſed by the <hi>Church.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <p>This is the Goodly ſtuff to be Impoſed on the Conſciences of the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> which even an Ignorant <hi>Indian,</hi> almoſt by the Light of Nature, might detect.
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:32542:48"/>And for refuſin, this, they were forced to undergoe all the Torments that wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Horrour could Invent. And to this thoſe that Recanted were obliged to ſwear in the following Words:</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">I Promiſe, Vow, and Swear, and moſt conſtantly profeſs by <hi>God</hi>'s Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence, to keep entirely and inviolably, till death, this ſelf-ſame <hi>Catholick</hi> and <hi>Apoſtolick Faith,</hi> out of which no Perſon can be ſaved. And this I do moſt truly and willingly profeſs; and that I will, to the utmoſt of my power, endeavour that it may be maintained and upheld, as far as any ways belongs to my charge. So help me <hi>God,</hi> and the <hi>Holy Virgin.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>And now to conclude this part of the Glorious Actions of <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. who would be taken for the very Champion of <hi>Mother-Church,</hi> we ſhall give you a Copy of the Certificate, that the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canting party is to leave with the Preiſt, when he makes his Abjuration:</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">I <hi>A. B.</hi> of the Pariſh of <hi>C.</hi> do cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie to all whom it may concern, that having acknowledged the Falſneſs of the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> or <hi>pretended Reformed Religion,</hi> and the Truth of the <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Religion,</hi> of my own free Will,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:32542:49"/>without any Compulſion, have accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly made profeſſion of the ſaid <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Roman Religion,</hi> in the Church of <hi>D.</hi> in the Hands of <hi>W. G.</hi> In teſtimony of the Truth whereof, I have ſigned this Act, in the preſence of the Witneſſes whoſe names are under-written This <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> day of the Month of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> in the Year of the Reign of our Sovereign Lord the King <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> and of our Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>By this the Reader may ſee how In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. would appear, when the Perſon is compelled to ſay he makes his <hi>Abjuration,</hi> without any manner of Force and Compulſion, voluntarily and willingly; when indeed, all People, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the Preiſt that takes it, knows it to be a palpable Lye. Indeed <hi>Pope Innocent</hi> XI. (and the <hi>Pope</hi> we muſt conclude to be no Friend to the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Religion, which is diametrically oppoſed to his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt,) when <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. by his Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador at <hi>Rome,</hi> bore himſelf ſo much upon the Meritorious Service he had done the <hi>Church,</hi> in converting ſuch a number of <hi>Hereticks,</hi> (as he ſtyled them,) told the Ambaſſador, <hi>That if his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter had nothing elſe to boaſt of, it would be little to his Glory; for his manner of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting</hi>
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:32542:49"/>Hereticks, <hi>was neither pleaſing to</hi> God <hi>nor</hi> Man. But, to trace this ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Prince a little farther, let us ſee how little he regards Religion, when his Intereſt or Wilfulneſs calls him on to Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and Arbitrary Motions. For e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the <hi>Pope</hi> himſelf fared little better in his Hands, as far as lay in his power to attempt againſt him, though he would be ſtyled, <hi>the Eldeſt, and moſt obedient Son of the Church:</hi> Whereby it will appear, that his Hand is againſt all, without di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction.</p>
               <p>Whilſt <hi>Lewis the Great</hi> was ſo earneſtly perſecuting his <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Subjects, <hi>Pope Innocent</hi> XI. (of a <hi>Pope,</hi> reckoned to be the beſt that has been for ſome hundreds of Years) finding an Increaſe of Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, Outrages and Villanies in the City of <hi>Rome,</hi> and that thoſe that committed them were harboured and protected; he thought the beſt way to prevent ſuch diſorder for the future, was to deprive them of their ſhelter, by taking away the <hi>Franchiſes</hi> of all the Ambaſſadors, that none might have cauſe to complain. And, in order thereto, he revoked thoſe Privileges by a <hi>Bull,</hi> bearing date the 12 of <hi>May, Anno</hi>— which was migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily oppoſed by the Marqueſs <hi>D' Lavar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine,</hi>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:32542:50"/>Ambaſſador for <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. though none elſe oppoſed it, as holding the <hi>Pope</hi> a Sovereign Prince: in his own City. But he proceeded not only to ſhelter Murtherers and Thieves, even in the City of <hi>Rome,</hi> but to Protect them, and with armed Force ſtood upon his Guard to oppoſe the Officers that were ſent to demand them, ſending a Diſpatch to his Maſter, to let him underſtand what had happened; who, in a Bravado, fell to big Words againſt his <hi>Holy Father,</hi> reſolving not to part with any part of his <hi>Franchiſes.</hi> However he ſeized upon the City of <hi>Avignion,</hi> whch had been held for many Ages as part of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Peter's</hi> Patrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and cauſed the <hi>Pope</hi>'s Supremacy to be denied in the <hi>Parliament</hi> of <hi>Paris,</hi> as appears by the Speech of Monſieur <hi>de Tolon, Advocate General,</hi> who likewiſe plays with the great Thunderbolt of the <hi>Roman See,</hi> (which has ſo long been a Bugbear to all the <hi>Roman Catholick Princes,</hi>) like a Tennis-Ball, when he has this Expreſſion; <hi>And to add,</hi> (ſays he,) <hi>to that</hi> Bull, (meaning that by which the <hi>Franchiſes</hi> were taken away,) <hi>vain Threats of Excommunication, that are not capable of creating the leaſt Terrour in the moſt timerous Minds, and in the niceſt
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:32542:50"/>Conſciences,</hi> &amp;c. But neither theſe big Words, nor his frequent Solicitations, nor his many Purſes of Gold diſtributed amongſt Favourites, could bring the <hi>Old Man</hi> to buckle <hi>to his Moſt Chriſtian Son</hi>'s Humour: For the Ambaſſador perſiſting to contemn the <hi>Pope</hi>'s Orders, he Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated him, and Interdicted the Church of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Lewis</hi> in <hi>Rome,</hi> for admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him in the Night-time to the <hi>Holy Sacrament,</hi> forbidding all manner of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to have Converſe either with them, or him. But the Circumſtances of this Matter we ſhall ſee in an <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Appeal,</hi> put in by the <hi>Attorney General</hi> of <hi>France</hi> to the <hi>Council,</hi> upon the Subject of the <hi>Pope's Bull</hi> concerning the <hi>Franchiſes,</hi> &amp;c. in theſe Words:</p>
               <p>Before the under-written <hi>Apoſtolick Notory,</hi> was preſent in his own Perſon <hi>Meſſire Achilles de Harlay,</hi> Counſellor of the King in his <hi>Conncil of State,</hi> and his Majeſty's <hi>Attorney General;</hi> who (in the Preſence, and by the Advice and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of <hi>Meſſire Denis Talon,</hi> and <hi>Meſſire Fra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cois Critean de la Moignon,</hi> alſo Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors of the King in his <hi>Council of State,</hi> and his <hi>Advocates General</hi> in his Courts of <hi>Parliament,</hi>) has declared,</p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <p>That ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſome time ſince ſeen Copies of a
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:32542:51"/>
                     <hi>Bull</hi> given on the 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>May</hi> laſt paſt, by our <hi>Holy Father, Pope Innocent</hi> XI. concerning the <hi>Franchiſes,</hi> which cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Perſons are in Poſſeſſion of in the City of <hi>Rome;</hi> he could not have ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined, that <hi>His Holineſs</hi> could have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Deſign of comprehending the Ambaſſadors the King was willing to ſend to him, in the general Menaces of Excommunication, which he judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed convenient to inſert therein, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the uſe obſerved by other <hi>Popes</hi> in the <hi>Bulls</hi> made by them. He had hoped, that if the remembrance of the ſovereign Power, which the King's Majeſty's Predeceſſors exerciſed in <hi>Rome,</hi> of their Liberalities to the <hi>Holy See,</hi> and of the Protection they gave to ſeveral <hi>Popes,</hi> could not induce this <hi>Pope</hi> to cauſe to be rendered to the King, in the Perſon of his Miniſters, Honours and Teſtimonies of Acknowledgment, proportionable to his Bounties: At leaſt his Holineſs, as viſible Head of the <hi>Church,</hi> would not be inſenſible to the Prodigies the King had performed before his Eyes, for the Reuniting with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Boſom of his <hi>Good Mother,</hi> ſo vaſt a number of Children that were gone aſtray from her;(<hi>by theſe he means the</hi>
                     <pb n="95" facs="tcp:32542:51"/>Dragoon'd Converts;) but that he would be Affected with the Piety of this Prince, and the powerful Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction he continually gives to Prelates; though he inſiſts not on his Victories and Power, and that he would not enter into Diſputes with him about Rights that had not ſuffered any Inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion under his <hi>Popedom</hi> for many Years: But being informed, that <hi>His Holineſs</hi> had given Orders to the <hi>Cardinal,</hi> that is his Vicar in <hi>Rome,</hi> to declare the Church of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>Lewis,</hi> in that City, and the <hi>Eccleſiaſticks</hi> that officiate in it, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terdicted, for having admitted to the participation of the <hi>Holy Myſteries of the Sacrament,</hi> on the Night wherein is Celebrated the Solemnity of our <hi>Lord's Nativy,</hi> Monſieur <hi>Le Marquis de La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vardin,</hi> the King's Ambaſſador Extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary to His <hi>Holineſs,</hi> and that it was ſuppoſed upon the Ordinance delivered upon this Subject, that he was noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly Excommunicated, for preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Contraventions to the <hi>Bull;</hi> the ſaid <hi>Attorney General</hi> did not think he could, without being wanting to his duty, remain any longer in Silence he hath hitherto kept.</p>
                  <p>Now, if the matter which has given
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:32542:52"/>an occaſion to ſo great an Exceſs, did concern the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Juriſdiction that belongs to the <hi>Pope,</hi> he would eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhew the Errours that have been com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by proceeding againſt a perſon that has not been particularly ſpecified in that <hi>Bull,</hi> to whom the State of the matter has not been ſignified ſince his being at <hi>Rome,</hi> who might be ignorant of them in <hi>France</hi> where it was not pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, that the <hi>Pope</hi> could condemn him as an Ambaſſador, though his Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter ought to ſecure him from theſe Thunders, in regard of his Functions; yet <hi>His Holineſs</hi> would not ſo much as hear him, or own him in that Quality, whatever Addreſſes he has cauſed to be made for that purpoſe; and that, in fine, the very Rules of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non Law requires, that Perſons of ſo eminent a Dignity ſhould be pointed out by Name in <hi>Bulls</hi> of that Nature, before they incurr the Penalties they utter.</p>
                  <p>But the <hi>Pope,</hi> in a matter purely Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral, as are theſe <hi>Franchiſes,</hi> has made uſe of the Spriritual Arms, which he is intruſted with, only for the Conduct and Edification of the Church. (Here, by the way, the <hi>Pope</hi> might have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:32542:52"/>of <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. Why he uſed <hi>Temporal</hi> Arms in <hi>Spiritual</hi> matters, as his <hi>Dragoon-Converts</hi> can teſtifie. But to go on:) And having conſtituted himſelf Judge in his own Cauſe, the Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication which his <hi>Holineſs Cardinal Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car</hi> declares to be Incurr'd, is ſo Null, that there is no occaſion for any Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding to annihilate it; and thoſe that are therein comprehended ought not to receive Abſolution, though it were offered them even at their own homes. And indeed the ſaid King's <hi>Attorney</hi> does, with all the <hi>French,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect from his Majeſties Single Power, the Reparation which theſe Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings challenge, and the Conſervation of thoſe <hi>Franchiſes</hi> which only depend on the Judgment of <hi>God,</hi> as the Rights of this Crown, which can admit of no Dominion but ſuch as the King's Moderation and Juſtice may give them. But as not any thing can Contribute more to leſſen, in the Minds of ſhallow Perſons and Libertines, the Veneration which people ought to have for the Power of the <hi>Church,</hi> than the Ill uſe which it's Miniſters may make of it; the King's ſaid <hi>Attorney General</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares, that he is Appealing, as indeed
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:32542:53"/>he appeals by the preſent Act, from the Abuſive uſe that is made of it in the ſaid <hi>Bull</hi> and <hi>Ordinance,</hi> not to our <hi>Holy Father Pope Innocent</hi> XI. ſo as has been practiſed by ſome of his Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors: When that they had the True Ideas of their Power that their years allow them to act of themſelves, there might be hopes that in time they might be brought to know the Juſtice and Truth of the Complaints that were brought before them: And, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the preventions in favour of their Country, or the Partialities of thoſe they honour'd with their truſt, did pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail over the obligations which the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of <hi>Common Father</hi> of all <hi>Chriſtians</hi> does Impoſe; Proteſting to carry on this his ſaid Appeal upon this grievance, and upon others which he reſerves to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to the <hi>firſt General Council</hi> that ſhall be held, as the Tribunal truly Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign and Infallible of the <hi>Church,</hi> to which it's Viſible Head muſt Submit as well as it's other Members; and therein to further, amongſt other things, a Regulation that ſhall prevent the Imploying ſo Holy an Authority, in uſes ſo far from thoſe for which it was conſided in the <hi>Church</hi> in the Perſon of
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:32542:53"/>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Peter.</hi> This may make the <hi>Pope</hi> be mindful, that <hi>God</hi> having ſeparated the two Powers of the <hi>Prieſthood</hi> and of the <hi>Empire,</hi> the <hi>Pope</hi> cannot make uſe of the Authority of the <hi>Firſt,</hi> for the Rights that depend on the <hi>Second;</hi> that is, according to Temporal Laws, he ought to poſſeſs thoſe Large Territories which his Predeceſſors have received from the Liberality of Temporal Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and particularly from that of our King's. And, in ſhort, he would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider upon a Truth, which a Great Archbiſhop in <hi>France</hi> wrote to one of his Predeceſſors, that a Prelate who Excommunicates a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> contrary to the Rules, and for Rights of a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the Earth, may in ſuch an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion loſe the Power of binding and unbinding, which his Character gives him, but he cannot deprive of Eternal Life him to whom he does this Injuſtice, if his Sins do not render him unworthy of the Mercy of <hi>God.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <p>This Act was ſigned on the 22<hi rend="sup">d</hi> of <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuary</hi> 1688.</p>
               <p>We hope the Reader will pardon us the tediouſneſs of this Matter, when by it he may perceive how little Zealous <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. is for the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi>
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:32542:54"/>when he thus violently affronts his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the <hi>Pope,</hi> its Viſible Head, only about a place of ſhelter for <hi>Thieves, Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers,</hi> and ſuch like Villains; when at the ſame time he will not allow his pious Subjects of the <hi>Reformed Religion,</hi> (whoſe Loyalty himſelf has owned, and whoſe Eſtates have been always ready to furniſh his Wars,) to have any ſhelter or aboad in his large Dominions, though they have all along appeared the very ſinews of his Kingdom, and held with a ſtrong Hand, and open Purſes, the Crown he wears on his Head. However the <hi>Pope</hi> would not yield to Revoke the <hi>Bull,</hi> but the <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſes</hi> remained Null; the <hi>Pope</hi> publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declaring <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. the apparent Enemy of <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> and the only Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that influenced the <hi>Turks</hi> to break the Truce, and with an Inundation of <hi>Barbarians</hi> to Invade the <hi>Empire.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="100-151" type="pages">
               <p>We have ſeveral times had Advice, That the Ambaſſador of <hi>France</hi> has been Abuſed in the <hi>Divan</hi> at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> being not only denied the <hi>Sofra,</hi> but beaten by the Command of the <hi>Grand Vizier,</hi> for throwing up his Cuſhion that chanced to fall upon the ſaid <hi>Vizier,</hi> as he was going out. And although him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf has placed, and held his Stool upon
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:32542:54"/>the <hi>Sofra,</hi> it has been removed; nay, he has had of late an Ambaſſador Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned there, whoſe Liberty was not gained without 100 Purſes of Money. And whilſt all <hi>Europe</hi> was wondering what Meaſures this <hi>Great Monarch</hi> would take to revenge the Affront, alas! the Buſineſs was tamely clapped up, the Ambaſſador was recalled, and another ſent in his ſtead, and as good Friends as ever, though the Kingdom of <hi>France,</hi> at the ſame time Reaps no extraordinary Benefit in the <hi>Turks</hi> Dominion. But thoſe that have more narrowly pried into this Affair, give their Opinion, That theſe Affronts were agreed on, to caſt a Miſt before the Eyes of the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Princes, ſo that they might not ſee the underhand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dealings that were carried on between the <hi>Moſt Chriſtian</hi> and <hi>Mahomitan Turk.</hi> For this way of miſuſing the Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor, was indeed looked upon by moſt, as tending to a Breach, and a Rupture was daily expected. But it ſeems the <hi>Moſt Chriſtian King</hi> delights moſt in ſhedding <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Blood, and his Zeal for Religion is manifeſted, in Burning, and Blowing up Churches of all <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Perſuaſions, as well thoſe of the <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> as the <hi>Proteſtants.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:32542:55"/>
               <p>Let us look now a little back, and we ſhall find Count <hi>Teckely</hi> in <hi>Hungary</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying with Fire and Sword, raiſing Troops with <hi>French</hi> Gold; and though a <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> ſecretly encouraged to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade the <hi>Empire</hi> by the <hi>French</hi> Emiſſaries, with Promiſe of greater Aſſiſtance. But proving too weak of himſelf to oppoſe the Armies that were drawn that way, the <hi>Turks</hi> broke the Truce at the Inſtiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>France,</hi> as will more largely ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear when we come to inſert the <hi>Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror</hi>'s Declaration of War with <hi>France.</hi> And under that Advantage, the Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Troops being drawn off, <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. very Piouſly Beſieged and took the City of <hi>Straſburg,</hi> a <hi>Free Imperial Town,</hi> when hardly any Body expected any Hoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity. His pretence was, to reſtore the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> which that <hi>Proteſtant</hi> City refuſed to admit with his <hi>Popiſh</hi> Trnmpery. The Articles of Surrender were very advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageous to the Citizens; as, a promiſe of their Religion, Liberties, and any thing they deſired. But the <hi>French</hi> gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Poſſeſſion, ſoon barred them of a great part, delivering many over to the Mercy of the enraged <hi>Biſhop,</hi> who never was any Favourer of the <hi>Proteſtants;</hi> and likewiſe reſtored <hi>Popery,</hi> building a
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:32542:55"/>Cittadel, or Caſtle, for the better cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing the Citizens; many of whom find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves ſo hardly dealt with at firſt, and fearing worſe, ſecretly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew, with what Subſtance they could, to other Cities remote; whereupon the Effects they left were ſeized, a ſtrict Charge was given to have an Eye upon the Inhabitants, and ſuch as they ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted going off were Impriſoned, and all the ſmall Towns and Villages were taken in as Dependences, and conſtrained to pay great Contributions; and ſuch as could not, or refuſed, were threatned with Military Execution. A great Army alſo of the King's, lay hovering on the <hi>Weſt</hi> Frontiers of the <hi>Empire,</hi> whilſt <hi>Cara Muſtapha,</hi> the <hi>Grand Vizier,</hi> was coming down on the <hi>Eaſt</hi> like a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luge, with about Two hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Tartars,</hi> who burnt and deſtroyed all before them: For by this time, <hi>Mahomet</hi> IV. had proclaimed War againſt the <hi>Emperor,</hi> and detained the Count <hi>de Caprara,</hi> his Ambaſſador. All Princes of the <hi>Empire,</hi> upon the ſudden <hi>Allarm,</hi> were in doubt, and ſuſpence, which of theſe <hi>Turks</hi> they ought moſt to fear. Though <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. out of a ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing pretence for the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> had
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:32542:56"/>made an offer to aſſiſt the <hi>Emperor;</hi> but this was only ſhadow, as appeared af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards, by his violent falling upon the <hi>Spaniſh Netherlands,</hi> whereby the Forces of the King of <hi>Spain</hi> were hinder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from Aſſiſting in the common Cauſe. And although moſt of the Princes of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope</hi> uſed their Intereſt with him, though all <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> in a manner lay at ſtake, nothing would prevail, till he perceived the <hi>Turks</hi> could not effect what they pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed. For, in the Year 1683<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they were totally Routed, and beat off from the Siege of <hi>Vienna,</hi> the principal City of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> when it was at the laſt <hi>Criſis,</hi> and could have held out but a few days longer.</p>
               <p>It is no wonder that the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> who, on all Hands, are deteſted, and accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Incendiaries of <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> by the moderate <hi>Roman Cotholicks,</hi> have ſo great an Influence in <hi>France,</hi> ſince Father <hi>Maimburgh,</hi> and Father <hi>La Cheſe</hi> have had ſo great an Influence over <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. to whoſe fiery Spirit they labour to add Fuel, and plunge him into Cruelty with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Remorſe, or diſtinguiſhing <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants</hi> from <hi>Roman Catholicks.</hi> And theſe were the bleſſed pair, that laid the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the Miſery of his Subjects of
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:32542:56"/>the <hi>Reformed Religion,</hi> by perſuading him, That by Rooting the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> out of his Kingdom, he would render himſelf greater than his Anceſtors, who were never able to accompliſh that mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; and, that if he could bring it to paſs, it would render his Name Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal in the <hi>Roman</hi> Kalendar. And, no doubt, as many Inſtances affirm, theſe Locuſts who ſeek to devour every thing that is pleaſant, have had as great an Influence in the Ruine of the Neighbou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <hi>Roman Catholicks.</hi> For, from the Wideneſs of his Conqueſts, they could not but promiſe to themſelves great Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, where they have ſo great an Influence over the Conqueror, as to have his very Conſcience in their keeping and diſpoſe. We have not of late heard that any, like Father <hi>Ante,</hi> have repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved him for Exorbitancy of Luſt, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Vices, but rather encouraged him therein, that they might reap the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit at the Price of his Eternal State. And of this we may give ſome hints, as we find it in a Letter that has of late been frequently Printed, and held to be Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentick, ſent from <hi>La Cheſe,</hi> Confeſſor to the <hi>French</hi> King, to Father <hi>Edmund Petre,</hi> late <hi>Great Almoner</hi> to King <hi>James</hi> II.
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:32542:57"/>though fatal in his Counſels to the repoſe of that unfortunate Prince. Wherein, amongſt other matters, undertaking to give the <hi>Jeſuit</hi> directions to put forward affairs, by his Counſels, Intereſt, and Power with King <hi>James,</hi> and others great at Court, he thus proceeds:</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng" rend="margQuotes">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Moſt Reverend Father,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>TO ſatisfie the deſire I have to ſhow you by my Letter, the Choice you ought to make of ſuch perſons fit to ſtir up, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I will, in few words, ſince you deſire it, inform you of the <hi>Genius</hi> of the people of our Court, of their inclinations, and of them we make uſe of, that, by a Parallel you make be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them and your <hi>Engliſh,</hi> you make uſe of, you may know them. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſhall begin with the Chief, I mean our Great Monarch. It is certain, he is naturally Good, and loves not to doe Evil, unleſs deſired to doe it. This being ſo, I may ſay, he never would have undertaken the Converſion of his Subjects, without the Clergy of <hi>France,</hi> and without our <hi>Society's</hi> Correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence abroad. He is a Prince Inlightned, who very well obſerves, what we put him upon is contrary to his Intereſt,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:32542:57"/>and that nothing is more oppoſite to his great Deſigns and his Glory, he aiming to be the Terrour of all <hi>Europe.</hi> The vaſt number of Malecontents he has cauſed in his Kingdom, forces him in time of <hi>Peace,</hi> to keep up three times more Forces than his Anceſtors did in the greateſt Domeſtick and Foreign <hi>Wars,</hi> which cannot be done without prodigious Expence.</p>
                     <p>The Peoples Fears alſo begin to leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen as to his aſpiring to an <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Monarchy,</hi> and they may aſſure them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves he has left thoſe Thoughts, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing being more oppoſite to his deſigns, than the method we enjoin him. His Candour, Bounty, and Toleration to the <hi>Hereticks,</hi> would undoubtedly have opened the door of the <hi>Low Countries, Palatinate,</hi> and other States of the <hi>Rhine,</hi> and even of <hi>Switzerland;</hi> whereas things are at preſent ſo altered, that we ſee the <hi>Hollanders</hi> at preſent free from any fear of Danger, the <hi>Switzers</hi> and City of <hi>Geneva</hi> reſolved to loſe the laſt drop of their Blood in their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence. Beſide ſome Diverſions we may expect from the <hi>Empire,</hi> In caſe we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not hinder a Peace with the <hi>Turks.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Sir, His Majeſty's Brother is always
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:32542:58"/>the ſame, I mean, he takes no notice of what paſſes at Court. It has ſometimes happened, the King's Brothers have acted ſo, as to be noted in the State: But, this we are ſure, will never do any thing to ſtain the Glory of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion and Obedience, and is willing to lend a helping hand for the Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the <hi>Hereticks,</hi> by the Inſtance he makes to his Majeſty, who now has promiſed him to cauſe his Troops to enter the <hi>Palatinate</hi> the next Month. The <hi>Dauphin</hi> is paſſionately given up to Hunting, and little regards the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of Souls; and therefore we do not care to Conſult him, how or which way the <hi>Hereticks</hi> ſhall be deſtroyed. He openly laughs at us, and ſlights all the Deſigns of which the King his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther makes great Account.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>The Letter goes on to Characterize the <hi>Dauphineſs</hi> in her witty Humour, and Hatred to the <hi>Proteſtants;</hi> as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe Monſieur <hi>Lovois,</hi> the <hi>Archbiſhop</hi> of <hi>Paris,</hi> and others, who labour to Agran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. by following the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods of the <hi>Society</hi> of <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> who have always been held the Foxes with Fire-Brands at their Tails, who have labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to promote Violence, War, and Blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:32542:58"/>in all Places where they come. <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> IV. Baniſhed them <hi>France,</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moliſhed their Houſes, for ſetting one of their Pupils to kill him in his Preſence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chamber amidſt his <hi>Nobles,</hi> becauſe he would not hearken to their Counſels, but deteſted their pernicious Ways. Yet, knowing them to be Sycophants, fraught with Malice and Revenge, after he had fruſtrated many of their Attempts, that great Prince, who had faced Death in all its Shapes, fearing their wicked Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes, thought fit to make fair Weather with them, and to recall them; which being oppoſed by a <hi>Lord</hi> of his <hi>Council,</hi> who alledged how pernicious they were in all Kingdoms, States and Governments, the King paſſionately broke out into this Expreſſion, <hi>viz. Secure me my Life then.</hi> And indeed, this King who had remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſafe in forty Battels, found his Death, as has been ſaid, in the midſt of his <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pital City,</hi> amongſt his Friends and Guards. Nor could the Obſtinacy of the Aſſaſſinate and Paricide denote any thing elſe, but that he was ſet on by theſe Men. For <hi>Raviliack,</hi> the bloody Actor, neither ſought to fly, nor excuſe the Fact: nor, when his Fleſh was pluck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed off with hot Pincers, would he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:32542:59"/>who inſpired him to doe it, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained obſtinate in the midſt of the moſt horrid Tortures, which demonſtrated, that he had been decoyed by ſuch as made him believe, the Fact was no leſs than Meritorious, and that Eternal Life was entailed upon him for the Deed. And no boubt, <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. is not fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, (notwithſtanding his Bravadoes) of ſome ſuch Fate, if he ſhould reject them and their Counſels; which makes him ſo far comply with their Maxims, as to involve the Nations in Blood, and carry Fire and Deſtruction where-ever his Armies come, and make himſelf the very <hi>Phaeton</hi> of the World. Some will object in their Excuſe, that <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. dares not keep his Armies Idle; for, the Soldiers having been ſo long trained up in War by a long Eaſe, would grow Luxurious, and be apt, like the <hi>Roman Pretorian</hi> Soldiers, at every little di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaſter to Mutiny: or, if that he ſhould disband them, they for the moſt part being Incapable of any other Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment than the Sword, would infallibly ſhake his Throne, by joining with thoſe his Tyranny has reduced in a manner to Deſpair. However, any Reaſonable Man might think, he might employ
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:32542:59"/>them in other matters, as fortifying his Inland-Towns, and building Piramids to his Glory, as the Kings of <hi>Egypt</hi> did, to keep their People from Idleneſs, upon the ſame Score, as moſt Hiſtorians con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture, whoſe Labour produced thoſe Laſting Monuments, whoſe Aſpiring Tops are ſaid to penetrate the Clouds. But <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. is of another Mind; he is for building a Structure with the untempered Mortar of Rapin and Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and Cementing it with <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Blood; wiſhing, no doubt, that all who oppoſe his deſigns, had but one Neck, as <hi>Heliogabulus</hi> did by the People of <hi>Rome,</hi> that himſelf, as a Laſting Monument of his Glory, might have the Honour of cutting it off; which ſhews the very Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of <hi>Jeſuit</hi>-Counſels.</p>
               <p>Pardon, Reader, this Digreſſion, if it may be ſo termed in a Hiſtory of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; for, where a Man pretends Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, he is inclined to one ſide or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ought to have the Awe of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, of what perſuaſion ſoever he be, upon his Mind, favouring that party to which he inclines. But <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. is of a contrary Temper, having his Hand againſt all, whilſt all mens Hands are more juſtly againſt him. We will not
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:32542:60"/>determine, what Orders he would give in relation to <hi>Turkiſh Moſques,</hi> or <hi>Mahomets</hi> Religion. But ſure we are, in all the Progreſs wherever his Arms have carried Deſtruction, the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Churches of whatſoever perſuaſion, have felt the Marks of his Irreligion and Sacrilege. Nay, it is affirmed upon credible teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, that when the numerous Hoſt of <hi>Infidels</hi> over-ran <hi>Hungary,</hi> and the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs was doubtful, whether the Loſs or Relieving <hi>Vienna</hi> ſhould hazard or ſave the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> part of the Empire; and Prayers were put up almoſt every where for the Succeſs of the <hi>Chriſtians, Anno</hi> 1683. the <hi>Moſt Chriſtian King</hi>'s <hi>Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent</hi> at S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Omers,</hi> gave a ſevere Repri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> for having ordered publick Prayers to be put up, and a Faſt to be held on that occaſion. And when this Inundation of <hi>Barbarians</hi> were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> carrying Fire and Sword into moſt of the <hi>Emperor</hi>'s Heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditary Provinces, with Slaughter, Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage and all the Outrages that can be Imagined; inſomuch that the flaming Towns and Villages ſeemed but one great ſcene of Fire, and the cries of the miſerable People rent the Skies, which bluſhed with the Aſcending Heat and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flexion
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:32542:60"/>of Blood; even then, when all good Men were overwhelmed with Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. brought down his huge Armies on the Front of the <hi>Empire,</hi> to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-awe the Little Princes, and keep their Troops for the Defence of their own Territories, that they might have no ſhare in the Glory, by aſſiſting the <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror</hi> againſt the <hi>Infidels.</hi> And Monſieur <hi>Seppeville</hi> was a Spie upon the <hi>Emperor</hi>'s Affairs, giving <hi>Lewis,</hi> his Maſter, from time to time, an Account of the Progreſs of the <hi>Turks,</hi> and of their Succeſs; and that the League between him and <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met</hi> IV. <hi>Emperor</hi> of the <hi>Turks,</hi> might be as much ſhadowed as it was poſſible, Monſieur <hi>Fouchay</hi> perſuaded him to make a Diverſion in the <hi>Spaniſh Netherlands,</hi> thereby to divert the Forces of the King of <hi>Spain</hi> from Aiding the <hi>Emperor.</hi> And here, under pretence of Dependencies, and other Matters, frivilous and ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, in the Opinion of the Neighbour-Princes; he ſwep'd away many Towns, though even the <hi>Turks</hi> themſelves, had they determined impartially, could not but have judged it not only <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nchriſtian</hi> like, but alſo unreaſonable: Or elſe what could any unbiaſſed Man conjecture, but that the <hi>Turks</hi> and the <hi>French</hi> King had
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:32542:61"/>combined to ſhare the <hi>Empire</hi> between them. Yet it would not have been ſo eaſie to have ſtopped an Inundation of <hi>Barbarians,</hi> fluſhed with Victory, as <hi>Lew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is</hi> XIV. imagined. And who can tell, but if they had prevailed, they might have been by this time in the Heart of <hi>France,</hi> and ſhewed him play at his own Weapons. How unjuſtly this King took <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> and other Places in the <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlands,</hi> few are ignorant, even when it was leaſt ſuſpected any Hoſtilities would have happened. But that great City could not ſuffice the Ambition of this Prince; for he ſent his <hi>Dragoons</hi> Abroad when <hi>Spain</hi> was altogether un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provided, and under Pretence of Depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencies, ſwept away whole Provinces, compelling the miſerable Villages, who had been ruined by a lingering War, to part with the ſmall Subſiſtence they had reſerved for the Preſervation of Life, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pretence of Contribution; by which means many of them periſhed in their Houſes, and in the Fields, when they had eaten all the Unclean Things they could find; and thoſe that refuſed, had their Houſes fired about their Ears, and their perſons Tortured, to make them confeſs where they had hid their Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:32542:61"/>or Goods; ſo that ſome of them died under the Tormentors Hands: By which it appears, that <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Zeal to the Church, in <hi>Dragooning</hi> as well the <hi>Papiſts</hi> as the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and even thoſe of <hi>Flanders,</hi> which above all are accounted the moſt zealouſly Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the <hi>Romiſh Superſtition;</hi> and this by way of Surprize, whilſt the <hi>Emperor</hi> of <hi>Germany,</hi> and the other Princes, his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates, as has been hinted, were ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring Glory at the point of their Swords. For this Monarch cares little for ingaging his Armies, it ever having been ſeen, that he has gained little or nothing by the fair dint of the Sword. And indeed, if we conſider how eaſily many ſtrong Towns have been delivered up to him by Garriſons that were able to defend them, the World cannot but conclude, falſe underhand Dealing has been a main Advancement to his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts; by which Methods his vaſt Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures have been frequently ſhrunk, and his Subjects Eſtates ſtretched upon the Tenters to recruit them. Upon this a <hi>French</hi> Rhimer deſcants, as it was found in a <hi>Billet</hi> laid on the King's Dreſſing Table, and Engliſhed thus;
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:32542:62"/>
                  <q>
                     <l>Thy Grandſire <hi>Harry,</hi> the Name of <hi>Great</hi> he bore,</l>
                     <l>Thy Father <hi>Juſt,</hi> but thou'art <hi>Lewis d'Ore.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>A <hi>Lewis d' Ore</hi> is a piece of <hi>French</hi> Gold Coin, by which we may under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that the Poet, ſuch as he was, inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuated, That he gained more by his Gold than by Valour or Vertue. The King was ſurprized at this, and diſſembled the Affront; ſeemed to praiſe the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, and promiſe, if he would diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver himſelf, not only to give him a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, but reward him. But, it ſeems, he had more wit than to truſt himſelf in the Lyon's Paws upon ſuch ſlender Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity: Yet, not to give over his Poetical Whimſey, there was ſoon after found in the ſame Place a Diſtich, in <hi>Engliſh</hi> thus,
<q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Lewis,</hi> the thing cannot be known,</l>
                     <l>I writ it when I was alone.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Hitherto we have endeavoured to ſhew the World the State of Affairs relating to <hi>France,</hi> ſince the coming of <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. to the Crown, who has in all Parts an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered the Prodigie of his Birth, living, as we may term it, in a perpetual Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt of War, to the Scourge of <hi>Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</hi>
                  <pb n="117" facs="tcp:32542:62"/>Few Kingdoms or Eſtates there are, that can boaſt themſelves exempted from the Damage received by the Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities that have frequently happened on that Occaſion. Nay, where his own Power has not reached ſo effectually, that of others has been imployed; not to mention his engaging the Northern Crowns of <hi>Denmark</hi> and <hi>Sweden,</hi> though <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Kingdom, in a tedious and expenſive War, but even ſoliciting the Pirates of <hi>Argier</hi> and <hi>Tripoly,</hi> to Invade the Traffick of the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> by hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring Navigation, and taking their Ships, offering them his Ports, lying advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous for the purpoſe, and, as it were, cajolling Neſts of Thieves, and the Off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcum of Mankind, with whom it is not for the Glory of ſo great a Monarch, as <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. would be thought to be, to have any Converſe withall. But we ſee Ambition will ſtoop low, when it hopes to ſoar aloft.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. when he committed theſe Outrages, and diſturbed the Repoſe of <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> had little regard to his Oath, and the Credit of his Ambaſſadors, who concluded the Peace at <hi>Nimeguen,</hi> nor of the Honour of the King of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, Charles</hi> II. who was <hi>Guarrantee</hi> of
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:32542:63"/>that Peace; nor were the States of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces</hi> leſs abuſed, who had ſo great a hand in bringing that memorable Treaty to paſs, wherein the Miniſters of all the Princes of <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, and at which place moſt of them were in Perſon. But to give a far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Light into this Matter, take the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Proclamation of Peace, publiſhed by the <hi>States.</hi>
               </p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" rend="margQuotes" type="proclamation">
                  <body>
                     <p>BE it known to all Perſons, that, to the Honour and Praiſe of <hi>God the Lord Almighty,</hi> to the Welfare and Furtherance of the Common Good of theſe <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Netherlands</hi> in General, and the good Inhabitants thereof in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, a good, ſure, faithful, and laſting Peace was made at <hi>Nimeguen,</hi> the Tenth Day of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Year 1678. betwen the King of <hi>France</hi> on the one ſide, and the <hi>States General</hi> of the <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Netherlands</hi> on the other; and that the Ratification on both ſides were exchanged in due Form at <hi>Nimeguen</hi> aforeſaid, on the Twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth of this Inſtant <hi>September.</hi> And that in purſuance thereof, all Acts of Hoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and Enmity, as well at Sea, and in freſh Water, as at Land, in all Cities
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:32542:63"/>and Places under their Reſpective Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, without Exceptions; as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe between their Subjects and Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants, of what Condition ſoever they be, muſt ceaſe and determine after the reſpective Terms hereafter mentioned; to wit, after four Weeks, to reckon from this Day the publication of the Peace hath been made in the <hi>Hague,</hi> that is, after the 26<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>October</hi> next, in the <hi>Eaſt</hi> and <hi>North</hi> Seas, from the <hi>Neſs</hi> in <hi>Norway</hi> to the <hi>Lands End</hi> of the <hi>Chanel;</hi> and after Six Weeks, that is, after the 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>November</hi> next, from the ſaid <hi>Lands End</hi> in the <hi>Chanel</hi> to the <hi>Cape St. Vincent;</hi> and after Ten Weeks, that is, after the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>December,</hi> from <hi>Cape St. Vincent</hi> to the <hi>Line;</hi> and laſtly, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Eight Months, that is, after the 28<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>May,</hi> 1679. in all Places of the World. Wherefore all, and every one, as well Subjects and Inhabitants of the ſeveral Provinces of the <hi>Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands,</hi> as thoſe that are under their <hi>High</hi> and <hi>Mighty Dominion</hi> and <hi>Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> are expreſly Charged and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, inviolably to Maintain the Peace, purſuant to the ſaid Treaty; and not to Act in the leaſt contrary thereunto, on pain of being puniſhed as
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:32542:64"/>Diſturbers of the Publick Peace, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Favour or Connivance.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>Done in the Aſſembly of the</hi> States Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <hi>in the</hi> Hague, <date>September 22th. 1678.</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>This may ſufficiently demonſtrate the good and honeſt Intentions of the <hi>States General,</hi> who could not think, but the Word of a King, and the <hi>Moſt Chriſtian</hi> King, as <hi>Lewis the Great</hi> ſtyles himſelf, would continue Sacred and Inviolable. But alaſs! his Ambition and Intereſt weigh down his Words and Oaths; and, in Concluſion, it appeared, that he on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly did it to bind up their Hands, whilſt that he might the more ſecurely prey up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Spaniſh Netherlands</hi> a Country the moſt pleaſant and fruitful in <hi>Europe,</hi> and for which many of his Predeceſſors have heartily longed, but never undertook the Methods he has obſerved to bring it under his Subjection. However, this <hi>Great Monarch</hi> has failed in his Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation, and has frequently been baffled, when his numerous Armies have thought themſelves moſt ſure. Yet, by the way, we may Mark out a peice of <hi>French</hi> Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery, though of an Elder date; by which we may ſee, it is in a Manner the
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:32542:64"/>very <hi>Genius</hi> of the Nation, though more ſuperabundant in <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV.</p>
               <p>It ſo happened in the <hi>Year of our Lord</hi> 1551. that the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> in <hi>Germany</hi> being greatly oppreſſed by the Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> I. <hi>Henry</hi> II. King of <hi>France,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to compaſſionate them, ſent <hi>Monmorency</hi> the <hi>Conſtable,</hi> with four thouſand Horſe and Foot, as it were to Relieve them, who demanded with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Inſinuations and Promiſes of Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, a Paſſage through the City of <hi>Metz,</hi> a City under <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Government. The People in hopes to be delivered from the Ravages the <hi>Imperial</hi> Soldiers com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in their Territories, joyfully con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented; and, in Gratitude, ſpread Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles in the Streets ready furniſhed with Proviſion, for the Soldiers to eat as they Marced through; bringing Barrels of Wine, and other Liquors, to Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modate them, the Magiſtrates waiting upon the <hi>Conſtable</hi> with all Imaginable demonſtrations of Kindneſs and Reſpect; who ſeeing his time, feigned to be trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with a ſudden Fit of the Gout and other Indiſpoſitions, and thereupon in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated the Magiſtrates, that he might have the opportunity of a Place of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirement for ſome time, and that he not
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:32542:65"/>knowing what might befal him in the Wars, or by that Sickneſs, was deſirous to make his Will. The Good-meaning Magiſtrates were highly ſatisfied with the Favour he would doe them, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to contend which of them ſhould have the Honour of entertaining him. But their Joy was ſoon turned into Mourning; for, when the Magiſtrates and moſt of the Gentry were aſſembled in his Chamber, whilſt the Scrivener was making his Will, to which they were to be Witneſſes, he gave private Orders for ſeizing the Gates. And, as ſoon as he knew it was done, riſing up in a fury, he ſuddenly ſtabbed the Mayor of the City to the Heart with his Dagger; which being the Signal to his Guards, they fell upon the reſt that were in the Chamber, and put them to the Sword. This being known, the <hi>French</hi> Soldiers over-ran the Streets, crying out, <hi>The City is won;</hi> and thereupon fell to plundering the Shops and Houſes. So that this City (like the flying-Fiſh in the <hi>Indian</hi> Seas) whilſt it thought to Eſcape one Miſchief, fell into another, as great if not greater: For, of this kind of Fiſh, Sailors report, that being purſued by the <hi>Dolphins,</hi> and finding it
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:32542:65"/>ſelf ready to be devoured, by help of its long Fins, that ſerve for Wings, it ſhoots into the Air, and flies a great many pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, till the Fins grow ſtiff by dryneſs, and then falls into the Sea; but frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, whilſt it is flying, the Cormorants, and other Ravenous Fowl that haunt thoſe Seas, catch them, and by them they are devoured.</p>
               <p>A Second Inſtance of Later Date, we may mention in <hi>Lewis</hi> XIII. Father to the preſent King, when he deſigned to ſeize upon the Dukedom of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> he, by the Advice of <hi>Cardinal Richlieu,</hi> ſent for the old Duke to come to him at his Town of <hi>Lyons,</hi> who, dreading no ſuch Treachery, left <hi>Nancy</hi> the Place of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity, and went to Complement the King who was at the head of his Troops; and after he had payed him that Homage and reſpect he conceived was due to him, he prepared to return, but found him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf miſtaken; for he was Arreſted by the Captain of the King's Guards, upon frivolous Pretences and Claims, and made him deliver up <hi>Nancy</hi> into which he entered as a Conquerour, the ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of which occaſioned the Loſs of the whole <hi>Duchy.</hi> Many Inſtances of the Like Nature, even the <hi>French</hi> Hiſtorians
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:32542:66"/>give us, who make the Actions of their Kings appear as fair and candid as they can. But now we come to <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV.</p>
               <p>The Peace, as we have ſaid, being made, and all <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> Relying on it, and firmly keeping it, except the <hi>French</hi> King; he thought this his time to play his Game, as thinking he had Charmed the Princes, or made them fear the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence of a Rupture. He ſoon forgot his Word, as appears by the <hi>Emperour</hi>'s early Complaint againſt his Proceedings by ſeveral Letters and Memorials, That, contrary to the Peace of <hi>Nimeguen,</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. He continued his Troops in the <hi>Empire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Remaining poſſeſſed of Places they ought to Evacuate.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Requiring Contributions.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Obliging the ten Towns of <hi>Alſace</hi> to take a new Oath, thereby pretending a Sovereignty over them, Erecting a new Court of Appeals, and forbiding any Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes to be made to the <hi>Imperial</hi> Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of <hi>Spires.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. Requiring an Oath from the <hi>Vaſſals</hi> and <hi>Nobles</hi> of <hi>Alſace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. Setting up Pretentions upon the <hi>Vaſſals</hi> of <hi>Metz, Toul,</hi> and <hi>Verdun,</hi> as likewiſe upon other <hi>Imperial</hi> States and Countries</p>
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:32542:66"/>
               <p n="7">7. Conſiſcating the Rents and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues of the <hi>Chapter</hi> of <hi>Straſburg.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. Making new Fortifications at <hi>Scie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtadt</hi> and <hi>Hunningen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9. Not Reſtoring <hi>Monpelgard.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">10. The ſlighting <hi>Daxburgh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11. The Taking <hi>Hamburgh</hi> and <hi>Bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And other Matters. Upon this, the <hi>Diet</hi> of <hi>Ratiſbone,</hi> to whom the Complaint was made, after ſome Deliberation, came to a Reſolution;</p>
               <p>That the proceedings of the <hi>French</hi> King were directly contrary to the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of <hi>Weſtphalia</hi> and <hi>Nimeguen;</hi> that therefore the <hi>Emperor</hi> ſhall be prayed, by Letter or by Embaſſie, in the Name of himſelf and the <hi>Empire,</hi> to demand of the <hi>Moſt Chriſtian King</hi> Reparation for the ſame; and that in the mean time the <hi>French</hi> Miniſters reſiding at the <hi>Imperial</hi> Court and here, ſhall be made acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with this Reſolution of the <hi>Diet,</hi> and that it ſhall be repreſented to them. For what concerns the two firſt Points, That the ſame are directly contrary to the 27th of the Treaty of <hi>Nimeguen,</hi> and the Firſt, Second, and Fourth Articles of the Inſtrument, afterwards ſigned by the Ambaſſadors, for the Executing the ſaid
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:32542:67"/>Treaty, that have been Religiouſly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by the Emperor. That the Third Point is contrary to the 30<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Article of the ſaid Treaty, and the 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Article of the ſaid Inſtrument. That for what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth the Fourth Point, it is known, that the Third Article of the Treaty of <hi>Munſter</hi> ſays, that the Countries of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pper</hi> and <hi>Lower Alſaces,</hi> and the <hi>Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> of <hi>Haguenaw,</hi> ſhall be yeilded to <hi>France,</hi> with an Expreſs Exception of the 10 <hi>Imperial</hi> Towns, and their Rights and Privileges; and that the <hi>French</hi> King ſhall pretend no Superiority over them, or require any Oath or Fidelity from them; and in purſuance of the Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment made at <hi>Nurenburgh,</hi> in the Year 1650. <hi>Haguenaw, Landaw,</hi> and other Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and other of the ſaid ten Towns, more Actually Evacuated by the <hi>French,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out pretending then, and ſeveral years afterwards, to any Sovereignty over the ſaid Towns, or requiring any Oath of Fidelity from them. That afterwards in 1665. Complaints were made to the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et,</hi> of the <hi>French</hi> ſetting up new Preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions; whereupon <hi>Arbitrators</hi> were cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen on the Part of the <hi>Empire</hi> and of <hi>France,</hi> Amicably to determine the ſame, who were ſeveral Years employed in that
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:32542:67"/>work, which was put to an end by the <hi>French</hi> poſſeſſing themſelves of the ſaid Towns, even before the War: That the Treaty of <hi>Nimeguen</hi> Confirms that of <hi>Weſtphalia,</hi> and conſequently that the ſaid Towns ought to have reſtored to them the Rights and Privileges which that ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulates for them. That for the Fifth and Sixth Points, they likwiſe directly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervene the ſaid Treaties. That as to the Seventh, they expect farther Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation in it. That for the Eighth, they cannot Imagine what Right the <hi>French</hi> have to Fortifie <hi>Sclechſtadt,</hi> conſidering what is aboveſaid of thoſe <hi>Free</hi> Towns. For the Ninth and Tenth, the <hi>French</hi> have acted notoriouſly contrary to the <hi>Weſtphalian</hi> and <hi>Nimeguen</hi>-Treaties. For the Eleventh, that <hi>Hamburgh</hi> belongs to ths <hi>Count</hi> of <hi>Naſſaw,</hi> as appears by the Treaty of <hi>Oſnaburgh.</hi> That concerning <hi>Bitſeth,</hi> they expect farther Information. And laſtly, They hope the King will not prejudice the City of <hi>Straſburgh</hi> in its Rights or Privileges, and particularly in that of fortifying <hi>Kiel,</hi> ſo neceſſary for its Security.</p>
               <p>This ſo Early Breach of the Peace, that had been ſo long laboured for by the <hi>Princes</hi> of <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> much diſpleaſed
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:32542:68"/>them, and filled many with Deteſtation, obſerving that <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. went beyond the Bounds of the <hi>Decree</hi> of the <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Conſtance,</hi> which ſays, <hi>That no Faith is to be kept with Hereticks;</hi> but he neither regards his Faith with thoſe the <hi>Romans</hi> unchriſtianly term ſo, nor with <hi>Roman Catholicks.</hi> However, having a mind to ſecure what he had belonging to the <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire,</hi> or Princes dependent, as appears by the Reſolution of the <hi>Diet,</hi> in his detai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſome, and impoſing on others, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Articles agreed on, he ſought to bring the <hi>States</hi> of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces</hi> into an Offenſive and Defenſive Alliance, againſt which all the Provinces, but <hi>Groningen</hi> and <hi>Frieſland</hi> Excepted, who did not ſo long; and their Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions were publiſh'd, declaring, They intended to keep inviolably the Peace and Eſteem they had for his Majeſty's Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, but could not enter into any ſuch Alliance as he required. However, he perſiſted to encroach upon the <hi>Empire,</hi> ſuffering his Troops, that ſhould have been withdrawn, to quarter at diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, eating up that little the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants had left them to ſubſiſt withal; winking at the many Complaints that were made, and proving deaf to the Cries of the People.</p>
               <pb n="129" facs="tcp:32542:68"/>
               <p>This occaſioned the King of <hi>England</hi> to complain by his Ambaſſadors; but this prevailed little or nothing, till he found a Defenſive Alliance was carrying on againſt him; and then, under pretence of Winter Quarter, he drew off ſome of his Troops.</p>
               <p>Let us look a little back upon the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding of <hi>Lewis le Grand,</hi> in the <hi>Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pality</hi> of <hi>Orange,</hi> a place of Sovereign Right for ſome Ages, belonging to the <hi>Illuſtrious Houſe</hi> of <hi>Naſſaw,</hi> and the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance of his preſent Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain.</hi> This <hi>Principality</hi> and City of <hi>Orange,</hi> is very advantageouſly Situate, exceeding fruitful, and for the moſt part Inhabited by <hi>Proteſtants.</hi> Theſe Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations made the <hi>French</hi> King Long to be Maſter of it; for he ſeldom troubles himſelf to War on the <hi>Alps,</hi> or in cold barren Countries. Whereupon, during the Minority of the Prince, without the leaſt Title or juſt Pretence to warrant his Actions, he ſent an Army to take Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of it, in the Year 1660. exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing a great deal of Cruelty and Inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manities upon the Subjects, contrary to the Law of Arms, and of Nations, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moliſhing the Baſtions and ſtrong Forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications; thereby purpoſing to himſelf,
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:32542:69"/>if he ſhould be obliged by the Princes, who looked upon him as an Intruder and an Oppreſſor, to relinquiſh it, he might with more Eaſe repoſſeſs himſelf of it, as he ſaw occaſion. Nay, ſo far extended his Malice, that he not only ruined the Cittadel, but cauſed the Magnificent Monuments of Prince <hi>Maurice</hi>'s Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to be laid in Ruines: And indeed, in the Year 1665. he was obliged to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquiſh that <hi>Principality,</hi> and the <hi>Sieur Zuilychem</hi> to take Poſſeſſion of it for his Maſter. When in <hi>April</hi> that year, as a preſage of the Prince's good Fortune, and future Greatneſs, a Crown of Light darting Rays, appeared over the City of <hi>Orange,</hi> hanging, as it were, in the Air, over the Palace, or place of State, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for his Reception, to Conſolate his diſtreſſed Subjects, who for five years had groaned under the Tyranny of <hi>France.</hi> But their Tranquillity laſted no longer than the Year 1673, for then the <hi>French</hi> King ſuppoſing to make his Arms the Terrour of <hi>Europe,</hi> that ſo he might at pleaſure become the great Arbitre of Peace and War; he, on a ſudden, and very unexpectedly, entered it with his Troops. And although after by an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Article of the Treaty of <hi>Nimeguen,</hi>
                  <pb n="131" facs="tcp:32542:69"/>the <hi>Principality</hi> of <hi>Orange</hi> was reſtored, and the King of <hi>England</hi> was <hi>Guarrantee</hi> of that Peace; yet the unwearied In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croachments of the <hi>French</hi> Troops of <hi>Provence,</hi> and the Intrigues of the <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Orange,</hi> rendered daily the Subjects of the <hi>Principality</hi> more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſie, till in the Year 1682. <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. in a time of full Peace, as well with the <hi>States</hi> as <hi>Confederate</hi> Princes, commanded a powerful Army to take poſſeſſion of it, without any manner of colour or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text, but the <hi>Turkiſh Motto,</hi> viz.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Sic Volo, ſic Jubeo; ſtat pro Ratione Voluntas,</l>
                  <l>This I will, this I command;</l>
                  <l>My Will it does for Reaſon ſtand.</l>
               </q>
               <p>And thereby his booted Miſſionaries or Dragoons, acted inhumane Barbari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties on the Inhabitants, unparallel'd in any Reign but his own. And here for an Eſſay of his inſupportable Vanity, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of a Kindneſs unuſual amongſt Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and derogatory to Majeſty it ſelf, we muſt not omit; That in a <hi>Breve</hi> in Favour of the late Prince of <hi>Conde,</hi> as Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrator of the Duke of <hi>Long aville, Lewis</hi> XIV. had the fooliſh Confidence to treat his preſent Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> with the Title of <hi>Meſſire William, Count</hi> of
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:32542:70"/>
                  <hi>Naſſaw,</hi> living at <hi>Amſterdam</hi> in <hi>Holland,</hi> as if thereby he had entailed upon himſelf the <hi>Principality</hi> of <hi>Orange,</hi> which at that time was the <hi>Supream Title</hi> of <hi>King William.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for the Actings of the <hi>French</hi> King in this <hi>Principality,</hi> we ſhall give you a brief Account, in the words of <hi>Monſieur <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e Chambrun, viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">The diſmal Cruelties (ſays he) acted upon my unhappy Country, and the City of <hi>Orange,</hi> ſo famous by the Greatneſs of its Princes, is at this day nought but a diſmal Heap, where one cannot enter without treading upon its Ruines. She is at this day a doleful Monument of Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty and Injuſtice. I cannot perſuade my ſelf, that the Ruines of <hi>Troy,</hi> or <hi>Carthage</hi> were more terrible than theſe I have mentioned, ſince to one that beholds them at a diſtance, they appear the Habitations of <hi>Oſtriches</hi> and <hi>Owls.</hi> If Poſterity ſhall enquire the cauſe of this horrid Deſolation, as certainly it muſt, the Account that ſhall be given of them will no doubt tend to the diſhonour of <hi>France.</hi> Hiſtory will not forget to hand down to ſucceeding Ages, the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roick Vertues of our <hi>Prince,</hi> when ſhe comes to relate the Ruine of his Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories, and Deſolation of his Subjects,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:32542:70"/>and when they ſhall underſtand, that the Juſtice, the Sincerity, the Valour, and indefatigable Care of maintaining the Liberty of <hi>Europe,</hi> were the only Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives that induced the <hi>French</hi> King thus to treat an <hi>Illuſtrious Prince;</hi> doubtleſs they will ſay, This has been the moſt diſmal and moſt corrupt of all Ages, ſince that which ought to have been the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration of the <hi>Great Ones</hi> of the Earth, was the Object of their Averſion and Hatred. If this great Prince would have conſented to the overturning of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of his Country, as he was ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly courted ſo to doe; if he would have taken part with thoſe that aim at the enſlaving <hi>Europe:</hi> In a word, If he would have betrayed his Country, and broken his Faith to his Allies, he might have mounted a Throne then offered him: But becauſe he loved his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try better than his Intereſt, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred his Honour to the richeſt Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages, and the Liberty of <hi>Europe</hi> to a Crown, it behoved his great Actions ſhould be regarded with Hatred, and followed with the unjuſteſt of Treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. But although this Conduct has been blamed in all the Courts of <hi>Europe;</hi> yet nothing has been done to oppoſe it.
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:32542:71"/>And I am forced to ſay, 'Tis the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour of all <hi>Europe,</hi> to have ſuffered a great Prince to expoſe ſo often his Life with the greateſt Bravery, for its Good and Liberty, and at the ſame time to abandon his Intereſt with ſuch an unaccountable Neglect. <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> was obliged to protect and aſſiſt this Prince, not only as being the <hi>Guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantee</hi> of the Peace of <hi>Nimeguen,</hi> but from the Principle of Blood and Alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance. And indeed, what Honour can Accrue to <hi>England,</hi> to ſee a Sovereignty wreſted by unjuſt violence, from a Prince that had Married the Heireſs of <hi>Three Kingdoms.</hi> As for me, I cannot think of the Deſolation of my Country with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſaying, amidſt my Tears, with <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remiah, How doth the City ſit ſolitary,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Is it nothing to you, all you that paſs by?</hi> &amp;c. In ſhort, is it poſſible (continues he) that a man that loves his God, his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and his Prince, could behold with dry Eyes ſo many Ruines as I ſaw in the Principality of <hi>Orange.</hi>
                  </q> 
                  <hi>Hic Seges</hi> eſt <hi>ubi</hi> Troja <hi>fuit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For this, ſee the Book of this learned Man, Printed at the <hi>Hague</hi> the laſt Year, Page 61, 62. Nor was it only the Buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings that ſuffered, but the People alſo,
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:32542:71"/>who for the moſt part, as well <hi>Papiſts</hi> as <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> were plundered of all they had, and many of them Dragooned out of their Religion, by the ſame barbarous Methods as were taken with his own Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of the <hi>Reformed Religion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. is ſeldom without preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to quarrel with his Neighbours; for, he has for that purpoſe, and to exalt himſelf <hi>Chief Monarch</hi> of <hi>Europe,</hi> ſet up a Chamber at <hi>Metz,</hi> called <hi>the Sovereign Court,</hi> before which he cauſes to be Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Kings and Princes (well knowing they will not appear then) under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence their Lands are Dependences, or under the Claim of antient Titles or Claims, for which himſelf can give no Reaſon; he cauſes them to be condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned as forfeited. And from this Court, where himſelf is both Judge and Jury, he will admit of no Appeal, but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds to take poſſeſſion, by ſending his Troops to quarter there, and Leavy great Contributions upon the Inhabitants, that, ſo by Impoveriſhing them, as he u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes his own Subjects, he may the better keep them under. And by this means he adjudged part of the King of <hi>Sweeden</hi>'s Terretories, and ſeized on the Countries of the Primes of <hi>Montbelliard, Pellite
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:32542:72"/>Pierre,</hi> and divers others, ſwallowing up Provinces like the <hi>Great Leviathan,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out making any Account of Rights or Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, though the time peradventure is at hand wherein he will be obliged to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorge them with Intereſt. His Eye has been indeed a long while up <hi>Italy,</hi> ſoa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that way towards the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy,</hi> which made him deal under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand with the Duke of <hi>Mantua</hi> for the ſtrong Garriſon of <hi>Caſſel,</hi> which ſerves as an Inlet over the <hi>Alps.</hi> Nor had <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neva</hi> eſcaped his Bombs, had not the <hi>Swiſſe-Cantons,</hi> fearful of their own Safety, declared with much warmth, to ſtand by that <hi>Proteſtant</hi> City with all their Forces.</p>
               <p>The Peace being concluded with <hi>Spain, Lewis</hi> XIV. finding himſelf uneaſie to be out of Action, picks a Quarrel with that Nation about 500000 Crowns he pretended were to be reſtored for da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages done in the <hi>Weſt Indias,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon ſent the Duke's <hi>D' Eſtree</hi> and <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temer,</hi> with a Squadron of <hi>Men of War,</hi> to block up <hi>Cadiz,</hi> and to take and deſtroy all ſuch Merchants-ſhips and Galleys as they light on. And indeed, they did conſiderable Miſchief againſt that <hi>Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time</hi> Town, by caſting Bombs, and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Fire-ſhips into the Harbour. Nor
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:32542:72"/>thought they this ſufficient, but they would have compelled the <hi>Dutch Men of War,</hi> who were at Peace with <hi>Spain,</hi> to aſſiſt them, and by that Means Involved them in an open Violation of the League. For, the latter of the Dukes having with him Eight Sail of <hi>Men of War,</hi> and happening to meet two Ships belonging to the <hi>States,</hi> Commanded by Capt. <hi>Ewycke,</hi> and Capt. <hi>Mevart,</hi> he compelled them to Sail with him towards <hi>Cadiz.</hi> However, in the Night the former ſtood away, and chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged his Courſe; upon which, he was followed by the <hi>Seiur Belle Iſle,</hi> who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing come up with him the next morning, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ired ſeveral ſhot at him; whereupon the <hi>Dutch</hi> Captain returned him a Broad-ſide, and began a ſharp Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which laſted four Hours; but then the Captain being killed with a Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non ſhot, as likewiſe a great many of the Men killed, and more <hi>French</hi> Ships ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing in ſight, they ſent on board the <hi>French</hi> to let them know, they would make no longer Reſiſtence. This open Violation being highly reſented by the <hi>Sates General,</hi> Monſieur <hi>D' Avaux,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> Ambaſſador at the <hi>Hague,</hi> put in a diſſembling <hi>Memorial</hi> to excuſe it, in which he complained, <q rend="margQuotes">That Captain
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:32542:73"/>
                     <hi>Ewyeke,</hi> had given the Duke his Word to go with him to <hi>Cadiz,</hi> but changing his Courſe by Night, he gave ground to ſuſpect his Intentions; and that the <hi>Sieur Belle Iſle</hi> following him, and he finding himſelf alone with one of his moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Majeſty's Ships, put out his Cannon, and came with all the Sail he could upon the <hi>French</hi> man, who ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red three ſhot one after another, as a Signal that he ſhould not advance any farther, to which the <hi>Hollander</hi> return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a whole Broad-ſide of 25 peices of Cannon, whereupon the ſight began: That the <hi>Dutch</hi> Captain being killed, the other Officers ſent on board the <hi>Sieur D' Belle Iſle</hi> to let him know, that they would make good the Word of their Captain: That the <hi>Sieur</hi> received the Meſſenger very kindly, and after having Lamented the Loſs of the <hi>Dutch</hi> Captain, a very brave Man, ſent him back, and gave them time till the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening to repair their Ship (of which the <hi>French</hi> had not leſs need, having fourteen Men killed and ſix wounded.)</q> And ſo he goes on to ſalve up the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, by endeavouring to make the <hi>Dutch</hi> Captain the Aggreſſor.</p>
               <p>The Damage the <hi>French</hi> King did
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:32542:73"/>the <hi>Spaniards</hi> at Sea and upon their Coaſt, were received but trivial by the King, and therefore contrary to Oath and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe he cauſed all the <hi>Spaniards</hi> Eſtates and Effects in the <hi>New Conqueſts</hi> to be ſeized; ſo that after ſome Debates, the Court of <hi>Spain</hi> found it ſelf under a Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of complying with his perempto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Demands; and thereupon the <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs de Los Balbaces,</hi> obliged himſelf to pay the 500000 Crowns at one entire Payment, ſo ſoon as the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Plate Fleet arrived; and this Agreement was taken by the <hi>French</hi> as ſatisfaction, yet it proved not ſo; for, the <hi>Men of War</hi> being yet Abroad, took, after a long and deſperate Fight, two of their Galleys, which <hi>Monſieur D' Avaux</hi> undertook likewiſe to excuſe, by another <hi>Memorial</hi> to the <hi>State, viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">That the <hi>Sieur Forran,</hi> that had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded a Squadron of his <hi>Moſt Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Majeſty's</hi> Ships, not knowing of the Agreement and Accommodation con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded by the <hi>French</hi> Ambaſſadors at <hi>Madrid,</hi> concerning the Five hundred thouſand Crowns, had met on the Coaſt of <hi>Biſcay</hi> two <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Galleyoons, moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted each with Sixty four Guns, ſailing towards <hi>Cadiz,</hi> and that endeavouring to
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:32542:74"/>hinder them from going thither, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his firſt Orders, there enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a very obſtinate Fight between them, which laſted a Day and an half, when two Ships of the ſame <hi>Squadron</hi> coming in, and joining with the <hi>Sieur Forran,</hi> the Galleyoons yielded, and were carried into <hi>Rochell:</hi> That his <hi>Moſt Chriſtian Majeſty</hi> having received certain Advice thereof, had ſent Orders for the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charging the ſaid Galleyoons, and had commanded him to tell the <hi>States,</hi> that this Accident ſhould not make any alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration in the Accommodation: That the Count <hi>Stirum,</hi> their Admiral, being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at the end of the Fight; and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving anſwered the <hi>Sieur Forran</hi> (who ſent to him to know,</q> whether he would aſſiſt the <hi>Spaniards</hi>) <q rend="margQuotes">that he had no Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to intermeddle with this Diſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and retiring thereupon after he had ſaluted the <hi>French</hi> Ships; his <hi>Moſt Chriſtian Majeſty</hi> had farther directed him to let the <hi>States</hi> know, how well ſatisfied he is with the Orders they had given the <hi>Count de Stirum,</hi> and with his prudent Conduct in purſuance of them.</q>
               </p>
               <p>By this we may ſee, whilſt the <hi>Dutch</hi> made a Conſcience of the leaſt Breach,
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:32542:74"/>and had their hands tied from aſſiſting their Allies by a Treaty, they would not break with <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. who could never find any ſtrong enough for his Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, when he ſaw it advantageous to break it. However, Heaven does not wink at ſuch Actions, nor leave them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puniſhed; for much about this time, <hi>Lewis the Great</hi> fell into a raging Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, occaſioned by an ulcerous <hi>Fiſtula</hi> in his Fundament, and knew in ſome kind, what it was to be miſerable, who had made many thouſands ſo. All the chief Chirurgions of <hi>France</hi> were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted about this matter, and concluded his Life was in danger, unleſs his <hi>Royal Bum</hi> was Cut and Launced. And, in fine, an Inciſion was made, and after that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers others, which kept him long in Bed, and conſequently put the thoughts quite out of his Head, of plotting a far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Diſturbance in the World at that time. Yet his Creatures were not Idle; for, to pick a new Quarrel, the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of <hi>Maeubuge</hi> ſet up the Arms of <hi>France</hi> in divers parts of the <hi>Spaniſh Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlands,</hi> under the old pretence of Boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daries and Limits of Dependencies; and although Complaints were made, yet little was returned in Satisfaction but a
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:32542:75"/>few Excuſes, and a Promiſe, that it ſhould be conſidered at a more convenient time, and that Perſons on either ſide ſhould be appointed to adjuſt the Limits, And, at the fame time they proceeded to build ſtrong Fortreſſes (contrary to the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) near <hi>Huneguen,</hi> and in the Territories of the <hi>Margrave</hi> of <hi>Baden;</hi> of which the <hi>Emperor</hi> complained by his Ambaſſadors, declaring how Religiouſly himſelf and all the Princes of the Empire intended to obſerve the Treaty. But this little availed; for the <hi>French</hi> went on with their Deſigns, and upon the ſetting out the Boundaries in the <hi>Spaniſh Netherlands,</hi> and on the Frontiers of the <hi>Empire,</hi> made unreaſonable Exactions of Places no ways belonging to them, nor any where aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned in the Treaty of <hi>Nimeguen.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> which the King of <hi>Spain</hi> was obliged to acquieſce, as having Exhauſted his Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures in a tedious War, and not in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to contend alone, when the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates</hi> did not hold themſelves obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to take his part, <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. not content with Matters, and the Extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Trouble he had given his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours on this ſide the <hi>Alps,</hi> began to breath towards the Dominion of <hi>Italy.</hi> He remembred his Predeceſſors, by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:32542:75"/>Inroads to that fruitful Country, had ſnatched many a pleaſant Morſel, and not only ſatiated their Ambition, but enriched themſelves till the Time of <hi>Charles</hi> V. Emperor and King of <hi>Spain,</hi> as likewiſe <hi>Philip</hi> II. King of <hi>Spain,</hi> in whoſe Reigns the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Monarchy was at the higheſt it ever was known to be, when it was graſped from the <hi>French</hi> with a hard hand, and they have ſince had little pretenſions to any place be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond that vaſt ridge of Mountains. But this King ſtrikes in with the Duke of <hi>Mantua</hi> for his ſtrong Fortreſs on the Frontier, for an Inlet into <hi>Italy;</hi> and, though it was oppoſed by all the <hi>Italian</hi> Princes, the <hi>French</hi> Gold out-balanced their Sollieitations, to prevent that Duke's ſurre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dering a place, which would at one time or other be the occaſion of ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing up his other Territories.</p>
               <p>The <hi>French</hi> King having poſſeſſed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of <hi>Caſſel,</hi> delayed not to threaten an Invaſion of <hi>Italy.</hi> This made moſt of the Princes combine in a ſtrict League, and ſollicite the <hi>Pope</hi> to his immediate Protection, and that he would become Head of the <hi>League.</hi> Theſe Proceedings ſtop the Ambitious Monarch at that time, but hindered him not from fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:32542:76"/>ſeveral pretenſions. Nor did he defer to ſhew his angry Reſentment, by picking a Quarrel with the City of <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noa,</hi> an <hi>Italian</hi> City, and the Head of a famous Republick, ſituate advantage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly on the Sea, upon a riſing Hill, there being a large <hi>Bay</hi> before it: So that he conjectured, that getting this Inlet and Harbour, he might facilitate the large Enterprizes he had caſt in his mind. The occaſion or Grounds of his Quarrel was about Ceremonies, and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vial Matters, but where the Power is, and in a hand like that of <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. it is eaſie to find occaſion of Offence, or to ſuggeſt one. Long he ſtood not to digeſt or debate the matter, before a conſiderable Fleet was equipped, which put ſome of the neighbouring Nations into doubt to what it might tend. Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes were given out it was deſigned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Infidel Piratical Governments of <hi>Argier, Tripoly,</hi> &amp;c. though People of better Underſtanding conſidering how he had favoured and incouraged thoſe Miſcreants, to make Spoil and Robbery upon the Seas, whilſt himſelf was doing the like at Land, and ſhedding Streams of <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Blood, were of a contrary O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion. Nor did the wonder laſt, for
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:32542:76"/>the Fleet being ready, immediately ſet Sail, and ſtood away for the Coaſt of <hi>Italy;</hi> and his Threats were ſent to the <hi>Doge</hi> and Senate of <hi>Genoua</hi> to comply with his demands of Satisfaction and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration which, appeared to them ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable, that they were rejected, and the City prepared for its Defence.</p>
               <p>The <hi>French</hi> Fleet of about Thirty <hi>Men of War,</hi> beſides <hi>Fireſhips</hi> and <hi>Tenders,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing come to an Anchor before the <hi>Bay,</hi> drew into a Line to block up the Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and fired very furiouſly; which was anſwered from the Cannon of the Town, thoſe in the few Ships that lay under the Shoar, and the Forts, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Works that lay as Curtains and Bull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>works. But the Cannon from the <hi>French</hi> Fleet doing little other damage, than beating down ſome Chimneys, the Tops of Steeples, and a few of the Battlements, they drew in under the Favour of the Night ſeveral heavy Galleys, with Gab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bions and Earth on their Decks, gaurded by <hi>Men of War</hi> and <hi>Fireſhips,</hi> from whence they played their Bombs, without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the Churches and Religious Houſes, that for the moſt part ſtood near the Sea, and had with them ſuch Fatal Succeſs, that a great part of that
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:32542:77"/>Famous City was layed in Ruines by their beating down and blowing up. Yet the <hi>French</hi> attempting to Land, were beaten off with conſiderable Loſs; who find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Governour of <hi>Milain</hi> was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring to come down with Forces to the Aſſiſtence of the <hi>Genoiſe,</hi> and that in all likelihood the Princes of <hi>Italy</hi> would not ſtand neuter, the <hi>French</hi> Admiral admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thoſe that were ſent off to come on board him, in order to treat of Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but was ſo extravagant in his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, that nothing was concluded at that time. But the Inhabitants finding the City almoſt ruined by the Bombs, which played upon them continually, and deſpairing of any Relief by Sea, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to Murmur and Mutiny, which ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtened the Agreement, very diſhonourable to that <hi>State,</hi> which had ſometimes Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it over the Ocean, and often defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it ſelf againſt the moſt powerful of <hi>States</hi> and <hi>Kings.</hi> For nothing would ſatisfie <hi>Lewis</hi> the <hi>Great,</hi> but that their <hi>Senators</hi> ſhould come into <hi>France,</hi> and beg his Pardon, and humble themſelves before his Greatneſs. A ſtrange ſort of Acknowledgment, when themſelves had received the Injury, which four Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions could not make Good. Yet what
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:32542:77"/>muſt be muſt be. Many other things were conſidered which mainly puffed up <hi>Lewis the Great,</hi> who now ſlattered him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be the Terrour of <hi>Europe</hi> as well by Sea as Land, not imagining but this dreadful Example, and the fear of bom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing, would make others cautious how they incurred the Fury of ſuch a Fire-Drake. But it ſeems his Terrour reached not ſo far as the Shoar of <hi>Africa.</hi> For even the Pirates of <hi>Argiers,</hi> whom he had ſo much countenanced, and to whom he had allowed his Ports as a ſafegaurd of Retreat, and for bringing in Prizes, and thereby a better Opportunity to rob his Neighbours; made no Scruple to break with him, and brave him, by ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king his Ships even in the Mouth of his own Harbours. This no doubt vexed <hi>Lewis the Great,</hi> and made him think him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf undervalued, if he ſhould put up ſuch Affronts. And though perhaps he was loth to ſhed <hi>Infidel</hi> Blood, having ſo long deal'd in that of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> which he had poured out in Rivolets, he found the Eyes of the Neighbouring Princes were upon him, and that his Greatneſs would ſuffer an Eclipſe if he diſſembled it, and that he ſhould become cheap to the World; notwithſtanding his being in
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:32542:78"/>League with the <hi>Grand Signiour,</hi> under whoſe protection this Government is, he ſet forth a Fleet to bomb it, but had not the Succeſs as before <hi>Genoa.</hi> For, the obſtinate <hi>Turks</hi> being ſtrongly forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, made a vigorous Defence; whereby his Ships were conſtrained to keep off at Sea. However, having ſpent a great many of his Fireballs at a Diſtance, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doing any extraordinary Damage, and not daring to land any Force; when Count <hi>D'Eſtrees,</hi> the Admiral, ſent to demand the <hi>French</hi> Slaves, and Repa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration for ſeveral Ships taken, and the breaking the Truce, all the Anſwer that could be obtained was, to have his <hi>Conſul</hi> that reſided there to negotiate Affairs, halled out of Priſon, and Ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med into a Cannon or Mortarpeice, and by its being fired, ſhot towards the Fleet. So that this great Preparation was fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated, and the <hi>French</hi> could only boaſt of ſome few Slaves that ſcaped on boards, as they lay before the City, pretending they were Conſtrained to return, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the boiſterouſneſs of thoſe Seas, through the far Advancement of the Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; when, on the contrary, it may be ſaid, to the Honour of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that a ſmall Squadron of our Ships
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:32542:78"/>has reduced thoſe <hi>Barbarians</hi> frequently to ſuch ſtraits, that they have been ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to truckle under what Terms has been thought fit to have been impoſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. having procured Cardinal <hi>Furſtemburg,</hi> his Creature, to be <hi>Coad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jutor</hi> to the <hi>Elector</hi> of <hi>Collogne,</hi> and that <hi>Elector</hi> dying in <hi>June</hi> 1688, he immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately ſtruck in to make a Party; and, to ſupport the Intereſt of <hi>Furſtemburg,</hi> and to procure his being choſen, as know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf ſhould have the Advantage, and ſuppoſing to hector others out of their Pretentions, the Count <hi>D' Avaux,</hi> on the 10 of <hi>June</hi> preſented the following <hi>Memorial</hi> to the <hi>States General, viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">That he was commanded to let them know, that the King his Maſter deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring nothing more than to preſerve the Peace of <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> his Majeſty was willing to prevent whatever might trouble it. And ſeeing nothing is more capable of preſerving the publick Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillity in the preſent Conjuncture, than if the Princes, Neighbours of the <hi>Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorate</hi> of <hi>Cologne,</hi> ſhould not leave the <hi>Chapter</hi> in an entire Liberty to proceed Canonically to the Election of a new <hi>Archbiſhop;</hi> That his Majeſty in ſuch caſe could not refuſe the <hi>Canons</hi> and
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:32542:79"/>
                     <hi>Chapter</hi> the Aſſiſtence they might ſtand in need of, for the Preſervation of their Rights, and for the Security of the Peace of the Country that depended on the <hi>Electorate;</hi> And if any one ſhould go about to cauſe any Troops to march towards the ſaid <hi>Electorate,</hi> under what pretence ſoever it may be, and to force the <hi>Canons</hi> and <hi>Chapter</hi> in any Manner whatever, or to uſe any force or violence againſt the Places or Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try of the ſaid <hi>Archbiſhoprick,</hi> his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty will ſend thither, at the ſame time, all the Succor that is neceſſary, to Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain thoſe that have the Adminiſtration thereof in all the Rights that belong to them. But if the <hi>States</hi> neighbouring to the <hi>Archbiſhoprick,</hi> do leave the <hi>Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> in an intire Liberty to chuſe a ſit and worthy Perſon, and in caſe there be no moving of Troops either in the <hi>Empire,</hi> or in the Territories of this <hi>State,</hi> or in the <hi>Spaniſh Netherlands,</hi> to Intimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date the ſaid <hi>Chapter,</hi> thoſe of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty will not likewiſe doe any thing that may be able to trouble the publick Tranquillity, or ever give the leaſt Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions to thoſe that are well In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentioned for the Maintenance of the Peace.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="151-181" type="pages">
               <pb n="151" facs="tcp:32542:79"/>
               <p>Theſe were the pretences of <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. to Amuſe his Neighbours; but they were too Apprehenſive, and knew him too well to be lulled into a Security, For indeed, he longed for this <hi>Electorate,</hi> and knew no better ways to gain it than by placing a Perſon in it wholly devoted to his Intereſt; and, to accompliſh this, Parties were made, and vaſt Treaſures expended: But, finding the <hi>Pope</hi> not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny way inclined to <hi>Furſtemburg,</hi> inſomuch as he had not approved or confirmed his <hi>Coadjutorſhip,</hi> and thinking he ſhould fail in his Expectation; he cauſed his Troops, contrary to what had been propoſed, to march to the Frontiers, and a great ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>French</hi> came privately Armed into the Cities of <hi>Cologne</hi> and <hi>Bonne;</hi> and the <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal,</hi> not like a peaceable Church man, but like a Martial Prince, came with Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Troops at his heels, which gave Apprehenſions to ſome, of the Danger that might befal them if they refuſed to give their Voice; and on the 19 of <hi>July</hi> they proceeded to Election, where after ſome Conteſt of the 24 <hi>Canons</hi> that have Voices, 13 were gained for <hi>Furſtemburg,</hi> 9 gave their Voices for the Prince <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> Brother to the Duke of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> and one for the Prince of <hi>Neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg:</hi>
                  <pb n="150" facs="tcp:32542:80"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="151" facs="tcp:32542:80"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="152" facs="tcp:32542:81"/>This puffed up the <hi>Cardinal</hi>'s mind, as thinking certianly he had car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried the day, and was capable of gratify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Maſter to the full. But then there aroſe other Scruples; for, thoſe that had voted againſt him made their proteſt, alledging that the <hi>Cardinal,</hi> as being Biſhop of <hi>Straſburgh,</hi> could not, without the <hi>Pop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>'s Diſpenſation be choſen, but by Poſtulation, which required two Thirds of the <hi>Electors</hi> to be for him, and that it was ſufficient for any other to have nine, in caſe the Voices were divided be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween two; but if they were divided a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt ſeveral, it was neceſſary that he that was poſtulated ſhould have double the number that any other had. So that Prince <hi>Clement</hi> having 9 Voices, and the <hi>Cardinal</hi> but 13, he was by virtue of his <hi>Holineſs</hi>'s Diſpenſation duly elected. However, the <hi>Cardinal</hi> and his Party, went and Proclaimed himſelf in the Choire of the <hi>Metropolitan</hi> Church, and the next day the Election of Prince <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> was proclaimed. Upon this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute, the <hi>French</hi> Troops began to move nearer. The <hi>Cardinal</hi> took poſſeſſion of the Palace, and both parties ſent to the <hi>Pope</hi> to be confirmed and approved in the Election. However, the Election of
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:32542:81"/>
                  <hi>Liege</hi> coming on, the <hi>Cardinal</hi> departed to <hi>Bonne,</hi> and from thence to <hi>Liege,</hi> in hopes to be elected there. But the <hi>French</hi> Gold, it ſeems, had not a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Opperation; For here he fared worfe than before, for the <hi>Baron</hi> of <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deren,</hi> Great Dean of the <hi>Cathedral,</hi> was choſen in the 17 of <hi>Auguſt, Biſhop</hi> and <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Liege,</hi> having 20 Voices, and the <hi>Cardinal</hi> but 18. And after the Election had been proclaimed, he was accompanied by the Prince of <hi>Neuburg,</hi> Great Maſter of the <hi>Tutonick</hi> Order, to his Palace, where he received the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plements of the Chief of the Country. So that the <hi>Cardinal</hi> ſinding himſelf de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, retired to <hi>Bonne,</hi> and proceeded to ſtrengthen himſelf in that Place, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately drawing in ſome <hi>French</hi> Troops that were advanced in order thereto. And <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. fretting to ſee his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects proſper no better, prepared for Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtility, ordering a new Leavy 10000 Foot and 6000 Horſe to be ſpeedily rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; giving out Commiſſions for that purpoſe, making a great many new Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Officers as <hi>Lieutenant Genera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> Mareſchals de Camp,</hi> and <hi>Brigadiers</hi> of Horſe and Foot, commanding the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darms</hi> and <hi>Light-horſe</hi> to form a Camp
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:32542:82"/>at <hi>Acheres,</hi> and the Mareſchal <hi>d'Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> was ſent to <hi>Flanders</hi> to form an Army of 25 Men near <hi>Mabeuge.</hi> How this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees with the <hi>Memorial</hi> of his Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor, we make the Reader judge. Upon notice that the <hi>Pope</hi> had declared in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of Prince <hi>Clement</hi> of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> Miniſters at <hi>Cologne</hi> preſſed that City to a Neutrality, offering it if they would take no more Troops in. But they were too wary to truſt to ſuch Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, when they could expect nothing more than to be ſuddenly inveſted. Whereupon they permitted the <hi>Mareſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chal</hi> to advance on the 11 of <hi>September</hi> with 2600 Foot and 100 Dragoons of the <hi>Circle</hi> of <hi>Weſtphalia.</hi> So that having left part of theſe Forces that made the Garriſon 5000 ſtrong, and viewed the <hi>Fortifications,</hi> he returned to <hi>Weſle.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout this time we had Notice that the <hi>Dutch</hi> Fleet was about to ſet Sail for <hi>England,</hi> which made Monſieur <hi>Albeville,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> Ambaſſador at the <hi>Hague,</hi> ſet forth, by a <hi>Memorial,</hi> amongſt other things, how deſirous his Maſter was to obſerve the Peace of <hi>Nimegnen,</hi> when at that time his Armies had entered the <hi>Palatinate</hi> under pretence of ſecuring the Right and Pretenſions of the Ducheſs of
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:32542:82"/>
                  <hi>Orleance;</hi> and General <hi>Monclar</hi> Inveſted <hi>Philipshu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> in which Count <hi>Maximilian</hi> of <hi>Staremourg</hi> was Governour, with a Gariſon of 3000 Men, and <hi>Keyſerlanter</hi> after two Aſſaults was taken, and <hi>Oppen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heim, Altzheim</hi> and <hi>Worms,</hi> were compelled to receive <hi>French</hi> Garriſons. They made themſelves Maſters likewiſe of <hi>Neuſtadt, Spires,</hi> and many other Places, and put the Countries of <hi>Wertemburg, Franconia,</hi> and <hi>Suabia</hi> under Contribution, and that the <hi>Dauphin</hi> might partake herein, he was ſent to the Camp before <hi>Philipsburg,</hi> which Place was defended with much Bravery; a great number of the <hi>French,</hi> and many of note were killed in the Attacks and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous Sallies of the beſieged. Yet whilſt the Siege went on, the <hi>French</hi> found an opportunity to ſurprize and Garriſon <hi>Treeves</hi> and <hi>Mayence,</hi> and put the Counties of <hi>Hanau, Darmſtadt, Solms,</hi> and the adjacent Countries under Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribution. They likewiſe ſeized on <hi>Hei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delburg;</hi> and on the 29 of <hi>October,</hi> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all that could be expected of a ſmall Garriſon againſt a powerful Army and deſpairing of Relief, <hi>Philipsburg</hi> was ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendered upon very Advantageous Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles. <hi>viz. That the Garriſon which then conſiſted not of above</hi> 1800 <hi>Men, ſhould
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:32542:83"/>march out, with Arms and Baggage, Drums beating, and Colours flying, and four Pieces of Cannon; the Garriſon to be Conducted to</hi> Ulme. Nor had it been ſo eaſily ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, had not the Governour been diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled from giving neceſſary Orders, by a dangerous Sickneſs. Nor were the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles any better obſerved, that what has been uſual with the <hi>French,</hi> or, as ſome will have it, by the <hi>Turks.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This ſtrong <hi>Hold</hi> being in their Hands, they ſoon poſſeſſed themſelves of almoſt all the Towns and Villages upon the <hi>Rhine,</hi> relating to the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting great Spoil, and many Outrages. They took <hi>Frankendale</hi> and <hi>Manheim,</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering the <hi>Elect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ate</hi> of <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e,</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding Two hundred thouſand Crowns of the Country of <hi>Juli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rs,</hi> to be paid in Eight Days, upon pain of Military Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution, and the like Contributions from the Country of <hi>Liege;</hi> which put the poor People, who had ſo often been ruined by the War, into the greateſt Surprize imaginable.</p>
               <p>Theſe Proceedings obliged the <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs</hi> of <hi>Baden,</hi> the <hi>Emperor's Plenepotentia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> and <hi>Principal Commiſſioner</hi> at the <hi>Diet</hi> of <hi>Ratiſbone,</hi> to repreſent to them the State of Affairs, in the following man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="157" facs="tcp:32542:83"/>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">That he doubts not, but that the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voys, Counſellors,</hi> and <hi>Deputies of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectorate</hi> Princes, and <hi>States</hi> of the <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire,</hi> are fully ſatisfied and informed, in what manner the Crown of <hi>France,</hi> beſides the former Acts of Hoſtility, has lately, for want of Succour, taken the Fortreſs of <hi>Philipſburgh,</hi> and afterwards, in a Hoſtile manner, attack'd, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged the remaining Places of the <hi>Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinate,</hi> to wit, <hi>Manheim, Fredricksburgh, Frankendale,</hi> as likewiſe the Fortreſs of <hi>Coblets,</hi> in the <hi>Electorate</hi> of <hi>Tryger,</hi> as likewiſe made Incurſions into the <hi>Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles</hi> of <hi>Suabia,</hi> and <hi>Franconia.</hi> That ſince the ſaid Crown does every day carry the Fire of the War farther into the <hi>Empire,</hi> having already poſſeſſed it ſelf of almoſt the four <hi>Electorates</hi> on the <hi>Rhine,</hi> by Force, and of other Lordſhips and Towns; ſo that the whole <hi>Empire</hi> is in danger to be intirely Deſolate. And ſince that the extream Neceſſity, to which things are now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, plainly ſhews, That the Delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of the <hi>Diet</hi> upon the Grievances complained of, and the Aſſiſtences de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, are no longer to be waited for; it ought with all ſpeed to be taken into deliberation in the <hi>Colleges</hi> of the
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:32542:84"/>
                     <hi>Empire,</hi> to declare without any delay theſe Irruptions to be a War againſt the <hi>Empire,</hi> and to reſiſt the Hoſtilities of <hi>France,</hi> with their whole and united Force; and that accordingly his <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial</hi> Majeſty, out of the paternal Care he has for the <hi>Empire,</hi> had commanded him to inform and aſſure the <hi>Diet,</hi> that he will not be wanting on his part, to contribute thereunto all that is poſſible for him to do.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. having thus openly Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated the <hi>Treaty,</hi> and being no longer able to diſſemble the Matter, proceeded to thunder out his Denunciation of War againſt the <hi>States General</hi> of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces;</hi> which, for the better under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of Matters, and to what he mainly pretends, we have thought fit to take notice of <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. in his Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of War againſt the <hi>States General,</hi> publiſhed at <hi>Paris</hi> in <hi>December</hi> 1688. after he has ſet forth, <q rend="margQuotes">That he has done ſtrange things, to give Peace to <hi>Europe,</hi> he comes to the main Point, that moſt of all grieves him, <hi>viz.</hi> That the <hi>States</hi> drawing their Army together, under the Command of Prince <hi>Waldeck,</hi> had an Influence upon hindering the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal of <hi>Furſtemburgh</hi> (whom, he ſays,
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:32542:84"/>he for many Reaſons was bound to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence, and Protect) from being Inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted in the <hi>Electorate</hi> of <hi>Cologne:</hi> And for this Reaſon, and no other given, he declares War againſt them by Sea and Land, commanding his Subjects to fall upon them, forbidding Trade or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce upon pain of Death, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vokes all Paſports, and Safe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>By this we may ſee, that he bore him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf mightily upon the Election of that <hi>Cardinal,</hi> whom not only a great part of the <hi>Roman</hi> Clergy, but the <hi>Pope</hi> himſelf, looked upon as an Enemy to the <hi>Church.</hi> By which it may appear, That the <hi>French</hi> King's Pretenſions to Support him, ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded only to ſiniſter Ends, and hopes by this means to annex that <hi>Electorate</hi> to the Crown of <hi>France.</hi> Upon this Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, contrary to the Law of Nations, a Guard was ſet upon the <hi>Dutch</hi> Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſador, which obliged the <hi>States General</hi> to do the like upon Monſieur <hi>d' Avaux;</hi> by which means an Exchange was made, and either of them permitted to return. And now, though in the depth of Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the <hi>French</hi> were abroad, ravaging the Country; and although this King had not declared againſt <hi>Spain,</hi> yet a
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:32542:85"/>great Impoſt was laid on Goods, to be brought out of the <hi>Spaniſh Netherlnads.</hi> But perceiving the <hi>Confederate</hi> Armies draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing together in great Bodies, he cauſed ſeveral of the Towns he had poſſeſſed himſelf of in the <hi>Palatinate</hi> to be ſligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and many Diſmantled, or Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed; the Souldiers requiring great Summs of the Inhabitants, to ſave them from plundering. Yet many, after they had paid what was demanded, had their Goods taken away, and their Perſons miſerably miſuſed.</p>
               <p>To retaliate in ſome Meaſure theſe Proceedings, the Governour of the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Netherlands</hi> laid an Impoſt upon Wines, and Brandy; of which, when the <hi>Mareſchal</hi> complained, his Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy told him, <hi>He could not but wonder, that his Maſter having done the like on the Goods of that Country, he ſhould find any Reaſon to complain.</hi> The <hi>Emperor</hi> more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over commanded the <hi>French</hi> Envoy to leave <hi>Vienna,</hi> and the <hi>Plenepotentiary</hi> of <hi>Ratiſbone.</hi> Prince <hi>Clement</hi> of <hi>Bavaria</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to ſee the <hi>French</hi> Miniſter ſent to Complement him, becauſe he denied to give him the Style of <hi>Elector;</hi> and thoſe <hi>Canons</hi> of the <hi>Electorate</hi> were comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to leave him, and return to their
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:32542:85"/>Dignities, on pain of being Diſpoſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and of incurring Excommunicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Whereupon the <hi>Cardinal,</hi> in a Pet, made a new Proteſtation againſt the <hi>Pope</hi>'s Proceedings, touching the <hi>Electo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate</hi> of <hi>Cologne.</hi> Whilſt theſe things were doing, the <hi>French</hi> Troops quitted <hi>Heyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourn,</hi> after having Plundered it, blown up the Gates, and part of the Walls, carrying with them four Hoſtages, for the payment of Fifty thouſand Crowns laid as a Tax. They likewiſe flighted <hi>Offemburgh,</hi> demoliſhed <hi>Manheim,</hi> and burnt <hi>Oberadt,</hi> with the Villages belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to that City, declaring they would burn and deſtroy all the Places of the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> and <hi>Electorate</hi> of <hi>Mentz,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept <hi>Philipſburgh.</hi> And indeed, the whole Country at a diſtance ſeemed in the Night time for ſome ſpace, but one Fire, the Villages and Towns every where flaming; which ſhew how little <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. notwithſtanding his ſpecious Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, regards the Peace and Tranquil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of <hi>Europe,</hi> this way of burning being altogether a <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Faſhion, which is not for his Glory to imitate.</p>
               <p>Theſe Proceedings made the <hi>Swiſſes,</hi> that were in the <hi>French</hi> Service in the <hi>Electorate</hi> of <hi>Cologne,</hi> quit it, declaring,
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:32542:86"/>
                  <hi>They could not fight againſt the</hi> Empire; and thereupon the <hi>Cardinal</hi> ſent to the <hi>French</hi> Court for more Aſſiſtence to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure <hi>Bonne,</hi> the Cittadel of <hi>Liege</hi> was commanded to be blown up, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly performed, except one Baſtion, and its Works; and although the Caſtle of <hi>Montjoy</hi> Surrendered upon good Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, the Soldiers, contrary to Faith given, were made Priſoners of War; and ſlighting <hi>Huy,</hi> they blew up the Walls, and either deſtroyed, or much defaced all the Places in the <hi>Dioceſe,</hi> except <hi>Chinay,</hi> which they Garriſoned.</p>
               <p>On the 12th. of <hi>February,</hi> 1688. the <hi>States</hi> of the <hi>Empire</hi> aſſembled at <hi>Ratiſbone,</hi> having taken into their Conſideration the Miſchief the <hi>French</hi> had done, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Truce of Twenty Years, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded at <hi>Nimeguen,</hi> proceeded to give their Reſolutions, to ſtand by the <hi>Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror,</hi> and aſſiſt him with all their Forces, for the ſuppreſſing the Diſturber of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom;</hi> ſetting forth at large, their Reſentments of his Proceedings. Upon this, and the like Reſolution, the <hi>French</hi> bethought themſelves of ſlighting <hi>Hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delburgh,</hi> and <hi>Frankendale,</hi> and Fortified <hi>Mentz, Bonne,</hi> and ſuch other Places as they conceived tenable. And now the
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:32542:86"/>
                  <hi>States</hi> of <hi>Holland</hi> finding the <hi>French Men of War,</hi> and <hi>Privateers,</hi> had taken many of their Merchants, and that open Hoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities were begun, proceeded to proclaim War againſt <hi>France,</hi> and accordingly a Declaration of War was publiſhed at the <hi>Hague,</hi> and at other Places; ſetting forth, <q rend="margQuotes">That conſidering the <hi>French</hi> King had openly broke the Treaties, and Peace conluded, without any juſt Reaſon or manner of cauſe, and had declared War againſt them on ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Pretences; they find themſelves conſtrained to make a publick Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of War againſt <hi>France.</hi>
                  </q> And towards the Concluſion they ſtrictly command, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. <q rend="margQuotes">That none of the Inhabitants of this <hi>State,</hi> or any Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigner reſiding within their Territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, ſhall Tranſport any thing to <hi>France,</hi> that is prejudicial to the <hi>State.</hi> 2. That all Counterband Goods that ſhall be taken going to <hi>France,</hi> ſhall be declared Prize. 3. That good Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity ſhall be given by all Perſons carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any Goods out of theſe Countries, that they are not deſigned for <hi>France.</hi> 4. That all Ships laden with Counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band Goods, that ſhall be found on the <hi>French</hi> Coaſt, ſhall be taken for good
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:32542:87"/>Prize. 5. That all Ships ought to have lawful Paſports. 6. The <hi>Men of War</hi> not to moleſt any Ships, having ſuch Paſports, and not bound with Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terband Goods to the Ports of <hi>France.</hi> 7. That ſuch as ſhall be offending here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, ſhall be puniſhed with Confiſcation of Ship and Goods. 8. That the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders of the Ships of <hi>War,</hi> ſhall pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually govern themſelves in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, according to the Treaties made in relation thereto with other Kings, Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and States. 9. That the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralties ſhall have the Cognizances of theſe Offences. 10, 11, 12. The Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney ariſing by ſuch Confiſcations, ſhall be diſpoſed of, as has been practiſed in like Caſes; and as to the Seizures, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Former <hi>Placates</hi> to be obſerved. 13. None of the Inhabitants of this <hi>State,</hi> ſhall Inſure any <hi>French</hi> Ships or Goods, or others bound to <hi>France,</hi> on Penalty of forfeiting the Summ Inſurred.</q>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Confederates</hi> being early Abroad this <hi>Spring,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> had not ſo good Succeſs as the former. For the <hi>Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denburgh</hi> Forces defeated a great Party of the Garriſon of <hi>Nuis,</hi> as likewiſe gave another Defeat to the <hi>Chevalier de Sourdis,</hi> who came with a ſtrong Party to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:32542:87"/>of the other, killing a great number in the Fight and purſuit, gaining a good Booty. Upon theſe Defeats, the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles of <hi>Lintz, Nuis, Zons, &amp;c.</hi> ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, and the <hi>French</hi> ſet Fire to, and blew up many places they deſpaired to keep; which ſo aſtoniſhed the Cardinal of <hi>Furſtemburgh,</hi> that he attempted to leave <hi>Bonne,</hi> ſending, in order thereto, his beſt Moveables to <hi>Mentz.</hi> Nor was <hi>Lewis the Great</hi> free from Apprehenſions of his own Subjects Revolting, which made him draw his Guards near his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and publiſh an Ordinance for the hindering the meeting of the <hi>New Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts</hi> in ſeveral Provinces of his Kingdom, and for the putting in Execution the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict</hi> of <hi>October</hi> 1685. and to raiſe the Ban and Arrear Ban of the Iſle of <hi>France;</hi> many ſmall Skirmiſhes happened on the <hi>Frontiers</hi> during the beginning of the Campagne; the <hi>French</hi> attempting to Surprize and Burn <hi>Bopert,</hi> were beaten off, and many of them killed; and ſoon after ſome of the Troops of the <hi>Land-grave</hi> of <hi>Heſſe,</hi> Surprized the Garriſon of <hi>Lintz,</hi> and cut them off. And notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding <hi>Liege</hi> had purchaſed a Neutra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trality, at the coſt of One hundred and thirty thouſand Crowns, and the ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:32542:88"/>their <hi>Cittadel</hi> to be demoliſhed; the <hi>French,</hi> who ſcorn to be Slaves to their Words or Oaths, ranged up and down in their Country, and gathered Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butions, under a ſlender Pretence, that the <hi>Cittadel</hi> was not demoliſhed ſo ſoon as it was agreed on by the Treaty of Neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trality, and were forced to ſhelter their Convoys, and furniſh even the Troops that were oppreſſing their Country, with ſuch Ammunition and Proviſion as they could ſpare.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Palatinate</hi> by this time growing ſomewhat too hot for the <hi>French</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion, they reſolved to doe what Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief they could before they ſhould be obliged to abandon it; and, amongſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, upon quitting <hi>Fredericksburg,</hi> they ſet it on fire, and ruined the Fortifications of <hi>Caſſel.</hi> But now the City of <hi>Liege</hi> finding the Misfortune of it's Neutrality, and being preſſed by the <hi>Emperor</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare either for the <hi>Confederates</hi> or <hi>France,</hi> (for he would allow no Neutrality,) it declared for the former, and ſecured the <hi>French</hi>-Reſident, with divers Officers and their Arms, as Hoſtages for the ſafety of their Miniſter in <hi>France.</hi> The <hi>Count de Rabenac,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> Ambaſſador, was likewiſe diſmiſſed the Court of <hi>Spain,</hi>
                  <pb n="167" facs="tcp:32542:88"/>and <hi>Furſtemburgh</hi> got into <hi>Mentz;</hi> and the <hi>French</hi> Garriſon of <hi>Straſburgh</hi> at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempting the Siege of <hi>Oberkirk,</hi> was beaten off, a Captain, with divers others, killed, and ſome of Note wounded.</p>
               <p>On the 19 of <hi>April.</hi> 1689 <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. cauſed a Declaration of War to be pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed in the City of <hi>Paris</hi> againſt the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> and ſent orders to break down all the Bridges on the River <hi>Sambre</hi> from <hi>Chaſtelet</hi> to <hi>Maubuge</hi> and ſo to <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drecy;</hi> the Garriſon of <hi>Luxemburgh</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding all the Country that depends on them, to bring in their Proviſions that exceed a Store for three Months, on great Penalties, flattering them, that after the Expiration of that time they ſhould be other ways ſupplied. But, for a brief Account of the Actions of <hi>Lew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is</hi> XIV. in his late proceedings, the <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror</hi> gives us theſe paſſages, amongſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, in his Letter to the King of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">
                     <hi>Your Serenity</hi> will have ſufficiently un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood by our former Letter how unjuſtly and treacherouſly the Crown of <hi>France,</hi> violating the Treaties of <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaila</hi> and <hi>Nimeguen,</hi> and the 20 years Truce concluded a few Years ſince, hath invaded us and the <hi>Empire</hi> at a time
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:32542:89"/>when we expected nothing leſs. But the Inormity of this Invaſion is infinitely Agravated, by the horrid Cruelties and Barbarities they continue to excerciſe in the Places they have poſſeſſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of, pillaging whole Towns and Countries, which, to preſerve them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, ſurrendered upon Articles, and afterwards payed the Contributions impoſed upon them, contrary to the Faith given them and confirmed by the King himſelf or the <hi>Dauphin,</hi> and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards deſtroying them with Fire, or Levelling the Walls and Houſes to the ground, and carrying away the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants bound as Slaves, in a manner on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly practiſed amongſt <hi>Barbarians;</hi> and forcing them with Threats of Death to follow the <hi>French</hi> Army unto other parts, not ſparing the ſtately Houſes and Palaces of Princes, which had been preſerved for Ages in the bloodieſt Wars; and not with-holding their Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious hands even from the Churches, and excerciſing many other Cruelties and Inhumanities, ſuch as are ſeldom Committed by the <hi>Turks</hi> themſelves, and which can be hardly found in any Hiſtory to be practiſed amongſt <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians;</hi> Which as they moſt deſervedly
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:32542:89"/>Excite the Hatred of all <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> againſt <hi>France,</hi> ſo they eſpecially lay a neceſſity upon us, of providing for the Safety of the <hi>Roman Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire,</hi> and of uſing all means to free it from un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard of Violences, and Oppreſſions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Thus we have the Word of an <hi>Emperor,</hi> to confirm what we have ſet forth; nor did his <hi>Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctoral Highneſs</hi> of <hi>Brandenburgh</hi> find himſelf leſs aggrieved, and in <hi>April</hi> 1689. cauſed his <hi>Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> of War to be publiſhed againſt <hi>France,</hi> in which, amongſt other things, he ſets forth, <q rend="margQuotes">That deſiring nothing more, than that the publick Tranquillity of <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> might be preſerved, and that his own Subjects might, under his Government, enjoy the Benefit of Peace; but that the <hi>French</hi> King having, againſt all Right and Juſtice, not only attacked the <hi>Roman Empire,</hi> but having likewiſe poſſeſſed himſelf of whole <hi>Circles</hi> and <hi>Provinces,</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed the ſame, in a moſt barbarous Manner, never before heard of amongſt <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> with Fire and Murthers, and other execrable Cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and threatned the Countries of <hi>Branden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh,</hi> and his <hi>Electoral Highneſs</hi>'s Subjects of <hi>Frankendale,</hi> with the ſame Inhumane Treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which he has begun even already to put in Execution, and having committed other the like Attempts upon his <hi>Electoral Highneſs,</hi> and his Allies, as well within as without the <hi>Empire,</hi> directly contrary to the Treaty of Peace and Truce, in order to the total Ruine of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Empire; His <hi>Electoral Highneſs</hi> having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to the Reſolution of the <hi>Emperor,</hi> and the <hi>Dyet</hi> at <hi>Ratisbonne,</hi> is obliged to make uſe of the Power which God and Nature have put into his Hands, and to take up Arms for the Defence of his Subjects,</q> and for the oppoſing with all
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:32542:90"/>his Force, the perfidious Attempts of <hi>France.</hi> And ſo proceeds to forbid all Commerce, upon very great Penalties.</p>
               <p>And now the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> not to be behind-hand with other Nations, the Knights, Citizens, and Burgeſſes aſſembled in Parliament, waited upon his Majeſty of Great <hi>Britain,</hi> on the 26<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>April,</hi> and preſented him an Addreſs in the <hi>Banqueting-Houſe,</hi> wherein, amongſt other things, they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, <hi>That whenever his Majeſty ſhould think fit to enter into a War againſt the</hi> French <hi>King, they would give him ſuch Aſſiſtance, in a</hi> Parliamentary <hi>Way, as might enable him (under the Protection that God Almighty has ever afforded him) to Support and go through with the ſame.</hi> To which <hi>His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty</hi> was graciouſly pleaſed to return this following Anſwer, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">I receive this Addreſs as a Mark of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence you have in me, which I take very kindly, and ſhall endeavour, in all my Actions, to confirm you in it. I aſſure you, That my own Ambition ſhall never be an Argument to incline me to engage in a War, that may expoſe the Nation either to Danger or Expenſe; but, in the preſent Caſe, I look upon the War ſo much already declared in effect by <hi>France</hi> againſt <hi>England;</hi> that it is not ſo properly an Act of Choice, as an inevitable Neceſſity in our own Defence. I ſhall only tell you, That as I have ventured my Life, and all that is dear to me, to reſcue this Nation from what it ſuffered, I am ſtill ready to do the ſame, in order to preſerve it from all its Enemies. And, as I do not doubt of ſuch an Aſſiſtance from you, as ſhall be ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to your Advice to me, to declare War a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a Powerful Enemy, ſo you may relie upon me, that no part of that which you ſhall give
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:32542:90"/>for the carrying it on with Suucce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, ſhall be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted by me to any other Uſe.</q>
               </p>
               <p>The Confederate Armies by this Time began to draw together, which made <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. haſten his Troops, and form Two Armies under the Commands of the Duke of <hi>Duras,</hi> and <hi>Mareſchal d' Humiers.</hi> Whereupon the Governour-General of the <hi>Spaniſh Netherlands,</hi> cauſed a <hi>Declaration of War</hi> to be publiſhed againſt <hi>France;</hi> wherein, after he had ſet forth the Cruelty and Injuſtice of the <hi>French</hi> King, as the others had done, he forbids all Commerce, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Upon which <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. cauſed his <hi>Declaration of War</hi> to be proclaimed againſt <hi>Spain,</hi> at <hi>Marſeilles, viz,</hi> on the 29<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>April,</hi> and proceeded to fill all the Towns of the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> that were not reduced to Aſhes, with his Soldiers, as foreſeeing the Storm that threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from ſo many Quarters of <hi>Europe;</hi> and, that ſuch <hi>Proteſtants</hi> as were willing to avoid his cruel Uſage and Extortions, might have Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to leave the Kingdom of <hi>France,</hi> their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties of <hi>Great Britain</hi> put forth a Proclamation, bearing Date the 25<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>April,</hi> for the Encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the <hi>French Proteſtants</hi> to Tranſport them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into this Kingdom, another Prohibiting the Importation of all Sorts of Manufactures, and Commodities whatſoever, of the Growth, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction, or Manufacture of <hi>France.</hi> And on the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>May,</hi> a <hi>Declaration of War</hi> was Signed, and afterwards Publiſhed, ſetting forth, <hi>The perfidious Dealing of the</hi> French <hi>King, as well in</hi> Europe <hi>as in</hi> Africa, <hi>againſt the Subjects of</hi> England, &amp;c. And whilſt theſe things were doing, News came from the Coaſt of <hi>Ireland,</hi> that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral, with a Squadron of the King of <hi>Britains</hi> Ships, had engaged and worſted Forty four Sail of the <hi>French,</hi> being double the number of the
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:32542:91"/>
                  <hi>Engliſh,</hi> as they were attempting to land Men and Arms in that Kingdom. And, to ſhew the <hi>French</hi> a farther Proof of our Naval Courage, the <hi>None-Such,</hi> a ſmall Fourth Rate Frigat o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 36 Guns, meeting off of <hi>Guernſey</hi> with two <hi>French Men of War,</hi> one of 30 Guns, and 120 Men; the other of 16 Guns, 6 Pettereroes, and 120 Men, who were bound, with about Twenty ſmall Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant Ships under their Convoy, to <hi>Newfound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> the <hi>Engliſh Man of War</hi> engaged them, but in the beginning of the Fight the Captain was killed, with the Maſter and Cook, and the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penter wounded; upon which, there being no Lieutenant on Board, the Boatſwain took upon him the Command of the Ship, and continued the Fight with that Bravery, that after a ſharp En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement of three Hours, he took both the <hi>French Men of War,</hi> and brought them into <hi>Plymouth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>During theſe Tranſactions, <hi>Rhinburgh,</hi> that had been Garriſoned with <hi>French</hi> Troops by <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal Furſtemburgh,</hi> ſurrendered to the <hi>Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates,</hi> and <hi>Keyſerwaert</hi> was blocked up. The <hi>French</hi> continued to fortifie <hi>Mentz,</hi> pulling dow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Streets of Building for their better convenienc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> on that Occaſion. Yet ſo far either Paſſion o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Fear had wrought in <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. that he was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken on the 30<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>May</hi> with an extraordinary Fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of an <hi>Ague,</hi> which held him for nine or ten Hours which made him fly to his old Refuge of taking the <hi>Jeſuits Powder,</hi> as well as their Counſels, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> latter having ever been fatal to <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> And, as if the <hi>French</hi> King had wanted Torche<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> or Bonefires for Joy of his Recovery, his Troops not ſatisfied with the Execrable Barbarities they had committed in the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> and other Places proceeded in the later end of <hi>May</hi> to lay in Aſhe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the famous Towns of <hi>Oppenheim, Worms,</hi> and
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:32542:91"/>
                  <hi>Spire;</hi> in the latter whereof, the <hi>Imperial</hi>-Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber had a long time been kept, not leaving ſo much as a Houſe ſtanding. But a party of the Garriſon of <hi>Bonne</hi> attempting to do the like to the Village of <hi>Hauff,</hi> the Country People took Arms, and falling upon them, killed about ſixty of their Number, putting the reſt to flight; and likewiſe ſeveral Parties of <hi>French</hi> Foragers, and ſuch as were ſent to make Incurſions into the Countries that neighboured on their Garriſon, were fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently defeated. And now the <hi>Moſt Chriſtian</hi> King finding himſelf hard beſet, ſought to cajole the <hi>Algerine</hi> Pirates to make a Peace with him, and fall upon the <hi>Confederates</hi> Merchants at Sea, although they had a little before ſo ſenſibly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronted him, as to ſhoot off his <hi>Conſul, &amp;c.</hi> and notwithſtanding any Propoſal, they would not hearken to any Treaty, unleſs he would redeem the <hi>French</hi> Captives, to the Number of 800, which he had demanded without any Ranſom. And when his Agent perceived this would not take, he propoſed a Truce, but that likewiſe was rejected by the <hi>Algerines.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>On the Ninth of <hi>June,</hi> the Marqueſs <hi>Choiſeul</hi> paſſed the <hi>Rhine</hi> at <hi>Hunningen,</hi> with 4000 <hi>French</hi> Horſe and Dragoons, and entered the Country of <hi>Durlach,</hi> declaring, That he came only to Forage, promiſing not to moleſt any that ſhould remain quiet in their Houſes; which the Country People relying on, thought they had nothing to fear; but they quickly found the little regard the <hi>French</hi> have to their Word: For no ſooner had they poſted themſelves in the Places they deſigned, but the Country was given up to the Diſcretion of the Soldiers, who committed the moſt outrageous Inſolencies, and Violencies, that can be imagined; So that many of the poor Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:32542:92"/>being plundered of all they had, and their perſons abuſed, were driven before the Soldiers, like Sheep or Oxon, towards <hi>Friburgh</hi> and <hi>Briſac.</hi> A few indeed eſcaped to the <hi>Black Forreſt,</hi> where ſeveral of them periſhed for Want, whilſt the <hi>French</hi> were cutting up their Corn, and deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the whole Country.</p>
               <p>During theſe Proceedings, <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. cauſed his <hi>Declaration of War</hi> againſt <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> to be publiſhed at <hi>Paris, viz.</hi> on the 28<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>June,</hi> commanding his Fleet to put again to Sea, propoſing great things to his Advantage. But as yet his Expections have been fruſtrated.</p>
               <p>The Town of <hi>Keyſerwaert</hi> being formally Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged, and cloſely preſſed by the <hi>Brandenburgh</hi> Forces, the Duke being before it in perſon, on the 25<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>June</hi> Monſieur <hi>Marcognet,</hi> the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour, Capitulated, upon Notice the <hi>German</hi> Soldiers, in Garriſon, were inclined to make Conditions for themſelves without him; and a Parly being beat, the Capitulation was Signed the next Morning; by which it was agreed, <hi>That one of the Gates ſhould be immediately delivered up; that the</hi> French <hi>Officers and Soldiers ſhould march out the Day following with Arms and Baggage,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and be Conducted to</hi> Luxemburgh, <hi>but that the</hi> Germans <hi>ſhould be at Liberty to go where they pleaſed, but not any more enter into the</hi> French <hi>Service.</hi> Whereupon moſt of them entered into the <hi>Duke</hi>'s Pay, and a great Number of <hi>French</hi> Soldiers deſerted their Army, notwithſtanding the ſevere Diſcipline to prevent it, by hanging up ſome Hundreds who had been taken going off. Nor did their Army in <hi>Flanders</hi> eſcape the angry Skies; for a violent Tempeſt happening, accompanied with extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Rains and Floods, divers Perſons periſhed, a great deal of Baggage was ſpoiled, and carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:32542:92"/>away in by the Rapidity of the Torrent, and the Mareſchal <hi>d' Humiers,</hi> who commanded in Chief, hardly eſcaped drowning. And although the <hi>French</hi> King laboured by many ſecret In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trigues and Contrivances, to widen, or keep on foot, the Differences between the King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> and Duke of <hi>Holſtein;</hi> yet by the Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of the <hi>Emperor,</hi> and <hi>Electors</hi> of <hi>Saxony</hi> and <hi>Bandenburgh,</hi> an Accomodation was made, and Signed on the Thirtieth of <hi>June,</hi> upon ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry Articles. Upon this News, upon what Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count we are yet to learn, the Duke <hi>De la Force,</hi> and the Marqueſs <hi>Vivaus,</hi> were clapped up in the <hi>Baſtile</hi> at <hi>Paris,</hi> and their Papers ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured. The Ducheſs <hi>De la Force</hi> was likewiſe ſent Priſoner to the Caſtle of <hi>Angers:</hi> And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the ſame time, a <hi>French</hi> Man of War, of Thirty ſix Guns, and Two hundred Men, was taken by two <hi>Dutch</hi> Ships, and carried into <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterdam.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Iriſh</hi> Forces Beſieging <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don-Derry,</hi> were beaten off with great Slaughter; and, amongſt others, many Principal Officers were killed, which obliged them, upon the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty's being Relieved with Proviſion, to raiſe the Siege, and retire in ſome Confuſion.</p>
               <p>The French Forces likewiſe in <hi>Catalonia</hi> were beaten by the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and upon the Approach of the Imperial Army, quitted all, or moſt of the Places they yet held in the <hi>Palatinate.</hi> And now the Storm of War threatning <hi>Montz</hi> and <hi>Bonne,</hi> the only ſtrong Places the Frence held in thoſe Parts, the Marqueſs <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xelles,</hi> Governour of the former, ſent to the Court of <hi>France</hi> to demand ſpeedy Aid; but had no other Anſwer returned him as to that particular, than, that the King had ſent the Arrear-Ban towards the
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:32542:93"/>Coaſts, and that by reaſon of ſome Diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, he muſt not expect very Powerful Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours, for that there were every where too great Occaſion for their Troops, the Enemy having never had ſuch numerous Forces in the Field, as at preſent. For at that time, the Army Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> was compoſed of 20000 <hi>Imperial</hi> Foot, and 8000 Horſe, 10000 <hi>Saxons,</hi> 8000 <hi>Lunenburghers,</hi> and 6000 of <hi>Heſſe-Caſſel.</hi> The <hi>Bavarian</hi> Army, with the Troops of <hi>Suabia</hi> 14000, with which were joined 8000 <hi>Imperialiſts</hi> under <hi>Caprapra.</hi> The Forces of the Duke of <hi>Brandenburgh</hi> amounted to 32000, thoſe of <hi>Munſter</hi> 6000, which with the 3000 <hi>Hollanders</hi> that were in that Country, and the 8000 after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſent by the Duke of <hi>Hanouer,</hi> amounted to 123000 Men, not accounting the <hi>Dutch</hi> and <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Armies in the <hi>Netherlands.</hi> Theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Forces made <hi>Lewis the Great</hi> begin to look about him more than ever, labouring with the King of <hi>Denmark</hi> to hold a Neutrality, to which he found him no ways inclinable. And the <hi>Pope's Nuntio</hi> being called Home, to prevent the <hi>Clergy</hi> flocking to him in his way, an Officer, contrary to Cuſtom, was ſent to him out of the Kingdom, and publiſhed an <hi>Ordinance,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding all the Subjects of <hi>France,</hi> whoſe Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, Children, or Brothers, are in the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of his Enemies, and the Women, whoſe Husbands are in that Service, to depart the Kingdom within the ſpace of a Month, which was, in many Places, put rigorouſly in Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>The French Troops under the Command of the Duke <hi>Duras,</hi> making an Attempt upon <hi>Heidel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh,</hi> the Regiment of <hi>Wertemburgh</hi> got oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunely into the Town, and beat them off, with
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:32542:93"/>the loſs of Three or Four hundred of their Men. And in <hi>Flanders,</hi> about Forty <hi>Engliſh</hi> Horſe meeting with a greater Number of <hi>French,</hi> kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Fifteen, and took Eight Priſoners. Theſe bad Succeſſes, one upon the Neck of another, made the <hi>French</hi> King cauſe his Orders to be publiſhed, Commanding the Inhabitants of <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan, Mezieres,</hi> and other Places, not to Sow their Ground with Corn this Year, on pain of Death, promiſing they ſhould be furniſhed other ways.</p>
               <p>It would be too tedious to mention all the Skirmiſhes that paſſed this <hi>Campaign</hi> with vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Succeſs, though moſtly to the Advantage of the Confederates: Wherefore, paſſing many over, we come to Inſtance that great Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment between the French, under the Command of the Mareſchal <hi>d' Humiers;</hi> and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Dutch,</hi> under the Command of Prince <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deck, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The French Troops Attacking the Village <hi>Forge,</hi> where Eight hundred Men were Poſted under the Command of Collonel <hi>Hodges,</hi> and Lieutenant-Collonel <hi>Goes,</hi> they bravely defended it, till ſending one Party after another on both ſides, the two Armies, in a manner, Engaged; where the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> more eſpecially, behaved themſelves with ſuch Bravery and Reſolution, that after a long and obſtinate Fight, the <hi>French</hi> gave Ground, and retired in ſome Confuſion, leaving behind them their Cannon and Ammu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition, and about Three thouſand Killed and Wounded. And the Six Battalions of Guards were for the moſt part cut off, which Loſs may be beſt gueſſed at by the following Account.</p>
               <p>Monſieur <hi>de Gelais,</hi> Mareſchal of the Camp, was killed with a Cannon-Shot, as likewiſe were
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:32542:94"/>Monſieur <hi>de Metz Tirecelin,</hi> Commiſſary of the Artillery. Killed of the Guards the Count <hi>d' Artuagan,</hi> four Captains, five Lieutenants, a Gentleman-Voluntier wounded. Three Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptains, eleven Lieutenants, the Aid-Major, and two Voluntiers of the Regiment of <hi>Campaign,</hi> the Chavalier <hi>de Colbert,</hi> Brigadier and Collonel, mortally wounded, the Lieutenant-Collonel wounded, the Major mortally wounded, two Captains killed, two Lieutenants killed, five Captains and ſeven Lieutenants wounded, the Liutenant of the Artillery wounded; of the <hi>Genſd'arms,</hi> an Exempt of the Guards wounded; of <hi>Vilpians</hi> Regiment of Horſe killed one Captain, wounded a Cornet and Aid-Major; of <hi>Greders</hi> Regiment of Foot, killed one Captain and Aid-Major, wounded two Captains, one Aid-Major, and a Lieutenant, ſeveral of the wounded dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their Wounds ſoon after the Battel. This blow greatly allarmed the Court of <hi>France,</hi> and might have put <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. into another Fit of his Ague, had not cordial News come from <hi>Rome,</hi> of the Death of <hi>Pope Innocent</hi> XI. upon which, he immediately ſent away the Count <hi>de Chaulms.</hi> his Ambaſſador; and the <hi>French</hi> Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals, ſuch as he would truſt with his Intereſt, prepared to follow him, in order to make his Party in the Election of a new <hi>Pope.</hi> But when they came to <hi>Rome,</hi> their Admiſſion into the <hi>Conclave</hi> was diſputed, till ſuch time the <hi>French</hi> King ſhould relinquiſh his Pretenſions to the <hi>franchiſes,</hi> which at laſt was agreed to be done, during the time of Election. But it ſo fell out, that neither the <hi>French</hi> Intereſt nor Gold was ſo Powerful as heretofore; for, after ſome Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt amongſt the Factions, Cardinal <hi>Ottoboni,</hi> a Noble <hi>Venetian,</hi> was Elected, and Confirmed
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:32542:94"/>
                  <hi>Pope</hi> by the Name of <hi>Alexander</hi> VIII.</p>
               <p>The City of <hi>Mentz</hi> having been violently At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacked by the Confederates, under the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> and others; and the Duke <hi>Duras</hi> in vain watching an Opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to relieve it, with an Army of between Six<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen and Eighteen thouſand Men; the Beſieged beat a Parly, and on the Eighth of <hi>Auguſt</hi> Hoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges were exchanged, and on the Ninth the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitulation was Signed; in purſuance whereof the Place was Surrendered, and the <hi>French</hi> Garriſon marched out, <hi>viz.</hi> 4500 Foot, 400 Dragoons, 280 Horſe, beſides ſix or 700 Foot, that went in ſmall parties with the Baggage, being the Remainder of 10000 that were in Garriſon at the beginning of the Siege. The reduction of this ſtrong Place, that had coſt ſo great a Summ in Fortifying, and in which ſuch confidence had been repoſed, did not a little ſtartle the Court of <hi>France;</hi> and, as is uſual upon ſuch Emergen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, occaſioned the change of a great many Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of State. And what heightned the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſternation more, was a fear of a General Revolt of the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> of that Kingdom, ſeeing many of them forced their Way through the French Barriers of <hi>Languedock, Provence,</hi> and <hi>Dauphin,</hi> and brought Terrour upon <hi>Savoy,</hi> (the only ſtickling Prince for <hi>France,</hi>) joining with others in the Valleys of <hi>Piemont, Lucern, &amp;c.</hi> which ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged the French King to keep ſtrong Guards on the Frontier Places of <hi>Dauphin:</hi> And ſome French Troops attempting to burn the Corn near <hi>Ghent,</hi> were ſo warmly received by the Cannon of the Town, and an Ambuſhment laid in a hollow Way, that moſt of them were cut off. And now perceiving they muſt quit the <hi>Electorate</hi> of <hi>Trier,</hi> they reſolved to uſe it with the ſame Civility
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:32542:95"/>they had done the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> burning ten Towns, beſide what they had formerly Conſumed, and laying that fruitful Country Waſte like a Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs; and farther proceeded to burn <hi>Franken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dale, Neuſtadt, Lubeſheim, Petterſheim, Dirmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtheim, Wachenheim,</hi> with ſeveral other Places, and a great many Villages in <hi>Houſdurgh.</hi> Which <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nchriſtian</hi> Proceedings demonſtrated their Power to be of ſhort Durance in thoſe Countries.</p>
               <p>The City of <hi>Bonne,</hi> Fortified by the Care and Diligence of Cardinal <hi>Furſtemberg,</hi> at the extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Charge of the <hi>French</hi> King, having been a conſiderable time Beſieged by the <hi>Elector</hi> of <hi>Brandenburgh,</hi> and making a ſtout Reſiſtance, deſpairing of Relief, was conſtrained on the 10th. of <hi>October</hi> to beat a Parly, and ſent out three Officers to treat about Articles of Surrender, which were finally concluded; and Signed on the 12th. under Seventeen Heads, conſiderably Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Garriſon; and the ſame Day, Three <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>undred Men of the Troops of <hi>Brandenburgh, Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and <hi>Munſter,</hi> took Poſſeſſion of one of the Gates of the Town, and on the Fifteenth the Garriſon, which at the beginning of the Siege con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted of 7000 Men, marched out to the number of 3500, and 1500 remained ſick and wounded in the Town. The Governour Count <hi>Alsfelt,</hi> was carried out in a Litter, and all the Stores and Cannon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> were delivered up to the <hi>Elector.</hi> So that by the Loſs of this Town, the <hi>French</hi> loſt their footing in thoſe <hi>Parts,</hi> and began to think of going into Winter-Quarters, after having in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damaged thoſe Countries more than Forty milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons can repair, in one <hi>Campaign.</hi> Whereupon, to be rid of ſo cruel and waſtful a People, the <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror</hi> publiſhed his <hi>Avocatoria,</hi> commanding all the <hi>French</hi> to depart out of his Dominions; when,
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:32542:95"/>on the other hand, <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. lay great Taxes to raiſe Money for his carrying on the next <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paign.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We might enlarge upon many other Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, to diſplay this Ambitious and Bloodthirſty <hi>Monarch,</hi> who has been ſo long the Troubler of <hi>Europe,</hi> as his League with the Empire, his ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciting them to make no Peace, and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raging them to ſtand off, by promiſes of the powerful Diverſions he intends to make in the <hi>Weſtern</hi> Parts. Under the favour of which, his Ambaſſador at the <hi>Port</hi> inſinuates what they have loſt in the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> as we find it ſet forth at large in the <hi>Emperor</hi>'s Declaration, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But we think we have ſaid enough, to give the World a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of this great <hi>Leviathan,</hi>
                  <q>
                     <l>Who floats on Seas of Blood, with vaſt deſire</l>
                     <l>To out-brave Heav'n, and ſet the World on fire.</l>
                     <l>But Heaven's Bolts hit ſure, whene'er they're aim'd,</l>
                     <l>And oft have Monſters, full as mighty, tam'd.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
